<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0275">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0073a22"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛 <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n04"/>住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>其有說言<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n05"/>『大力』者，其唯難陀，此是正說。其有說言『最端<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n06"/>
              政』者，其唯難陀，是則正說。其有說言『愛欲重』者，其唯難陀，是則正說。諸比丘！而今難陀關閉根門，飲食知量，初夜、後夜精勤修習，正智成就，堪能盡壽，純一滿淨，梵行清白。      
                        彼難陀比丘關閉根門故，若
            <pb ed="T" n="0073b"/>眼見色，不取色相，不取隨形好。若諸眼根增不律儀，無明闇障，世間貪<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n07"/>愛、惡不善法，不漏其心。生諸律儀，防護於眼、耳、鼻、舌、身、意根。生諸律儀，是名『難陀比丘關閉根門』。飲食知量者，難陀比丘於食繫數，不自高、不放逸、不著色、不著莊嚴，支身而已，任其所得，為止飢渴。修梵行故，故起苦覺令息<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n08"/>滅，未起苦覺令不起故。成其崇向故，氣力安樂。無<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n09"/>聞獨住故，如人乘車，塗以膏油，不為自高、……（乃至）莊嚴，為載運故。又如塗瘡，不貪其味，為息苦故。如是，善男子難陀知量而食，……（乃至）無<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n09"/>聞獨住，是名『難陀知量而食』。彼善男子難陀初夜、後夜精勤修業者：彼難陀晝則經行，坐禪，除去陰障，以淨其身。於初夜時經行，坐禪，除去陰障，以淨其身。於中夜時房外洗足，入於室中，右脅而臥，屈膝累足，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n10"/>係念明<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n11"/>想，作起覺想。於後夜時徐覺徐起，經行，坐禪。是名『善男子難陀初夜、後夜精勤修<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n12"/>集』。彼善男子難陀勝念正知者：是善男子難陀觀察東方，一心正念，安住觀察。觀察南、西、北方，亦復如是，一心正念，安住觀察。如是觀者，世間貪<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n13"/>愛、惡不善法，不漏其心。彼善男子難陀覺諸受起，覺諸受住，覺諸受滅，正念而住，不令散亂。覺諸想起，覺諸想住，覺諸想滅，覺諸覺起，覺諸覺住，覺諸覺滅，正念<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0073n14"/>心住，不令散亂。是名『善男子難陀正念正智成就』。是故──諸比丘！──當作是學：關閉根門。如善男子難陀飲食知<pb ed="T" n="0073b"/>量。如善男子難陀初夜、後夜精勤修業。如善男子難陀正念正智成就。如善男子難陀如教授難陀法，亦當持是為其餘人說。</p>
        </q>
        <p>時有異比丘而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0275a">
            <l>善關閉根門<caesura/>正念攝心住</l>
            <l>飲食知節量<caesura/>覺知諸心相</l>
            <l>善男子難陀<caesura/>世尊之所歎</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
