<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 012. It is found in the 佛說戒德香經 Sutra at T.02.0116.0507.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0116.0507b14">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0116.0507b14"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時佛遊舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
        <p>時賢者阿難閑居獨思。世有三香。一曰根香。二曰枝香。三曰華香。是三品香唯隨風香不能逆風。寧有雅香隨風逆風者乎。</p>
        <p>賢者阿難獨處思惟於義所歸不知所趣。即從坐起往詣佛所。稽首<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n08"/>佛足下<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n09"/>長跪叉手<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n10"/>而白佛言。</p>
        <p>我獨處思惟。世有三香。一曰根香。二曰枝香。三曰華香。此三品香唯能隨風不能逆風。寧有雅香隨風逆風者乎。</p>
        <p>佛告阿難。善哉善哉。誠如汝問。有香真正隨風逆風。</p>
        <p>阿難白佛。願聞其<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n11"/>香</p>
        <p>佛言。若於郡國縣邑村落。有善男子善女人。修行十善身不殺盜<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n12"/>淫。口不妄言兩舌惡口綺語。意不嫉<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n13"/>妬恚癡。孝順父母奉事<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n14"/>三尊。仁慈道德威儀禮節。東方無數沙門梵志歌頌其德。南西北方四維上下沙門梵志咸歌其德。某郡國土縣邑村落。有善<pb ed="T" n="0507c"/>男子善女人。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n15"/>奉行十善敬事三寶。孝順仁慈道德恩義不失禮節。是香名曰隨風逆風靡不周。照十方宣德一切蒙賴。</p>
        <p>佛時頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>雖有美香花<caesura/>不能逆風熏</l>
          <l>不息名栴檀<caesura/>眾雨一切香</l>
          <l>志性能和雅<caesura/>爾乃逆風香</l>
          <l>正士名丈夫<caesura/>普熏于十方</l>
          <l>木<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n16"/>蜜及栴檀<caesura/>青蓮諸雨香</l>
          <l>一切此眾香<caesura/>戒香最無上</l>
          <l>是等清淨<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n17"/>者<caesura/>所行無放逸</l>
          <l>不知魔徑路<caesura/>不見所歸趣</l>
          <l>此道至永安<caesura/>此道最無上</l>
          <l>所獲斷穢源<caesura/>降伏絕魔網</l>
          <l>用上佛道堂<caesura/>昇無窮之慧</l>
          <l>以此宣<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n18"/>經義<caesura/>除去一切弊</l>
        </lg>
        <p>佛告阿難。是香所布<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n19"/>不礙須彌山川天地。不礙四種地水火風。通達八極上下亦然。無窮之界咸歌其德。一身不殺<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n20"/>生。世世長壽。其命無<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n21"/>橫。不盜竊者。世世富饒又不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n22"/>妄遺財寶。常存施為道根。不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n23"/>婬色者。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n24"/>人不犯<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n25"/>妻。所在化生蓮華之中。不妄言者。口氣香好言<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n26"/>輒信之。不兩舌者。家常和合無<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n27"/>有別離。不惡口者。其舌常好言辭辯通。不綺<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n28"/>語者。人聞其言莫不諮受宣用為珍。不嫉妬者。世世所生眾人所敬。不瞋恚者。世世端正人見歡<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n29"/>喜。除愚癡者。所生智慧靡不諮請。捨于邪見常住正道。從行所得各自然生。故當棄邪從其真妙。</p>
        <p>佛說如是。時諸比丘聞之歡喜。作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
