<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1073">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0278c08"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時尊者阿難獨一靜處，作是思惟：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>有三種香，順風而熏，不能逆風。何等為三？謂根香、莖香、華香。或復有香，順風熏，亦逆風熏，亦順風、逆風熏耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>作是念已，晡時從禪覺，往詣佛所，稽首佛足，退住一面，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>世尊！我獨一靜處，作是思惟：<q who="anando">有三種香，順風而熏，不能逆風。何等為三？謂根香、莖香、華香。或復有香，順風熏，逆風熏，亦順風、逆風熏耶？</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告阿難：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>如是，如是，有三種香，順風熏，不能逆風，謂根香、莖香、華香。阿難！亦有香，順風熏，逆風熏，順風、逆風熏。阿難！順風熏，逆風熏，順風、逆風熏者。阿難！有善男子、善女人，在所城邑、聚落成就真實法，盡形壽不殺生、不偷盜、不邪婬、不妄語、不飲酒。如是善男子、善女人，八方上下，崇善士夫，無不稱歎言：<q who="gotamo">某方、某聚落善男子、善女人持戒清淨，成真實法，盡<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0278n09"/>形壽不殺、……（乃至）不飲酒。</q>阿難！是名有香，順風熏，逆風熏，順風、逆風熏。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1073a">
            <l>非根莖華香<caesura/>能逆風而熏</l>
            <l>唯有善士女<caesura/>持戒清淨香<pb ed="T" n="0279a"/>
            </l>
            <l>逆順滿諸方<caesura/>無不普聞知</l>
            <l>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n01"/>多迦羅<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n02"/>栴檀<caesura/>優鉢羅末利</l>
            <l>如是比諸香<caesura/>戒香最為上</l>
            <l>栴檀等諸香<caesura/>所熏少分限</l>
            <l>唯有戒德香<caesura/>流熏上昇天</l>
            <l>斯等淨戒香<caesura/>不放逸正受</l>
            <l>正智等解脫<caesura/>魔道莫能入</l>
            <l>是名安隱道<caesura/>是道則清淨</l>
            <l>正向妙禪定<caesura/>斷諸魔結縛</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，尊者阿難聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
