<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 012. It is found in the 佛說戒香經 Sutra at T.02.0117.0508.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0117.0508a10">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0117.0508a10"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>如是我聞。一時佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。與大比丘眾俱。</p>
        <p>爾時尊者阿難來詣佛所。到已頭而禮足。合掌恭敬而白佛言。世尊。我有少疑欲當啟問。唯願世尊為我解說。我見世間有三種香。所謂根香花香子香。此三種香遍一切處。有風而聞。無風亦聞。其香云何。</p>
        <p>爾時世尊告尊者阿難。勿作是言。謂此三種之香。遍一切處有風而聞無風亦聞。此三種香有風無風遍一切處而非得聞。阿難。汝今欲聞普遍香者。應當諦聽。為汝宣說。</p>
        <p>阿難白佛言。世尊。我今樂聞。唯願宣說。</p>
        <p>佛告阿難。有風無風香遍十方者。世間若有近事男近事女。持佛淨戒行諸善法。謂不殺不盜不婬不妄及不飲酒。是近事男近事女。如是戒香遍聞十方。而彼十方咸皆稱讚。而作是言。於某城中有如是近事男女。持佛淨戒行諸善法。謂不殺不盜不婬不妄及不飲酒等。具此戒法。是人獲如是之香。有風無風遍聞十方。咸皆稱讚而得愛敬。</p>
        <p>
          <pb ed="T" n="0508b"/>爾時世尊。而說頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="7">
          <l>世間所有諸花果<caesura/>乃至沈檀龍麝香</l>
          <l>如是等香非遍聞<caesura/>唯聞戒香遍一切</l>
          <l>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0508n02"/>旃檀欝金與蘇合<caesura/>優鉢羅并摩隷花</l>
          <l>如是諸妙花香中<caesura/>唯有戒香而最上</l>
          <l>所有世間沈檀等<caesura/>其香微少非遍聞</l>
          <l>若人持佛淨戒香<caesura/>諸天普聞皆愛敬</l>
          <l>如是具足清淨戒<caesura/>乃至常行諸善法</l>
          <l>是人能解世間縛<caesura/>所有諸魔常遠離</l>
        </lg>
        <p>爾時尊者阿難及比丘眾。聞佛語已。歡喜信受。禮佛而退。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
