<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 013. It is found in the 四分律 Vinaya at T.22.1428.0797.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T22.1428.0797b03">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t22.1428.0797b03"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">爾時世尊。化此千比丘已便作是念。我先許瓶沙王請。若我成佛得一切智。先來至羅閱城。我今應往見瓶沙王。即正衣服。將大比丘千人。皆是舊學螺髻梵志。皆已得定調柔永得解脫。從摩竭國界遊化漸至杖林中。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊。於杖林中善住尼拘律樹王下坐。時瓶沙王。聞沙門瞿曇出自釋種出家學道。將千弟子遊行摩竭界。皆是舊學螺髻梵志。皆已得定調柔永得解脫。從摩竭界遊行來至杖林中。止善住尼拘律樹王下坐。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">彼沙門瞿曇有大名稱。靡所不聞。所謂名稱者。如來至真等正覺明行足為善逝世間解無上士調御丈夫天人師佛世尊。於天及世間久魔若魔天及梵天眾沙門婆羅門眾中。自知得神通智證。常自娛樂。與人說法。上中下言悉善。義味深邃。具足演布。修諸梵行善哉乃得見如是阿羅漢。我今寧可自往見大沙門瞿曇。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>時王瓶沙。駕萬二千乘車。將八萬四千人前後圍繞。以王威勢出羅閱城。欲見世尊。時王瓶沙。往杖林中。齊車所至處。即下車步進入林。遙見世尊顏貌殊特猶如紫金。便發歡喜心。於如來所前頭面禮足已在一面坐。時摩竭國人。或有禮足而坐者。或有舉手相問訊而坐者。或有稱姓名而坐者。或有叉手合掌向如來而坐者。或有默然而坐者。時摩竭國人作是念。為大沙門從欝鞞羅迦<pb ed="T" n="0797c"/>葉學梵行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT22p0794n14"/>耶。為欝鞞羅迦葉并弟子眾從大沙門瞿曇學梵行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT22p0794n14"/>耶。時世尊。知其國人心中所念。即以偈向欝鞞羅迦葉說。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>汝等見何變<caesura/>捨諸事火具</l>
          <l>吾今問迦葉<caesura/>云何捨火具</l>
        </lg>
        <p>爾時迦葉。復以偈報世尊言。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>飲食諸美味<caesura/>愛欲女及祀</l>
          <l>我見如<anchor type="variant" n="fnT22p0797n06"/>是垢<caesura/>故捨事火具</l>
        </lg>
        <p>世尊。復以偈問迦葉言。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>飲食諸美味<caesura/>於中無所樂</l>
          <l>天上及世間<caesura/>今說樂何處</l>
        </lg>
        <p>迦葉。復以偈報世尊言。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>我見迹休息<caesura/>三界無所礙</l>
          <l>不異不可異<caesura/>不樂事火祀</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">時摩竭國人復生是念。大沙門說二偈。欝鞞羅迦葉亦說二偈。我等猶故未別。為大沙門從迦葉受學耶。為迦葉及弟子從大沙門受學耶。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>時世尊。知摩竭國人心中所念已。告迦葉言。汝起為吾扇背。答言爾。時迦葉受佛教已。即從坐起上昇虛空。還下禮世尊足。以手摩捫如來足。以口嗚之自稱姓字。世尊是我師。我是弟子。即持扇在如來後而扇。時摩竭國人自相謂言。大沙門瞿曇。不從迦葉學梵行。迦葉及弟子眾。從大沙門瞿曇學梵行。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>爾時世尊。知摩竭國人無有疑故。漸次為說法。勸令發歡喜心。所謂法者。布施持戒生天之法。呵欲不淨。讚歎出離為樂。</p>
        <p>時摩竭國人瓶沙王為首。八萬四千人十二那由他天。諸塵垢盡得法眼淨。<pb ed="T" n="0798a"/>見法得法成就諸法自知得果證。前白佛言。我等歸依佛法僧。聽為優波塞。盡形壽不殺生。乃至不飲酒。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
