<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1074">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0279a12"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在摩竭提國人間遊行，與千比丘俱，皆是古昔<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n04"/>縈髮出家，皆得阿羅漢，諸漏已盡，所作已作，捨諸重擔，逮得己利，盡諸有結，正智，善解脫，到<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n05"/>善建立<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n06"/>支提<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n07"/>杖林中住。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>摩竭提王<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n08"/>瓶沙聞世尊摩竭提國人間遊行，至善建立<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n06"/>支提杖林中住，與諸小王、群臣、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n09"/>羽從，車萬二千乘，馬萬八千步 ，逐眾無數。摩竭提婆羅門長者悉皆從王出王舍城，詣世尊所，恭敬供養。到於道口，下車步進，及於內門，除去五飾，脫冠却蓋，除扇去劍<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n10"/>刀，脫革屣。到於佛前整衣服，偏露右肩，為佛作禮，右遶三匝，自稱姓名，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bimbisaro">
          <p>世尊！我是摩竭提王瓶沙。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告瓶沙：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>如是，大王！汝是瓶沙。可就此坐，隨其所安。</p>
        </q>
        <p>時瓶沙王重禮佛足，退坐一面。諸王、大臣、婆羅門居士悉禮佛足，次第而坐。時<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n11"/>欝鞞羅迦葉亦在座中。時摩竭提婆羅門長者作是念：</p>
        <q who="magadhiko">
          <p>為大沙門從欝鞞<pb ed="T" n="0279b"/>羅迦葉所修梵行耶，為欝鞞羅迦葉於大沙門所修梵行耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊知摩竭提婆羅門長者心之所念，即說偈而問言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1074a">
            <l>欝鞞羅迦葉<caesura/>於此見何利</l>
            <l>棄汝先所奉<caesura/>事火等眾事</l>
            <l>今可說其義<caesura/>捨事火之<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n12"/>由</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>欝鞞迦葉說偈白佛：</p>
        <q who="uruvelakassapo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1074b">
            <l>錢財等滋味<caesura/>女色五欲果</l>
            <l>觀察未來受<caesura/>斯皆大垢穢</l>
            <l>是故悉棄捨<caesura/>先諸奉火事</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊復說偈問言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1074c">
            <l>汝不著世間<caesura/>錢財五色味</l>
            <l>復何捨天人<caesura/>迦葉隨義說</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>迦葉復以偈答世尊言：</p>
        <q who="uruvelakassapo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1074d">
            <l>見道離有餘<caesura/>寂滅無餘跡</l>
            <l>無所有不著<caesura/>無異趣異道</l>
            <l>是故悉棄捨<caesura/>先修奉火事</l>
            <l>大會等受持<caesura/>奉事於水火</l>
            <l>愚癡<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0279n13"/>沒於中<caesura/>志求解脫道</l>
            <l>盲無智慧目<caesura/>向生老病死</l>
            <l>不見於正路<caesura/>永離生死道</l>
            <l>今始因世尊<caesura/>得見無為道</l>
            <l>大龍所說力<caesura/>得度於彼岸</l>
            <l>牟尼廣濟度<caesura/>安慰無量眾</l>
            <l>今始知瞿曇<caesura/>真諦超出者</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>佛復說偈歎迦葉言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1074e">
            <l>善哉汝迦葉<caesura/>先非惡思量</l>
            <l>次第分別求<caesura/>遂至於勝處</l>
          </lg>
          <p>汝今──迦葉！──當安慰汝徒眾之心。</p>
        </q>
        <p>時欝鞞羅<pb ed="T" n="0279c"/>迦葉即入正受，以神足力向於東方，上昇虛空，作四種神變：行、住、坐、臥。入火三昧，舉身洞然：青、黃、赤、白、頗梨紅色。身上出水，身下出火，還燒其身；身上出水，以灌其身；或身上出火，以燒其身；身下出水，以灌其身。如是種種現化神通息已，稽首佛足，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="uruvelakassapo">
          <p>世尊！佛是我師，我是弟子。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>我是汝師，汝是弟子。隨汝所安，復座而坐。</p>
        </q>
        <p>時欝鞞羅迦葉還復故坐。爾時摩竭提婆羅門長者作是念：</p>
        <q who="magadhiko">
          <p>欝鞞羅迦葉定於大沙門所修行梵行。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，摩竭提王瓶沙及諸婆羅門長者聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
