<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 013. It is found in the 方廣大莊嚴經 Sutra at T.03.0187.0612.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T03.0187.0612c06">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t03.0187.0612c06"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時世尊從波羅奈國與優<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0612n02"/>婁頻螺迦葉兄弟三人及千羅漢。至摩伽陀國。</p>
        <p>時頻婆娑羅王久聞菩薩得成佛道。巨身丈六紫磨金色。三十二相八十種好。十號具足已得知見。成就五眼證獲六通。梵釋四王皆悉奉事。今入我國心甚歡喜。吾本共要成佛相度。乃不忽遺從我所願。即勅國內嚴淨道路。王乘寶車。大臣百官前後導從。千乘萬騎出城迎佛。爾時世尊近王舍城在遮越林於大樹下千比丘眾圍遶而坐。王遙見佛如星中月。如日初出。既如帝釋。亦似梵王處於天宮。儼若金山巍巍超絕。王心歡喜下車步進。去五威儀稽首禮佛。自稱其號作如是言。久服尊德欽渴積時。如來即以梵音慰問王言。大王。四大常安隱不。統理人務無乃勞耶。王曰蒙祐幸得安隱。</p>
        <p>爾時頻婆娑羅王及諸臣民。咸覩迦葉於佛邊坐。心自念言。迦葉耆舊眾仙之宗。豈應棄道作佛弟子。為是佛師為師佛乎。佛知其意。即以偈頌問迦葉言。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>汝常祀山川<caesura/>歸依水火風</l>
          <l>日月眾梵天<caesura/>夙夜勤精進</l>
          <l>事來幾何時<caesura/>其心無懈廢</l>
          <l>汝所奉神祇<caesura/>寧有致福不</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <pb ed="T" n="0613a"/>爾時迦葉以偈答曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>自念祠祀來<caesura/>已經八十載</l>
          <l>風水火梵天<caesura/>山川及日月</l>
          <l>夙夜常精進<caesura/>祈心不懈廢</l>
          <l>畢竟無所獲<caesura/>值佛乃得安</l>
        </lg>
        <p>說是偈已。王及群臣國中人民。乃知迦葉為佛弟子。佛告迦葉。汝起宜應現汝羅漢神通。迦葉即時承佛教已。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0613n01"/>踊在虛空身上出火身下出水。或身上出水其身不濡。或身下出火其身不灼。飛行虛空七現七隱。入地如水履水如地。穿過須彌無所罣礙。於佛前地。西沒東現。東沒西現。南沒北現。北沒南現。既變化已還於佛前。長跪叉手而白佛言。我是弟子佛是我師。王及臣民重明迦葉是佛弟子。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p> 爾時世尊告頻婆娑羅王言。大王。色是無常苦空無我。受想行識亦是無常苦空無我。色如聚沫不可撮摩。受如水泡不得久立。行如芭蕉中無有堅想。如所夢為虛妄見。識如幻化從顛倒起。三界不實一切無常。大王。有此國來為幾何時。王言。有此國來七百餘代。所領之王盡識以不。答曰。知吾父耳。佛言。世間須臾<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0611n06"/>惟道可恃。應修來福無為空過。大王當知。如人生時。雖因父母而生其身。不由父母招其果報。善惡美醜先業所為。若造諸善命終之後。生天人中十方佛前。若造諸惡。命終之後生於地獄餓鬼畜生。一切諸法緣合即生緣散即滅。<pb ed="T" n="0613b"/>大王當知。無明緣行。行緣識。識緣名色。名色緣六處。六處緣觸。觸緣受。受緣愛。愛緣取。取緣有。有緣生。生緣老死憂悲苦惱。大王。無明滅故則行滅。行滅故則識滅。識滅故則名色滅。名色滅故則六處滅。六處滅故則觸滅。觸滅故則受滅。受滅故則愛滅。愛滅故則取滅。取滅故則有滅。有滅故則生滅。生滅故則老死滅。老死滅故則憂悲苦惱滅。大王。十二因緣盡坦然。無跡猶如虛空。分別本無逮得法忍。</p>
        <p>說是法時八萬四千諸天及人。遠塵離垢得法眼淨。無央數眾發阿耨多羅三藐三菩提心。爾時頻婆娑羅王得法眼淨。欣然請佛願受五戒大臣百官國內人民。皆悉歸佛亦受五戒。既受戒已即從座起。頂禮佛足而白佛言。世尊。乃能棄捨轉輪王位出家為道。我於昔日輙先奉請。若得道時願前見度我。於今者宿願成滿。幸蒙佛恩得履道跡。國務殷繁比更親奉。王及群臣遶佛三匝辭退而去。王至宮已群臣上賀。古昔諸王悉不見佛。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0611n06"/>惟獨大王得值如來。王益欣喜復慰群臣。卿等夙福今幸遇佛出興於世。因勅後宮妃嬪婇女及國內人民。長修齋戒盡令奉法。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
