<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 016. It is found in the 賢愚經•無惱指鬘品 Sutra at T.04.0202.0423.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T04.0202.0423b06">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t04.0202.0423b06"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>如是我聞。一時佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>於時國王名波斯匿王。有輔相。聰明巨富。其婦懷妊。生一男兒。形貌端正。容體殊絕。於時輔相。見兒歡喜。即召相師。令占相之。相師看見。懷喜而言。是兒福相。人中挺特。聰明智辯。有踰人之德。父聞遂喜。勅為作字。相師問言。兒受胎來。有何異事。輔相答言。其母素性。不能良善。懷妊<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n12"/>已來。倍更異常。心性恭順。樂宣人德。慈矜苦厄。不喜說過。相師言曰。此是兒志。當為立字。號阿舋賊奇。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n13"/>晉言無惱。兒漸長大。雄壯絕倫。有力士之力。一人敵千。騰接飛鳥。走疾奔馬。其父輔相。甚愛念之。</p>
        <p>於<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n14"/>是國中。有一婆羅門。聰明博達。多聞廣識。有五百弟子。追逐隨學。爾時輔相。即將其<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n15"/>子。往<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n16"/>囑及之。令其學問。婆羅門可之。受持教<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n17"/>授。阿舋賊奇。夙夜勤業。一日諮受。勝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n18"/>餘<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n19"/>終年。學未經久。普悉通達。婆羅門師。異常待遇。行來進止。每與<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n20"/>是俱。及諸同學。傾意瞻敬。</p>
        <p>爾時婆羅門師婦。見其端正才姿挺<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n21"/>邈過踰人表。懷情色著。愛不去意。然諸弟子。與共<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n22"/>周<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n23"/>迴。行止不獨。無緣與語。有心不遂。常以歎悒。會有檀越。來請其師及諸弟子。三月一時。婆羅門師。內與婦議。我今<pb ed="T" n="0423c"/>當行受請三月。當留一人經<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n24"/>紀於後。時婦內喜。密自懷計。白婆羅門。是事應爾。後家理重。宜須才能。可留無惱<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n16"/>囑以後事。時婆羅門。即勅無惱。我今赴彼檀越之請。後事總多。須人料理。卿<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n25"/>著才能。為吾營後。無惱受教。即住不行。師及徒眾。引<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n26"/>導而去。其婦怡悅欣喜無量。極自莊飾。多作姿媚。與共談語。嬈動其意。無惱志固。無心相從。欲心轉盛。實意語之。我相欽愛。由來有素。但<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n27"/>逼眾人。有懷未發。汝師臨去。吾故相留。今既獨靜。當從我意。無惱曉謝語言。我梵志法。不婬師婦。若當違犯非婆羅門。寧交取死。終不為此。於時師婦。望重違心。慚愧瞋憤。復作密計。候師垂至。挽裂衣裳。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n28"/>爴破其面。塵土坌身。憔悴臥地。無所言<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n29"/>語。時婆羅門師徒俱到。師即入內。見婦色狀。即問其故。何緣乃爾。婦垂泣言。不足問也。時婆羅門。重更問之。汝有何事。當相告語。云何不說。婦啼而言。汝所欽<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n30"/>美。阿舋賊奇。自汝去後。常見侵凌。我適不從。抴裂我衣。壞我身首。汝畜弟子。云何乃爾。婆羅門聞。甚懷恚忿。語其婦言。此無惱者。力敵千人。輔相之子。種族強盛。雖欲治之。宜當以漸。</p>
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n31"/>詮謀是已。往見無惱。隨宜方便。而慰<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n32"/>喻<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0423n33"/>言。我去之後。苦汝營勞。又汝前後。奉事盡忠。常感汝意。思欲相酬。有一秘法。由來未說。若能成辦。直生梵天。無惱長跪。問是何事。答言。若持七日之中。斬千人首。而取一指。凡得千指。以為鬘飾。爾時梵天。<pb ed="T" n="0424a"/>便自來下。命終之後。定生梵天。無惱聞此情懷猶豫。復白師言。此事不應。殺害眾生。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0424n01"/>便生梵天。師又告言。汝我弟子。豈不信我至要之言。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0424n02"/>若汝不信則為義絕。隨爾道徑莫復此住。又更作呪。竪刀在地。說呪已訖惡心轉生。師知其意。即授與刀。受刀走外。得人便殺。取指為鬘。人見便號鴦仇魔羅。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0424n03"/>晉言指鬘</p>
        <p>周行斬害到七日。頭方得九百九十九指。唯少一指。殘殺一人。指數便滿。人皆藏竄。無敢行者。遍行求覓。更不能得。七日之中。不得飲食。其母憐愍。遣人為致。悉各懷懼。無敢往者。其母持食。躬自致往。兒遙見母。走趣欲殺。母時語言。咄不孝物。云何懷逆。欲危害我。兒便語言。我受師教。要七日中。滿得千指。便當得願生於梵天。日數已滿。更不能得。事不獲已。當殺於母。母又語言。事苟當爾。但取我指。莫見傷殺。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>於時世尊具遙<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0424n04"/>覩見。知其可度。化作比丘。行於彼邊。鴦仇<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0424n05"/>摩羅。已見比丘。捨母騰躍。走趣規殺。佛見其來。徐行捨去。指鬘極力走不能及。便遙喚言。比丘小住。佛遙答言。我常自住。但汝不住。指鬘復問。云何汝住。我不住耶。佛即答言。我諸根寂定。而得自在。汝從惡師。稟受邪倒。變易汝心。不得定住。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0424n06"/>晝夜殺害。造無邊罪。指鬘聞此意欻開悟。投刀遠棄。遙禮自歸。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>於時如來爾乃待之。還現佛身。光明朗日。三十二相。昺著奇妙。指鬘見佛光相威儀。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>以身投地。悔過自責。佛粗說法。得法眼淨。心遂純<pb ed="T" n="0424b"/>信。求索出家。佛即可之。善來比丘。鬚髮自落。法衣著身。隨彼所應。重為說法。心垢都盡。得羅漢道。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
