<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 016. It is found in the 出曜經 Sutra at T.04.0212.0703.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T04.0212.0703a23">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t04.0212.0703a23"/>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <lg met="4">
          <l>人前為過<caesura/>後止不犯</l>
          <l>是照世間<caesura/>如月雲消</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>昔佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>彼時去國界不遠有梵志子。名曰無害。常追逐師友。讀梵志經典。所事師者耆舊長老。年過八十所納妻婦。年幼少壯顏貌端正。女之禮節威儀備舉。無害梵志子亦復端正丈夫姿顏世無雙<pb ed="T" n="0703b"/>比。時彼女人婬欲熾盛。即捉梵志子無害手。吾敬卿德欲與情交宜可爾不。無害聞之。以手掩耳我寧喪命終不敢聽。女答之曰。夫人<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n06"/>飢渴給以食飲豈不篤意耶。我今婬火熾盛。須卿婬水滅之。豈不適我情耶。設當由汝喪我命根者。於此經典何用學為。無害答曰。我從母意犯梵志法死入地獄。豈不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n07"/>抂乎。時彼無害自抴走出門外。時梵志婦<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n08"/>蓬頭亂髮以土自坌。裂壞衣裳坐地<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n09"/>
          <g ref="g017">[口*號]</g>哭。長老梵志行還見之問其婦曰。誰取汝打撲乃爾。婦答梵志是汝親信弟子。梵志聞已內自思惟。吾今不宜彰露此事。彼人備聞害我不疑。當以權宜微以誘進乃獲其身斷其命根。即呼梵志子而告之曰。汝前後已來。所學呪術皆悉備具無有缺漏。然當選擇良日祭<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n10"/>祠諸神呪乃得行。左手援<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n11"/>楯右手援劍。詣彼要道嶮路值人斬之。數滿千人而取一指。如是成鬘呪乃得行。是時弊魔復遣<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n12"/>鳩槃<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n13"/>荼鬼。衛護其人使得行惡。斷絕人路無復行人。漸漸乃至闍<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n14"/>梨<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n15"/>違尼園中。人民丘曠舉國被災。又少一指不充其數。無害親所生母每生此念。吾子久在曠野。飢寒勤苦必然不疑。時母送餉躬詣彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n16"/>園。無害遙見便生此念。吾受師訓當辦指鬘。今少一指不充其數。今值我母自來送餉。若我先食呪術不成。若我先殺母者當犯五逆罪。梵志子應從佛得度。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>如來三達見彼無害。興五逆意殺母不疑。若審爾者億佛不救。吾今宜往拔濟其苦。使母子俱全豈不善乎。即化作比丘。手執應器視地而行。<pb ed="T" n="0703c"/>循彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n17"/>徑路直趣彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n18"/>園。路側行人諸牧牛者語曰。沙門止止莫從此路。前有暴賊。名曰指鬘。前後已來傷害人民不可稱計。我等所忌不從此路。沙門單弱<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n19"/>儻為賊所害者不亦劇耶。化人曰無苦。賊不害我。吾有禁呪足能制彼。使不害我。轉復前進遂欲至園。指鬘遙見有比丘來。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>歡喜踊躍不能自勝。吾願果矣。必成指鬘又不害母。呪術成辦權停我母及此餉食。殺彼比丘然後能食。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>執<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n20"/>刀擎<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n11"/>楯往逆比丘。無害素是壯<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n21"/>士。走及奔馬馳趣向佛。佛以神力<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n22"/>令彼無害在地。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0703n23"/>頓縮佛地寬舒如是疲極不能及佛。指鬘舉聲喚沙門曰。止止沙門吾欲問義。比丘答曰。吾自久住卿自不住。爾時指鬘以偈向比丘說曰。</p>
        <lg met="6">
          <l>沙門行反言住<caesura/>我住反言不住</l>
          <l>沙門當說此義<caesura/>云何汝住我不住</l>
        </lg>
        <p>爾時佛復以偈答曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>指鬘我已住<caesura/>無害一切人</l>
          <l>汝為凶暴人<caesura/>何不改罪過</l>
        </lg>
        <p>廣說如契經偈。爾時指鬘賊即以劍楯頭上。指鬘投於深澗。叉手合掌向如來懺悔。復以偈讚曰</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>
            <pb ed="T" n="0704a"/>自歸大聖雄<caesura/>欲覲尊沙門</l>
          <l>今欲自悔過<caesura/>久來所作罪</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>爾時世尊還現色相威神炳著。手執指鬘詣祇<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n01"/>洹精舍告諸比丘。汝等將此指鬘度為比丘。即如佛教得為道人。清旦著衣持鉢入舍衛城分<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n02"/>越。爾時城門裏有一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n03"/>牝象。懷妊欲產不時得產。象主遙見比丘來即起迎逆。比丘若能使象時產者。可得入城乞。不能使象產者不得入城分<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n04"/>越。比丘答<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n05"/>曰。吾先不誦此呪。且小停住須吾還至世尊所受誦神呪。還當呪之<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n06"/>使得產。時指鬘比丘即至世尊所。頭面禮足白世尊曰。向者入城分<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n04"/>越。值城門裏有象欲產責我呪術。象得產者然後得乞。唯願世尊願受神呪。使象得產使得分<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n04"/>越。佛告指鬘。汝往彼所當以此言呪之。今至誠呪。自生<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n07"/>以來初不殺生。持是至誠語使象得產無他。爾時鴦<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n08"/>掘魔。從佛受呪術。即往呪象安隱得產。時諸人民皆稱善哉。世間乃有此奇怪之事。此指鬘前後殺生不可稱計。今方自呪從生<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n07"/>以來初不殺生。持是至誠語使象得產無他。便得入城街巷人民見指鬘來。其中<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n09"/>或父母兄弟妻息。為指<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n10"/>鬘所殺者。皆前報怨。或以刀杖瓦石打指鬘極使牢熟。破頭傷體裂壞。衣被鉢盂亦破。即<pb ed="T" n="0704b"/>走出城竟不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT04p0704n11"/>乞食。還至世尊所頭面禮足自說緣本。佛知其意指鬘受緣報何其速哉。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時世尊漸與說法。即於坐上得須陀洹果乃至羅漢六通清徹。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
