<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1077">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0280c18"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在央瞿多羅國人間遊行。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0280n07"/>經陀婆闍梨迦林中，見有牧牛者、牧羊者、採柴草者及餘種種作人。見世尊行路，見已，皆白佛言：</p>
        <q who="kammakarino">
          <p>世尊！莫從此道去！前有央瞿利摩羅賊，脫恐怖人。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告諸人：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>我不畏懼。</p>
        </q>
        <p>作此語已，從道而去。彼再三告，世尊猶去，遙見央瞿利摩羅手執刀楯，走向世尊。以神力現身徐行，令央瞿利摩羅<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0280n08"/>駃走不及。走極疲乏已，遙語世尊：</p>
        <q who="angulimalo">
          <p>住！住！勿去！</p>
        </q>
        <p>世尊竝行而答：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>我常住耳，汝自不住。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時央瞿利摩羅即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="angulimalo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1077a">
            <l>沙門尚<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0280n08"/>駃行<caesura/>而言我常住</l>
            <pb ed="T" n="0281a"/>
            <l>我今疲勌住<caesura/>說言汝不住</l>
            <l>沙門說云何<caesura/>我住汝不住</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊以偈答言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1077b">
            <l>央瞿利摩羅<caesura/>我說常住者</l>
            <l>於一切眾生<caesura/>謂息於刀杖</l>
            <l>汝恐怖眾生<caesura/>惡業不休息</l>
            <l>我於一切蟲<caesura/>止息於刀杖</l>
            <l>汝於一切蟲<caesura/>常逼迫恐怖</l>
            <l>造作凶惡業<caesura/>終無休息時</l>
            <l>我於一切神<caesura/>止息於刀杖</l>
            <l>汝於一切神<caesura/>長夜苦逼迫</l>
            <l>造作黑惡業<caesura/>于今不止息</l>
            <l>我住於<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0281n01"/>息法<caesura/>一切不放逸</l>
            <l>汝不見四諦<caesura/>故不息放逸</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>央瞿利摩羅說偈白佛：</p>
        <q who="angulimalo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1077c">
            <l>久乃見牟尼<caesura/>故隨路而逐</l>
            <l>今聞真妙說<caesura/>當捨久遠惡</l>
            <l>作如是說已<caesura/>即放捨刀楯</l>
            <l>投身世尊足<caesura/>願聽我出家</l>
            <l>佛以慈悲心<caesura/>大僊多哀愍</l>
            <l>告比丘善來<caesura/>出家受具足</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時央瞿利摩羅出家已，獨一靜處，專精思惟。所以族姓子剃除鬚髮，著袈裟衣，正信非家，出家學道，增修梵行，現法自知作證，我生已盡，梵行已立，所作已作，自知不受後有。時央瞿利摩羅得阿羅漢，覺解脫喜樂，即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="angulimalo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1077d">
            <l>本受不害名<caesura/>而中多殺害</l>
            <l>今得見諦名<caesura/>永離於傷殺<pb ed="T" n="0281b"/>
            </l>
            <l>身行不殺害<caesura/>口意俱亦然</l>
            <l>當知真不殺<caesura/>不迫於眾生</l>
            <l>洗手常血色<caesura/>名央瞿摩羅</l>
            <l>浚流之所漂<caesura/>三歸制令息</l>
            <l>歸依三寶已<caesura/>出家得具足</l>
            <l>成就於三明<caesura/>佛教作已作</l>
            <l>調牛以捶杖<caesura/>伏象以鐵鈎</l>
            <l>不以刀捶杖<caesura/>正度調天人</l>
            <l>利刀以水石<caesura/>直箭以<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0281n02"/>熅火</l>
            <l>治<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0281n03"/>材以斧斤<caesura/>自調以黠慧</l>
            <l>人前行放逸<caesura/>隨後能自斂</l>
            <l>是則照世間<caesura/>如雲解月現</l>
            <l>人前放逸行<caesura/>隨後<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0281n04"/>能自斂</l>
            <l>於世恩愛流<caesura/>正念而超出</l>
            <l>少壯年出家<caesura/>精勤修佛教</l>
            <l>是則照世間<caesura/>如雲解月現</l>
            <l>少壯年出家<caesura/>精勤修佛教</l>
            <l>於世恩愛流<caesura/>正念以超出</l>
            <l>若度諸惡業<caesura/>正善能令滅</l>
            <l>是則照世間<caesura/>如雲解月現</l>
            <l>人前造惡業<caesura/>正善能令滅</l>
            <l>於世恩愛流<caesura/>正念能超出</l>
            <l>我已作惡業<caesura/>必向於惡趣</l>
            <l>已受於惡報<caesura/>宿<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0281n05"/>責食已食</l>
            <l>若彼我怨憎<caesura/>聞此正法者</l>
            <l>得清淨法眼<caesura/>於我修行忍</l>
            <l>不復興鬪訟<caesura/>蒙佛恩力故</l>
            <l>我<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0281n06"/>怨行忍辱<caesura/>亦常讚歎忍</l>
            <l>隨時聞正法<caesura/>聞已隨修行</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>
          <pb ed="T" n="0281c"/>佛說此經已，央瞿利摩羅聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
