<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 018. It is found in the 增壹阿含經 Sutra at T.02.0125.0733.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0125.0733b12">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0125.0733b12"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時。尊者童真迦葉在舍衛國晝闇園中。</p>
        <p>是時。迦葉夜半而經行。爾時。有天來至迦葉所。在虛空中語迦葉言。比丘當知。此舍夜便有烟。晝日火然。婆羅門語智者曰。汝今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n13"/>持刀鑿山。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n14"/>當鑿山時。必當見有負物。當拔濟之。汝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n15"/>當鑿山。當鑿山時。必當見山。汝今當捨山。汝今當鑿山。當鑿山時。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n16"/>必見蝦蟇。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n17"/>今當捨蝦蟇。汝今當鑿山。當鑿山時。當見肉聚。已見肉聚。當捨離之。汝今當鑿山。當鑿山時。當見枷。已見枷。便捨離之。汝今當鑿山。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0729n13"/>已鑿山。當見二道。已見二道。當捨離之。汝今當鑿山。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0729n13"/>已鑿山。當見樹枝。已見樹枝。當捨離之。汝今當鑿山。已鑿山。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n18"/>見龍。已見龍。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n19"/>勿共語。當自歸命。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n20"/>慕令得所。比丘。當善思念此義。設不解者。便往至舍衛城。到世尊所。而問此義。若如來有所說。善念行之。所以然者。我今亦不見有人‧沙門‧婆羅門‧<pb ed="T" n="0733c"/>魔‧若魔天能解此義者。除如來及如來弟子。若從我聞。是時。迦葉報天曰。此事甚佳。</p>
        <p>爾時。迦葉清旦至世尊所。到已。頭面禮足。在一面坐。以此因緣。具白世尊。爾時。迦葉問世尊曰。今當問如來義。天之所說。何所趣向。何以故<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n21"/>舍夜有烟。晝便火然。何以故名為婆羅門。何以故名為智者。又言鑿山者。其義何所趣向。言刀者。亦所不解。何以故名為負物。又言山者。其義云何。何以故復言蝦蟇。何以故復言肉聚。何以故復言枷。何以故<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n22"/>復言二道。樹枝義其義云何。何以<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n23"/>故名龍。</p>
        <p>世尊告曰。舍者。即是形體也。四大色所造。受父母血脈漸漸長大。恒當養食。不令有乏。是分散<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n24"/>法。夜有烟者。眾生之類心之所念<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n25"/>是。晝日火然者。身‧口‧意所造行是也。婆羅門者。是阿羅漢也。智者。是學人也。鑿山者。精進之心是也。刀者。智慧是也。負物者。是五結也。山者。是憍慢也。蝦蟇者。瞋恚心是也。肉聚者。貪欲是也。枷者。五欲是也。二道者。疑是也。樹枝者。是無明也。龍者。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n26"/>是如來‧至真‧等正<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0609n02"/>覺是。彼天所說。其義如是。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>汝今當熟思惟。不久當盡有漏。</p>
        <p>爾時。迦葉受如來<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n27"/>如是之教。在閑靜<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n02"/>之處。而自修行。所以族姓子。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n28"/>剃除鬚髮。出家學道者。欲修梵行。生死已盡。梵行已立。所作已辦。更不復受胎。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0733n29"/>如實知之。爾時。迦葉便成<choice>
            <sic>陀</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">阿</corr>
          </choice>羅漢。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時。迦葉聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
