<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1079">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0282a22"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在王舍城迦蘭陀竹園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有異比丘，於後夜時至<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0281n08"/>搨補河邊，脫衣，置岸邊，入水，洗浴。浴已，還上岸，著一衣，待身乾。時有一天子，放身光明，普照<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0281n08"/>搨補河側，問比丘言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p>比丘！比丘！此是丘塚，夜則起烟，晝則火然。彼婆羅門見已，而作是言：<q who="brahmano">壞此丘塚！</q>發掘者智<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0282n03"/>，持以刀劍，又見大龜。婆羅門見已，作是言：<q who="brahmano">除此大龜！</q>發<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0099.0282b" n="0282b"/>掘者智，持以刀劍，見有氍氀 。婆羅門見已，作此言：<q who="brahmano">却此氍氀！</q>發掘者智，持以刀劍，見有肉段。彼婆羅門見已，作是言：<q who="brahmano">除此肉段！</q>發掘者智，持以刀劍，見有屠殺。婆羅門見已，作是言：<q who="brahmano">壞是屠殺處！</q>發掘者智，持以刀劍，見有楞耆。彼婆羅門見已，作是言：<q who="brahmano">却此楞耆！</q>發掘者智，持以刀劍，見有二道。彼婆羅門見已，作是言：<q who="brahmano">除此二道！</q>發掘者智，持以刀劍，見有門扇。婆羅門見已，作是言：<q who="brahmano">却此門扇！</q>發掘者智，持以刀劍，見有大龍。婆羅門見已，作是言：<q who="brahmano">止！勿却大龍！應當恭敬！</q>比丘！汝來受此論，往問世尊。如佛所說，汝隨受持！所以者何？除如來，我不見世間諸天、魔、梵、沙門、婆羅門於此論心悅樂者，若諸弟子從我所聞，然後能說。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時比丘從彼天所聞此論已，往詣世尊，稽首禮足，退坐一面，以彼天子所問<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0282n04"/>諸論廣問世尊：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p>云何為丘塚？云何為夜則起烟？云何為晝則火然？云何是婆羅門？云何發掘？云何智者？云何刀劍？云何為大龜？云何氍氀？云何為肉段？云何為屠殺處？云何為楞耆？云何為二道？云何為門扇？云何為大龍？</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>丘塚者，謂眾生身──麤四大色、父母遺體、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0282n05"/>摶食、衣服、覆蓋、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0282n06"/>澡浴、摩飾長養，皆是變、壞、磨、滅之法。夜起烟者，謂有人於夜時起隨覺、隨觀。晝行其教身業、口業。婆羅門者，謂如來．應．等正覺。發掘者，謂精勤方便。智士者，謂多聞聖弟子。刀劍者，謂智慧刀劍。大龜者，謂五蓋。氍氀者，謂忿恨。肉段者，謂慳、愱。屠<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0099.0282c" n="0282c"/>殺者，謂五欲功德。楞耆者，謂無明。二道，謂疑惑。門扇者，謂我慢。大龍者，謂漏盡羅漢。如是──比丘！──，若大師為聲聞所作哀愍、悲念，以義安慰，於汝已作。汝等當作所作，當於<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0282n07"/>曝露、林中、空舍、山澤、巖窟敷草、樹葉，思惟、禪思，不起放逸，莫令後悔！是則為我隨順之教。</p>
        </q>
        <p>即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1079a">
            <l>說身為丘塚<caesura/>覺觀夜起烟</l>
            <l>晝業為火然<caesura/>婆羅門正覺</l>
            <l>精進勤發掘<caesura/>黠慧明智<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0282n08"/>士</l>
            <l>以智慧利劍<caesura/>厭離勝進者</l>
            <l>五蓋為巨龜<caesura/>忿恨為氍氀</l>
            <l>慳愱為肉段<caesura/>五欲屠殺處</l>
            <l>無明為楞耆<caesura/>疑惑於二道</l>
            <l>門扇現我慢<caesura/>漏盡羅漢龍</l>
            <l>究竟斷諸論<caesura/>故我如是說</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，彼比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
