<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 018. It is found in the 佛說蟻喻經 Sutra at T.01.0095.0918.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0095.0918b25">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0095.0918b25"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時世尊。放大光明普照耀已。告苾芻眾言。汝等當知。於一時中有諸蟻聚。夜中出煙。晝日火然。有一婆羅門。見是事已。乃作是言。若有執持快利刀者。必能破散其聚。如是言已。次復見一大龜。其婆羅門亦作是言。若有執<pb ed="T" n="0918c"/>持快利刀者。必能破壞。次見諸水母蟲。次見一水蛭蟲。次見諸阿西蘇那蟲。次見一大蛇。次見一挼陀鉢他蟲。次見一<g ref="g018">[昝-人+几]</g>哥嚩吒蟲。其婆羅門見彼諸蟲已。皆如前言。最後見一大龍。婆羅門言。如我所見其事云何。唯佛世尊悉能了知。即時往詣一苾芻所。具陳上事。復言。苾芻。汝以此事為我問佛。使我疑心而得開曉。如佛所說我當憶持。何以故。苾芻。我不見彼天人世間沙門婆羅門眾中有以此義能問佛者。是故不能使諸疑心而得開曉。</p>
        <p>時彼苾芻即如其言。來詣我所。到已禮足退住一面。具陳上事已復發問言。如婆羅門所見蟻聚。其事云何。夜中出煙晝日火然。此復云何。又見大龜水母蟲水蛭蟲阿西蘇那蟲大蛇挼陀鉢他蟲<g ref="g018">[昝-人+几]</g>哥嚩吒蟲大龍。此等所見皆是何相。即彼婆羅門復是何人。何故名為利刀破散。願佛為說。</p>
        <p>諸苾芻我時謂彼苾芻言。其蟻聚者。即是一切眾生五蘊聚身。夜中出煙者。即是眾生起諸尋伺。晝日火然者。即是眾生隨所尋伺起身語業。大龜者。即是五鄣染法。水母蟲者。即是忿恚。水蛭蟲者即是慳嫉。阿西蘇那蟲者。即是五欲之法。蛇者即是無明。挼陀鉢他蟲者。是疑惑。<g ref="g018">[昝-人+几]</g>哥嚩吒蟲者。是我慢。龍者即是諸阿羅漢。婆羅門者。即是如來應供正等正覺。快利者。即是有智之人。刀者即是智慧。破散者。即是發起精進勝行。諸苾芻。於汝意云何。彼所見相以要言之。即是一切眾生五蘊聚身羯邏藍等。父母不淨之所出生。四大合成。虛假色相。麁惡劣<pb ed="T" n="0919a"/>弱。積集苦惱畢竟破壞。而諸眾生不能覺知。於晝夜中起諸尋伺。而身語業不善施作。五鄣煩惱之所覆蔽。耽著五欲。增長無明。生我慢心。於諸聖法疑惑不決。忿恚慳嫉。念念發起。不求解脫。是故如來應供正等正覺。欲令諸有智者發精進行。修習智慧。斷諸煩惱。趣證聖果。汝諸苾芻。已盡諸漏證阿羅漢果。故說如龍。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>復次諸苾芻。過去未來諸佛世尊。悲愍利樂一切眾生。欲令斷諸煩惱趣證聖果。為諸聲聞廣說是義。我於今日亦如諸佛。乃以此緣為汝宣說。汝諸苾芻。憶念是事。當於曠野空舍山間樹下巖穴菴室諸寂靜處。諦心思惟觀察是義。無令放逸生退轉心。亦復轉為他人開示教導。普令修習得大利樂。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時世尊為諸苾芻如是說已。而諸苾芻。皆悉信受。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
