<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1082">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0283b27"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊晨朝著衣持鉢，入舍衛城乞食。食畢，還精舍，洗足已，入安陀林坐<pb ed="T" n="0283c"/>禪。時有異比丘，亦復晨朝著衣持鉢，入舍衛城乞食。食畢，還精舍，洗足已，入安陀林，坐一樹下，入晝正受。是比丘入<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n10"/>晝正受時，有惡、不善覺起，依貪嗜心。時有天神，依安陀林住止者，作是念：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p>此比丘不善、不類，於安陀林坐禪而起不善覺，心依惡貪。我當往呵<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n11"/>責！</p>
        </q>
        <p>作是念已，往語比丘言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p>比丘！比丘！作瘡疣耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>比丘答言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p>當治令愈。</p>
        </q>
        <p>天神語比丘：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p>瘡如鐵鑊，云何可復？</p>
        </q>
        <p>比丘答言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p>正念正<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n12"/>智，足能分復。</p>
        </q>
        <p>天神白言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p>善哉！善哉！此是真賢治瘡。如是治瘡，究竟能愈，無有發時。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊晡時從禪覺，還祇樹給孤獨園。入僧中，於大眾前敷座而坐，告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>我今晨朝著衣持鉢，入舍衛城乞食。乞食還，至安陀林坐禪，入<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n10"/>晝正受。有一比丘，亦乞食，還至安陀林，坐一樹下，入<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n10"/>晝正受，而彼比丘起不善覺，心依惡貪。有天神，依安陀林住，語比丘言：<q who="devata">比丘！比丘！作瘡疣耶？……（如上廣說。乃至）如是，比丘！善哉！善哉！此治眾賢。</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1082a">
            <l>士夫作瘡疣<caesura/>自生於苦患</l>
            <l>願求世間欲<caesura/>心依於惡貪</l>
            <l>以生瘡疣故<caesura/>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n07"/>蛆蠅競來集</l>
            <l>愛<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n13"/>求為瘡疣<caesura/>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n07"/>蛆蠅諸惡覺</l>
            <l>及<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n14"/>諸貪嗜心<caesura/>皆悉從意生</l>
            <l>鑽鑿士夫心<caesura/>以求華名利</l>
            <l>欲火轉熾然<caesura/>妄想不善覺</l>
            <l>身心日夜羸<caesura/>遠離寂靜道</l>
            <l>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0283n15"/>若內心寂靜<caesura/>決定智明了</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0284a"/>無有斯瘡疣<caesura/>見佛安隱路</l>
            <l>正士所遊跡<caesura/>賢聖善宣說</l>
            <l>明智所<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0284n01"/>知道<caesura/>不復受諸有</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
