<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1083">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0284a05"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住毘舍離國獼猴池側重閣講堂。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有眾多比丘，晨朝著衣持缽，入毘舍離乞食。時有年少比丘，出家未久，不閑法、律，當乞食時，不知先後次第。餘比丘見已，而告之言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p>汝是年少，出家未久，未知法、律，莫<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0284n03"/>越、莫重，前後失次而行乞食，長夜當得不饒益苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p>年少比丘言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p>諸上座亦復越次，不隨前後，非獨我也。</p>
        </q>
        <p>如是再三，不能令止。眾多比丘乞食已，還精舍，舉衣缽，洗足已，詣佛所，稽首禮足，退坐一面，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p>世尊！我等晨朝著衣持缽，入毘舍離乞食。有一年少比丘，於此法、律出家未久，行乞食時，不以次第，前後復重。諸比丘等再三諫，不受，而作是言：<q who="bhikkhu">諸上座亦不次第，何故呵我？</q>我等諸比丘三呵，不受，故來白世尊。唯願世尊為除非法，哀愍故！</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>如空澤中有大湖水。有大龍象，而居其中，拔諸藕根，洗去泥土，然後食之。食已，身體肥悅，多力多樂。以是因緣，常喜樂住。有異種族象，形體羸小，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0284n04"/>效彼龍象，拔其藕根，洗不能淨，合泥土食。食<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0284n05"/>之不消，體不肥悅，轉轉羸弱，緣斯致死，或同死苦。如是宿德比丘學道日久，不樂嬉戲，久修梵行，大師所歎。諸餘明智修梵行者，亦復加歎。是等比丘依止城邑、聚落，晨朝著衣持<pb ed="T" n="0284b"/>缽，入城乞食，善護身、口，善攝諸根，專心繫念，能令彼人不信者信，信者不異。若得財利──衣被、飲食、床臥、湯藥，不染、不著、不貪、不嗜、不迷、不逐，見其過患，見其出離，然復食之。食已，身心悅澤，得色得力。以是因緣，常得安樂。彼年少比丘出家未久，未閑法、律，依諸長老，依止聚落，著衣持缽，入村乞食，不善護身，不守根<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0284n06"/>門，不專繫念，不能令彼不信者信，信者不變。若得財利──衣被、飲食、臥具、湯藥，染著貪逐，不見過患，不見出離，以嗜欲心食，不能令身悅澤，安隱快樂。緣斯食故，轉向於死，或同死苦。所言『死』者，謂捨戒還俗，失正法、正律。『同死苦』者，謂犯正法、律，不識罪相，不知除罪。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1083a">
            <l>龍象拔藕根<caesura/>水洗而食之</l>
            <l>異族象<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0284n07"/>效彼<caesura/>合泥而取食</l>
            <l>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0284n08"/>因雜泥食故<caesura/>羸病遂至死</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
