<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 030. It is found in the 增壹阿含經 Sutra at T.02.0125.0642.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0125.0642b29">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0125.0642b29"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時。佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨<pb ed="T" n="0642c"/>
            園。
                                爾時。尊者
          <seg type="not-parallel">婆迦梨身得重患。臥在大小便上。</seg>意欲<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n20"/>自刀殺。<seg type="not-parallel">無此勢可自坐起。是時。尊者婆迦梨告侍者。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n21"/>汝今可持刀來。吾欲自殺。所以然者。如今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n22"/>日釋迦文佛弟子之中。信解脫者無出我上。然我今日有漏心不解脫。所以然者。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n23"/>
              然如來弟子遇苦惱時。亦復求刀自殺。我今用此命。為不能從此岸至彼岸。
                                  是時。婆迦梨弟子出家未久。未知今世．後世。不知從此岸至彼岸。亦復不知死此生彼。便授刀與之。
            </seg>時。婆迦梨手執刀已。以信堅固。持刀自刺。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">是時。婆迦梨以<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n24"/>刀自刺。而作是念。釋迦文佛弟子之中。所作非法。得惡利不得善利。於如來法中。不得受證而<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n25"/>取命終。是時。尊者婆迦梨便思惟是五盛陰。是謂此色。是謂色<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n26"/>習。是謂色滅盡。是謂痛．想．行．識。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n27"/>是謂痛．想．行．識集。是謂痛．想．行．識．滅盡。彼於此五盛陰熟思惟之。諸有生法皆是死法。知此已。便於有漏心得解脫。爾時。尊者婆迦梨於無餘涅槃界而般涅槃。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>爾時。世尊以天耳聽聞尊者婆迦梨求刀自殺。爾時。世尊告<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n28"/>
            阿難。諸比丘在舍衛城者。盡集一處。吾欲所勅。
                                是時。尊者阿難受世尊教。即集諸比丘。在普
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n29"/>集講堂。還白世尊<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n30"/>
            曰。今日比丘已集一處。
                                是時。世尊
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n31"/>將比丘僧。前後圍遶。至彼婆迦梨比丘精舍。<seg type="not-paraqllel">當於爾時。弊魔波旬欲得知尊者婆迦梨神識所在。為在何處。為在人耶。為非人耶。天．龍．鬼神．乾沓惒．阿須倫．迦留羅．摩休勒．閱叉。今此神識竟為所在。在何處生遊。<pb ed="T" n="0643a"/>不見東西南北。四維上下。皆悉周遍而不知神識之處。是時。魔波旬身體疲極。莫知所在。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>爾時。世尊將比丘僧。前後圍遶。至彼精舍。爾時。世尊觀魔波旬欲得知神識所在。世尊告諸比丘。汝等頗聞此精舍之中有大聲乎。又在光怪。
                        諸比丘對曰。如是。世尊。我等<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0641n29"/>
            已見。
                                世尊告曰。此弊魔波旬。欲得知婆迦梨神識所在。
          </p>
        <p>是時。尊者阿難白世尊曰。唯願世尊<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0643n01"/>說婆迦梨比丘神識為<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0643n02"/>何所在。</p>
        <p>世尊告曰。婆迦梨比丘神識永無所著。彼族姓子<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0641n31"/>以般涅槃。當作如是持。</p>
        <p>
          是時。尊者阿難白世尊曰。此婆迦梨比丘何日得此四諦。
                              世尊告曰。今日之中得此四諦。
        </p>
        <p>阿難白佛。此比丘抱病經久。本是凡人。
                        世尊告曰。如是。阿難。如汝所言。但彼比丘<choice>
            <sic>嫌</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">謙</corr>
          </choice>苦甚久。諸有釋迦文佛弟子之中。信解脫者此人最勝。然有漏心未得解脫。我今可求刀自刺。是時。彼比丘臨自刺時。即思惟如來功德。捨壽之日。思惟五盛陰。是謂此色<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0642n26"/>習．此色滅盡。爾時。彼比丘思惟此已。諸有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0643n03"/>習之法皆悉滅盡。此比丘<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0641n29"/>已般涅槃。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
