<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1091">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0286a02"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城毘婆羅山七葉樹林石室中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有尊者<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0286n02"/>瞿低迦，住王舍城<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0286n04"/>仙人山側<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0286n02"/>黑石室中，獨一思惟，不放逸行，修自饒益。時受意解脫，身作證，數數退轉：一、二、三、四、五、六反，退還復得。時受意解脫，身作證，尋復退轉。彼尊者瞿低迦作是念：</p>
        <q who="godhiko">
          <p>我獨一靜處思惟，不放逸行，精勤修習，以自饒益。時受意解脫，身作證，而復數數退轉，……（乃至）六反，猶復退轉。我今當以刀自殺，莫令第七退轉。</p>
        </q>
        <p>時魔波旬作是念：</p>
        <q who="papima">
          <p>沙門瞿曇住王舍城毘婆羅山側七葉樹林石窟中。有弟子瞿低迦，住王舍城仙人山側黑石室中，獨一靜處，專精思惟。得時受意解脫，身作證，六反退轉，而復還得。彼作是念：<q who="godhiko">我已六反退，而復還得，莫令我第七退轉。我寧以刀自殺，莫令第七退轉。</q>若彼比丘以刀自殺者，莫令自殺，出我境界去。我今當往告彼大師。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時波旬執<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0286n05"/>琉璃柄琵琶，詣世尊所，鼓<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0286n06"/>絃說偈：</p>
        <q who="papima">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1091a">
            <l>大智大方便<caesura/>自在大神力</l>
            <l>得熾然弟子<caesura/>而今欲取死</l>
            <l>大牟尼當制<caesura/>勿令其自殺</l>
            <l>何聞佛世尊<caesura/>正法律聲聞</l>
            <l>學其所不得<caesura/>而取於命終</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>時魔說此偈已。世尊說偈答言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1091b">
            <l>波旬放逸種<caesura/>以自事故來</l>
            <l>堅固具足士<caesura/>常住妙禪定</l>
            <l>晝夜勤精進<caesura/>不顧於性命</l>
            <l>見三有可畏<caesura/>斷除彼愛欲</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0286b"/>已摧伏魔軍<caesura/>瞿低般涅槃</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1091c">
          <l>波旬心憂惱<caesura/>琵琶落於地</l>
          <l>內懷憂慼已<caesura/>即沒而不現</l>
        </lg>
        <p>爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>汝等當來，共至仙人山側黑石室所，觀瞿低迦比丘以刀自殺。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊與眾多比丘往至仙人山側黑石室中，見瞿低迦比丘殺身在地，告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>汝等見此瞿低迦比丘殺身在地不？</p>
        </q>
        <p>諸比丘白佛：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p>唯然，已見，世尊！</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>汝等見瞿低迦比丘周匝遶身黑闇烟起，充滿四方不？</p>
        </q>
        <p>比丘白佛：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p>已見，世尊！</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>此是惡魔波旬於瞿低迦善男子身側，周匝求其識神。然比丘瞿低迦以不住心，執刀自殺。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊為瞿低迦比丘受第一記。爾時波旬而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="papima">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1091d">
            <l>上下及諸方<caesura/>遍求彼識神</l>
            <l>都不見其處<caesura/>瞿低何所之</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1091e">
            <l>如是堅固士<caesura/>一切無所求</l>
            <l>拔<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0286n07"/>恩愛根本<caesura/>瞿低<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0286n08"/>般涅槃</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
