<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 031. It is found in the 太子瑞應本起經 Sutra at T.03.0185.0477.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T03.0185.0477a21">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t03.0185.0477a21"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">於是第六化應聲天。</seg>天上魔王。見菩薩清淨無欲。精思不懈。心中煩毒。飲食不甘。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0477n08"/>伎樂不御。念是道成必大勝我。欲及其未作佛。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0477n09"/>當壞其道意。<seg type="not-parallel">魔子薩陀。前諫父曰。菩薩行淨。三界無比。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0477n06"/>以得自然神通。眾梵諸天億百。皆往禮侍。此非天王所當沮壞。無為興惡自虧福也。</seg>魔王不聽。召三玉女。一名欲妃。二名悅彼。三名快觀。使行壞菩薩意。三女皆被羅縠之衣。服天名香瓔珞珠<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0477n10"/>寶。極為妖冶<pb ed="T" n="0477b"/>巧媚之辭。欲亂其意。菩薩心淨。如琉璃珠。不可得污。三女復<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0477n11"/>白曰。仁德至重。諸天所敬。應有供<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0477n12"/>養故天獻我。我等好潔。年在盛時。天女端正。莫有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0477n13"/>殊我者。願得晨起夜寐供侍左右。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">菩薩答曰。汝宿有福。受得天身。不惟無常。而作妖媚。形體雖好。而心不端。譬如畫瓶中盛臭毒。將以自壞。有何等奇。福難久居。婬惡不善。自亡其本。死即當墮三惡道中。受鳥獸形。欲脫致難。汝輩亂人正意。非清淨種。革囊盛屎。而來何為。去吾不用<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0477n14"/>汝。其三玉女。化成老母。不能自復。</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
