<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 031. It is found in the 修行本起經 Sutra at T.03.0184.0470.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T03.0184.0470c11">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t03.0184.0470c11"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0470n15"/>菩薩心自念言。今當降魔官屬。即放眉間毫相光明。感動魔宮。</seg>魔大惶怖。心中不寧。觀見菩薩。已在樹下。清淨無欲。精思不懈。心中煩毒。飲食不甘。妓樂不御。念是道成。必大勝我。欲及其未作佛壞其道意。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">魔子須摩提(<choice>
              <sic>[＊]<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0462n10"/>
              </sic>
              <corr resp="T100">
                <anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0462n08"/>
              </corr>
            </choice>漢言賢意)。前諫父曰。菩薩行淨。三界無比。以得自然神通。眾梵諸天億百皆往禮侍。此非天人所當沮壞。無為興惡自毀其福。魔王不聽。</seg>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0470n16"/>三女自占。一名恩愛。二名常樂。三名大樂。父王莫憂。吾等自往壞菩薩道<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0470n17"/>意。不足勞父王。勿復憂念。於是三女。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0470n18"/>嚴莊天服。從五百玉女。到菩薩所。彈琴歌頌。婬欲之辭欲亂道意。三女復言。仁德至重。諸天所敬。應有供養。故天獻我。我等<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0470n19"/>好潔。年在盛時。願得晨起夜寐供侍左右。<seg type="not-parallel">菩薩答言。汝宿有福。受得天身。不惟無常。而作妖媚。形體雖好。而心不端。譬如畫瓶中盛臭毒。將以自壞。有何等奇。福難久居。婬惡不善。自亡其本。福盡罪至。墮三惡道。受六畜形。<pb ed="T" n="0471a"/>欲脫致難。汝輩亂人道意。不計非常。經歷劫數。展轉五道。今汝曹等。未離勤苦。吾在世間。處處所生。觀視老者如母。中者如姊。小者如<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0471n01"/>妹。諸姊<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0471n02"/>等各各還宮。勿復作是曹事。菩薩一言。便成老母。頭白齒落。眼冥脊傴。柱杖相扶而還。</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
