<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 031. It is found in the 佛說觀佛三昧海經 Sutra at T.15.0643.0652.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T15.0643.0652a19">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t15.0643.0652a19"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>魔見是相。憔悴懊惱却臥床上。魔有三女長名悅彼。中名喜心。小名多媚。時魔三女至父王<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n05"/>所。長跪叉手為父作禮啟言。父王。今日何故愁悴乃爾。其父答言。沙門瞿曇結誓深重。今坐道樹要壞我民。是故愁耳。女白父言。我能往亂。願父莫愁。即自莊飾著雜寶冠。容媚挺特過<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n06"/>踰魔后。百千萬倍。眄目作姿現諸妖冶。瓔珞晃耀光翳六天。<seg type="not-parallel">乘羽<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n07"/>寶車。安施寶帳垂諸天華。於華鬚頭諸化玉女。手執樂器<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n08"/>鼓樂<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n09"/>絃歌聲萬種音<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n10"/>凡在世人之所憙樂。一一玉女。從五百女以為<pb ed="T" n="0652b"/>侍御。繒蓋<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n11"/>幢幡如雲而下。身毛孔中香烟芬馥。有百千色。玄黃<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n12"/>昱爍甚適人目。</seg>安<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n13"/>庠徐步至菩薩所。下車合掌禮敬菩薩。旋遶七匝。白菩薩言。太子生時。萬神侍御七寶來臻何棄天位來此樹下。我是天女盛美無比。顏貌紅輝六天無雙。今以微身奉上太子。供給左右可備灑掃。我等善能調身<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n14"/>按摩。今欲親附願遂下情。太子坐樹身體疲懈。宜須偃息服食甘露。即以寶器獻天百味。太子寂然身心不動。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">以白<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n15"/>毫擬。令天三女<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n16"/>自見身內膿囊涕唾。九孔筋脈一切根本。大腸小腸生藏熟藏。於其中間。迴伏婉轉<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n17"/>踊生諸蟲。其數滿足有八<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n18"/>千戶。戶有九億諸小蟲等。蟲遊戲時走入小腸。皆有四口張口上向。大蟲遊戲入大腸中。從大腸出復入胃中。冷病起時胃<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n19"/>管閉塞。蟲不得入故食不消。脾腎肝肺心膽喉嚨。肺腴肝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n20"/>鬲。如是中間復生四蟲。如四蛇合。上下同時唼食諸藏。滓盡汁出。入眼為淚。入鼻為<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n21"/>涕。聚口成唾。放口<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n22"/>涎流。薄皮厚皮。筋<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0652n23"/>髓諸脈悉生諸蟲。細於秋<anchor type="variant" n="fnT15p0650n14"/>毫數甚眾多不可具說。其女見此即便嘔吐從口而出。無有窮盡。</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
