<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 031. It is found in the 過去現在因果經 Sutra at T.03.0189.0639.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T03.0189.0639c28">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t03.0189.0639c28"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p> 魔<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0639n14"/>有三女。形容儀貌。極為端<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0636n07"/>正。妖冶巧媚。<pb ed="T" n="0640a"/>善能惑人。於天女中。最為第一。熏以名香。佩好瓔珞。一名染欲。二名能悅人。三名可愛樂。三女俱前白其父言。不審今者何故憂愁。父即寫心。語諸女言。世間今有沙門瞿曇。身被法鎧。執自在弓。鏃智慧箭。欲伏眾生壞我境界。我若不如。眾生信彼。皆悉歸依。我土則空。是故愁耳。及<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n01"/>未成道。欲往摧挫壞其橋梁。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">於是魔王。手執強弓。又持五箭。男女眷屬。俱時往彼畢波羅樹下。見於牟尼。寂然不動。欲度生死三有之海。爾時魔王。左手執弓。右手調箭。語菩薩言。汝剎利種。死甚可畏。何不速起。宜應修汝轉輪王業。捨出家法。習於施會。得生天樂。此道第一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n02"/>勝先所行。汝是剎利轉輪王種。而為乞士。此非所應。今若不起。但好安坐。勿捨本誓。我試射汝。一放利箭。苦行仙人。聞我箭聲。莫不驚怖。惛迷失性。況汝瞿曇。能堪此毒。汝若速起。可得安全。魔說<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n03"/>此語。以怖菩薩。菩薩怡然。不驚不動。魔王即便挽弓放箭。并進天女。菩薩爾時。眼不視箭。箭停空中。其鏃<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n04"/>下向。變成蓮花</seg>
        </p>
        <p>時三天女。白菩薩言。仁者至德。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n05"/>天人所敬。應有供侍。我等今者年在盛時。天女端<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0636n07"/>正。無踰我者天今遣我。以相供給。晨昏寢臥。願<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n06"/>侍左右。<seg type="not-parallel">菩薩答言。汝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n07"/>植小善。得為天身。不念無常。而作妖媚。形體雖美。而心不端。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n08"/>淫<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n09"/>惑不善。死必當墮三惡道中。受鳥獸身。免之甚難汝等今者欲亂定意。非清淨心。今便可去。吾不相須。時三天女。變<pb ed="T" n="0640b"/>成老姥。頭白面皺。齒落垂涎。肉消骨立。腹大如鼓。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0640n10"/>柱杖羸步。不能自復。</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
