<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1107">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0291a27"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住鞞舍離國獼猴池側重閣講堂。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>過去世時有一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0291n07"/>夜叉鬼，醜陋惡色，在帝釋空座上<pb ed="T" n="0291b"/>坐。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0291n08"/>三十三天見此鬼醜陋惡色，在帝釋空座上坐。見已，咸各瞋恚。諸天如是極瞋恚已，彼鬼如是如是隨瞋恚漸漸端正。時三十三天往詣天帝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0291n09"/>釋，白帝釋言：<q who="devatavatimsa">憍尸迦！當知有一異鬼，醜陋惡色，在天王空座上坐。我等諸天見彼鬼醜陋惡色，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0291n10"/>坐天王座，極生瞋恚。隨<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0291n11"/>彼諸天瞋恚，彼鬼隨漸端正！</q>釋提桓因告諸三十三天：<q who="sakko">彼是瞋恚對治鬼。</q>爾時天帝釋自往彼鬼所，整衣服，偏袒右肩，合掌，三稱名字<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0291n12"/>而言：<q who="sakko">仁者！我是釋提桓因。</q>隨釋提桓因如是恭敬下意，彼鬼如是如是隨漸醜陋，即復不現。時釋提桓因自坐已，而說偈言：<q who="sakko">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1107a">
                <l>人當莫瞋恚<caesura/>見瞋莫瞋報</l>
                <l>於惡莫生惡<caesura/>當破壞憍慢</l>
                <l>不瞋亦不害<caesura/>名住賢聖眾</l>
                <l>惡罪起瞋恚<caesura/>堅住如石山</l>
                <l>盛瞋恚能持<caesura/>如制逸馬車</l>
                <l>我說善御士<caesura/>非謂執繩者</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>釋提桓因於三十三天為自在王，歎說不瞋。汝等如是正信非家，出家學道，亦應讚歎不瞋，當如是學。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
