<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 022. It is found in the 增壹阿含經 Sutra at T.02.0125.0697.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0125.0697b16">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0125.0697b16"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時。佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
        <p>爾時。世尊告諸比丘。昔者。釋提桓因告三十三天曰。若諸賢與阿須倫共鬪時。設阿須倫不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n12"/>如。諸天得勝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n13"/>者。汝等捉<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n14"/>毘摩質多羅阿須倫。將來至此。身為五繫。是時。毘摩質多羅阿須倫。復告諸阿須倫曰。卿等。今日與諸天共鬪。設得勝者。便捉釋提桓因。縛送此間。比丘當知。爾時。二家共鬪。諸天得勝。阿須倫不如。是時。三十三天躬捉毘摩質多羅阿須倫王。束縛其身。將詣釋提桓因所。著中門外。自觀<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n15"/>彼五繫。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>是時。毘摩質多羅阿須倫王便作是念。此諸天法<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n16"/>整。阿須倫所行非法。我今不樂阿須倫。便當即住此諸天宮。是時。以生此念言。諸天法<pb ed="T" n="0697c"/>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n16"/>整。阿須倫非法。我欲住此間。作此念已。是時。毘摩質多羅阿須倫王便自覺知身無縛繫。五欲而自娛樂。設毘摩質多羅阿須倫王生此念已。言。諸天非法。阿須倫法<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n16"/>整。我不用此三十三天。還<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n17"/>欲詣阿須倫宮。是時。阿須倫王身被五繫。五欲娛樂自然消滅。</p>
        <p>比丘當知。纏縛之急。莫過此事。魔之所縛。復甚於斯。設<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n18"/>與結使魔<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n02"/>以被<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n19"/>縛。動魔被縛。不動魔不被縛。是故。諸比丘。當求方便。使心不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n20"/>被縛。樂閑靜之處。所以然者。此諸結使是魔境界。若有比丘在魔境界者。終不脫生‧老‧病‧死。不脫愁‧憂‧苦‧惱。我今說此苦際。若復比丘心不移動。不著結使。便脫生‧老‧病‧死‧愁‧憂‧苦‧惱。我今說此苦際。是故。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n21"/>諸比丘。當<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0697n22"/>作是學。無有結使。越出魔界。如是。比丘。當作是學。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時。諸比丘聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
