<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1110">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0292b14"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>過去世時有天帝釋天、阿修羅對陣欲戰。釋提桓因語三十三天眾言：『今日諸天與阿修羅軍戰。諸天得勝，阿修羅不如者，當生擒毘摩質多羅阿修羅王，以五繫縛，將還天宮！』毘摩質多羅阿修羅王告阿修羅眾：『今日諸天、阿修羅共戰。若阿修羅勝，諸天不如者，當生擒釋提桓因，以五繫縛，將還阿修羅宮！』當其戰時，諸天得勝，阿修羅不如。時彼諸天捉得毘摩質多羅阿修羅王，以五繫縛，將還天宮，縛在帝釋斷法殿前門下。帝釋從此門入出之時，毘摩質多羅阿修羅縛在門側，瞋恚罵詈。時帝釋御者見阿修羅王身被五縛，在於門側，帝釋出入之時輒瞋恚罵詈。見已，即便說偈，白帝釋言：
                    <q who="sangahako">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1110a">
                <l>
                  <pb ed="T" n="0292c"/>釋今為畏彼<caesura/>為力不足耶</l>
                <l>能忍阿修羅<caesura/>面前而罵辱</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0292n11"/>釋即答言：<q who="sakko">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1110b">
                <l>不以畏故忍<caesura/>亦非力不足</l>
                <l>何有黠慧人<caesura/>而與愚夫對</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
                御者復白言：
                    <q who="sangahako">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1110c">
                <l>若但行忍者<caesura/>於事則有闕</l>
                <l>愚癡者當言<caesura/>畏怖故行忍</l>
                <l>是故當苦治<caesura/>以智制愚癡</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
                帝釋答言： 
                　　<q who="sakko">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1110d">
                <l>我常觀察彼<caesura/>制彼愚夫者</l>
                <l>見愚者瞋盛<caesura/>智以靜默伏</l>
                <l>非力而為力<caesura/>是彼愚癡力</l>
                <l>愚癡違遠法<caesura/>於道則無有</l>
                <l>若使有大力<caesura/>能忍於劣者</l>
                <l>是則為上忍<caesura/>無力何有忍</l>
                <l>於他極罵辱<caesura/>大力者能忍</l>
                <l>是則為上忍<caesura/>無力何所忍</l>
                <l>於己及他人<caesura/>善護大恐怖</l>
                <l>知彼瞋恚盛<caesura/>還自守靜默</l>
                <l>於二義俱備<caesura/>自利亦利<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0292n12"/>他</l>
                <l>謂言愚夫者<caesura/>以不見法故</l>
                <l>愚夫謂勝忍<caesura/>重增其惡口</l>
                <l>未知忍彼罵<caesura/>於彼常得勝</l>
                <l>於勝己行忍<caesura/>是名恐怖忍</l>
                <l>於等者行忍<caesura/>是名忍諍忍</l>
                <l>於劣者行忍<caesura/>是則為上忍</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>釋提桓因於三十三天為自在王，常行忍辱，讚歎於忍。汝等比丘正信非<pb ed="T" n="0293a"/>家，出家學道，亦應如是行忍，讚歎於忍，應當學。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0293n01"/>說經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
