<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1115">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0294c19"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>過去世時有一聚落，有諸仙人於聚落邊空閑處住止。時有諸天、阿修羅去聚落不遠，對陣戰鬪。爾時毘摩質多羅阿修羅王除去五飾，脫去天冠，却傘蓋，除劍刀，屏寶拂，脫革屣，至彼仙人住處，入於門內，周向看視，不顧眄諸仙人，亦不問訊。看已，還出。時有一仙人，遙見毘摩質多羅阿修羅王除去五飾入園，看已，還出。見已，語諸仙人言：<q who="isi">此何等人？有不調伏色，不似人形，非威儀法，似田<pb ed="T" n="0295a"/>舍兒，非長者子，除去五飾，入於園門，高視觀看，亦不顧眄，問訊諸仙人。</q>有一仙人答言：<q who="isi">此是毘摩質多羅阿修羅王，除去五飾，觀看而去。</q>彼仙人言：<q who="isi">此非賢士，不好不善，非賢非法，除去五飾，來入園門，看已，還去，亦不顧眄，問訊諸仙人。以是故，當知天眾增長，阿修羅損減！</q>時釋提桓因除去五飾，入仙人住處，與諸仙人面相問訊、慰勞，然後還出。復有仙人，見天帝釋除去五飾，入於園門，周遍問訊。見已，問諸仙人：<q who="sakko">此是何人？入於園林，有調伏色，有可適人色，有威儀色，非田舍兒，似族姓子，除去五飾，來入園門，周遍問訊，然後還出。</q>有仙人答言：<q who="isi">此是天帝釋，除去五飾，來入園門，周遍問訊，然後還去。</q>彼仙人言：<q who="isi">此是賢士，善好真實威儀法，除去五飾，來入園門，周遍問訊，然後還去。以是當知天眾增長，阿修羅眾損減！</q>
              時毘摩質多羅阿修羅王聞仙人稱歎諸天。聞已，瞋恚熾盛。時彼空處仙人聞阿修羅王瞋恚熾盛，往詣毘摩質多羅阿修羅王所，而說偈言：
                                  　
            <q who="isi">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1115a">
                <l>仙人故來此<caesura/>求乞施無畏</l>
                <l>汝能施無畏<caesura/>賜牟尼恩教</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
                    
                毘摩質多羅以偈答言：
                    <q who="vepacitti">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1115b">
                <l>於汝仙人所<caesura/>無有施無畏</l>
                <l>違背阿修羅<caesura/>習近帝釋故</l>
                <l>
                  <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0295n01"/>於此諸無畏<caesura/>當遺以恐怖</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
                    
                仙人復說偈言：
                <q who="isi">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1115c">
                <l>隨行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0295n02"/>殖種子<caesura/>隨類果報生</l>
                <pb ed="T" n="0295b"/>
                <l>來乞於無畏<caesura/>遺之以恐怖</l>
                <l>當獲無盡畏<caesura/>施畏種子故</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
                    時諸仙人於毘摩質多羅阿修羅王面前說呪已，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0295n03"/>凌虛而逝。即於是夜毘摩質多羅阿修羅王心驚三起，眠中聞惡聲言：<q who="voice">釋提桓因<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0295n04"/>興四種兵，與阿修羅戰。</q>驚覺恐怖，慮戰必敗，退走而還阿修羅宮。時天帝釋敵退，得勝已，詣彼空閑仙人住處，禮諸仙人足已，退於西面，諸仙人前東向而坐。時東風起，有異仙人，即說偈言：
                    <q who="isi">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1115d">
                <l>今此諸牟尼<caesura/>出家來日久</l>
                <l>腋下流汗臭<caesura/>莫順坐風下</l>
                <l>千眼可移坐<caesura/>此臭難可堪</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
                時天帝釋說偈答言：
                    <q who="sakko">
              <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1115e">
                <l>種種眾香華<caesura/>結以為華鬘</l>
                <l>今之所聞香<caesura/>其香復過是</l>
                <l>寧久聞斯香<caesura/>未曾生厭患</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>彼天帝釋於三十三天為自在王，恭敬出家人，亦常讚歎出家人，亦常讚歎恭敬之德。汝等比丘正信非家，出家學道，常應恭敬諸梵行者，亦當讚歎恭敬之德。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
