<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 046. It is found in the 優陂夷墮舍迦經 Sutra at T.01.0088.0912.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0088.0912a18">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0088.0912a18"/>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時佛在舍衛國止城東出。有女人子字蕪耶樓。人呼為蕪耶樓母。佛在蕪耶樓母家殿上坐。有一女人奉持教戒。字墮舍迦以月十五日朝起沐浴。有七子婦皆使沐浴著好衣。日未中因飯。飯已澡手。將七子婦至佛所前為佛作禮。佛言就座。皆却就座。佛問優<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0912n06"/>陂夷墮舍迦。今日何等沐浴著好衣。與子婦俱至佛所。墮舍迦言。今日十五日我齋戒。我聞一月當六齋。我與子婦俱共齋不敢懈慢。佛告墮舍迦。佛正齋法有八戒。使人得度世道。不復墮三惡處。所生常有福祐。亦從八戒本因緣致成佛。</p>
        <p>
          <pb ed="T" n="0912b"/>何等為佛正齋法。是間有賢善人持戒。一月六日齋。月八日一齋。十四日一齋。十五日一齋。二十三日一齋。二十九日一齋。三十日一齋。齋日朝起告家中言。今日我身齋。家中今一日。且莫飲酒莫鬪諍莫道說錢財。家中事意所念口所說。當如阿羅漢。阿羅漢無殺意。齋日持戒亦當如阿羅漢。無殺意無捶擊意。念畜生及虫蛾。使常生如阿羅漢意。是為一戒。今日與夜持殺意使不得殺。持意如是為佛一戒。</p>
        <p>佛言。齋日持意當如阿羅漢無貪心。無所貪慕於世間。無貪毛菜之意。齋日如是持意如阿羅漢。富有者。當念作布施。貧無有者。當當念施。是為二戒。
                    佛言。齋日持意當如阿羅漢。阿羅漢不畜婦亦不念婦。亦不貪女人亦無婬意。齋日如是持意如阿羅漢。是為三戒。
                    佛言。齋日持意當如阿羅漢。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0912n07"/>
            不妄語不傷人意。語即說佛經。不語者但念諸善。齋日如是持意如阿羅漢。是為四戒。
                                佛言。齋日持意當如阿羅漢。阿羅漢不飲酒。不念酒不思酒。用酒為惡。齋日如是持意如阿羅漢。是為五戒。
                                佛言。齋日持意當如阿羅漢。阿羅漢意不在歌舞。聞亦不喜音樂聲。亦不在香華氣。齋日如是持意如阿羅漢。是為六戒。
                                佛言。齋日持意當如阿羅漢。阿羅漢不於高好床臥。意亦不念高好床上臥。齋日如是持意如阿羅漢。是為七戒。
          <pb ed="T" n="0912c"/>佛言。齋日持意當如阿羅漢。阿羅漢日中<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0912n08"/>及食。日中已後至明不得復食。得飲蜜漿。齋日如是持意如阿羅漢。是為八戒。</p>
        <p>佛<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0912n09"/>復告優<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0912n04"/>陂夷墮舍迦。是間有人頭髮有垢自沐其頭。沐已其人便喜言。我頭垢已去。有人持八戒一日一夜者。明日即喜。喜者便<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0912n10"/>念佛經戒廼如是。其有人心中有惡意即去善意即還。</p>
        <p>佛言。有人身體饒垢入水中治。身垢皆去出水即喜言。我垢去身輕。其有人齋戒一日一夜。明日即喜念佛正語。自念當何時得道。使我心不復動不復走。使我心一志無為之道。佛言。有人衣多垢。以得灰浣之垢去。其人即喜。其有人齋戒一日一夜。明日即喜。便念比丘僧言。比丘僧中。有須陀洹斯陀含阿那含阿羅漢。念比丘僧如是。</p>
        <p>佛言。如人有鏡鏡有垢。磨去其垢鏡即明。其有人齋戒一日一夜。有慈心於天下。心開如明如鏡者。不當有瞋怒意。其有人一日一夜齋戒。閱哀天下。淨心自思自端其意。自思念身中惡露如是。如是者不當復瞋怒。</p>
        <p>佛告優<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0912n04"/>陂夷墮舍迦。持八戒齋一日一夜不失者。勝持金銀珠璣施與比丘僧也。天下有十六大國。一者名鴦迦。二者名摩竭。三者名迦夷。四者名拘薛羅。五者名鳩溜。六者名般闍荼。七者名阿波耶。八者名阿洹提渝。九者名脂提渝。十者名越祇渝。十一者名速摩。十二者名速賴吒。十三者名越蹉。十四者名末羅。十五者名渝匿。十六者名劍善提。是十六<pb ed="T" n="0913a"/>大國中珍寶物施與比丘僧。不如齋戒一日一夜也。齋戒使人得度世道。以財寶施與。不能使人得道。今我得佛道本從是八戒起。</p>
        <p>佛告墮舍迦。天下人多憂家事。我用是故。使一月六齋持八戒。若有賢善人。欲急得阿羅漢道者。若欲疾得佛道<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n01"/>者。若欲生天上者能自端其心一其意者。一月十五日齋亦善。二十日齋亦善。人多憂家事故與一月六齋。六日齋者。譬如海水不可斛量。其有齋戒一日一夜者。其福不可計。佛告墮舍迦。且將子婦歸。誦念是正齋法八戒也。優<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n02"/>陂夷墮舍迦。前為佛作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
