<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 046. It is found in the 佛說齋經 Sutra at T.01.0089.0913.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0089.0913a17">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0089.0913a17"/>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時婆迦婆在舍衛城祇樹給孤獨園。爾時世尊告諸比丘。我今當說聖八關齋。諦聽諦聽。善思念之。我今當說。對曰。如是世尊。</p>
        <p>爾時彼比丘從佛受教。世尊告曰。於是比丘。若信族姓子族姓女。欲知聖八關齋。便教某甲當作是說。猶如阿羅漢。盡形壽不殺生。亦不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n05"/>教人殺生。無怨恨心<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n06"/>當懷慚愧。有慈心愍一切眾生。我字某名某。為阿羅漢所教。自今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n07"/>日始隨意所欲不復殺生。無怨恨心常懷慚愧。有慈心愍一切眾生。猶如阿羅漢。盡<pb ed="T" n="0913b"/>形壽不盜好施。亦不教人盜。常樂閑處。如是我字某名某。為阿羅漢所教。隨意所欲不復盜竊。常懷惠施樂閑居處。猶如阿羅漢。盡形壽不習不淨行。常修梵行清淨無穢而自娛樂。如是我字某名某。為阿羅漢所教。自今已後不復婬妷。清淨無穢猶如阿羅漢。盡形壽不妄語。常行審諦。最尊最貴。諸尊長為世所貴。如是我字某名某。為彼阿羅漢所教。自今已後更不復妄語。亦不教人使習妄語。當行審諦。為世尊長不行妄語。猶如阿羅漢。亦不飲酒。如是我字某名某。自今已後隨意所欲亦不飲酒。亦不教人使飲酒。猶如阿羅漢。盡<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n08"/>形壽不犯齋。隨時食。如是我字某名某。今一日一夜隨意所欲亦不犯齋。亦不教人使犯齋。隨時食。猶如阿羅漢。盡形壽不於高好<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n09"/>床坐。如是我字某名某。今一日一夜不於高廣<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n09"/>床坐。亦不教人<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n10"/>使坐。猶如阿羅漢。盡形壽不習歌舞戲樂。亦不著<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n11"/>紋飾香熏塗身。今一日一夜不習歌舞戲樂。亦不著<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n11"/>紋飾香熏塗身。如是修行聖八關齋。於是八關齋中功德不可限量。言有爾所福爾所功德爾所福報。如是眾多福不可稱計。諸比丘。譬如五大流水皆同一處。所謂恒伽謠婆奴新頭<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0913n12"/>阿脂耶婆提摩棄。彼水所流處不可限量。言有爾所水有爾所瓶水。有爾所千瓶百千瓶水。如是聖八關齋福不可稱量。言有爾所福爾所功德爾所果報。此大福不可稱計。爾時諸比丘聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
