<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1226">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0334c13"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在拘薩羅人間遊行，至舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0334n19"/>波斯匿王聞世尊<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0334n20"/>拘薩羅人間遊行，至舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園，聞已，往詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>世尊！我聞世尊自記說成<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0334n21"/>阿耨多羅三藐三菩提。諸人傳者，得非虛妄過長說耶？為如說說，如法說，隨順法說耶？非是他人損同法者，於其問答生厭薄處耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告大王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>彼如是說，是真諦說，非為虛妄。如說說，如法說，隨順法說。非是他人損同法者，於其問答生厭薄處。所以者何？大王！我今實得阿耨多羅三藐三菩提故。</p>
        </q>
        <p>波斯匿王白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>雖復世尊作如是說，我猶故不信。所以者何？此間有諸宿重沙門婆羅門，所謂：<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0334n22"/>富蘭那迦葉、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0334n23"/>末迦利瞿舍梨子、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0334n24"/>刪闍耶毘羅胝子、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0334n25"/>阿耆多枳舍欽婆羅、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0334n26"/>迦羅拘陀迦栴延、尼乾陀若提子，彼等不<pb ed="T" n="0335a"/>自說言得阿耨多羅三藐三菩提。何得世尊幼小年少，出家未久，而便自證得阿耨多羅三藐三菩提？</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告大王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>有四種雖小，而不可輕。何等為四？剎利王子年少幼小，而不可輕。龍子年少幼小，而不可輕。小火雖微，而不可輕。比丘幼小，而不可輕。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1126a">
            <l>剎利形相具<caesura/>貴族發名稱</l>
            <l>雖復年幼稚<caesura/>智者所不輕</l>
            <l>此必居王位<caesura/>顧念生怨<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0335n01"/>害</l>
            <l>是故難可輕<caesura/>應生大恭敬</l>
            <l>善求自護者<caesura/>自護如護命</l>
            <l>以平等自護<caesura/>而等護於命</l>
            <l>聚落及空處<caesura/>見彼幼龍者</l>
            <l>莫以小蛇故<caesura/>而生輕慢想</l>
            <l>雜色小龍形<caesura/>亦應令安樂</l>
            <l>輕蛇無士女<caesura/>悉為毒所害</l>
            <l>是故自護者<caesura/>當如護己命</l>
            <l>以斯善護己<caesura/>而等護於彼</l>
            <l>猛火之所食<caesura/>雖小食無限</l>
            <l>小燭亦能燒<caesura/>足薪則彌廣</l>
            <l>從微漸進燒<caesura/>盡聚落城邑</l>
            <l>是故自護者<caesura/>當如護己命</l>
            <l>以斯善護己<caesura/>而等護於彼</l>
            <l>盛火之所焚<caesura/>百卉蕩燒盡</l>
            <l>滅已不盈縮<caesura/>戒火還復生</l>
            <l>若輕毀比丘<caesura/>受持淨戒火</l>
            <l>燒身及子孫<caesura/>眾災流百世</l>
            <l>如燒多羅樹<caesura/>無有生長期</l>
            <pb ed="T" n="0335b"/>
            <l>是故當自護<caesura/>如自護己命</l>
            <l>以斯善自護<caesura/>而等護於彼</l>
            <l>剎利形相具<caesura/>幼龍及小火</l>
            <l>比丘具淨戒<caesura/>不應起輕想</l>
            <l>是故當自護<caesura/>如自護己命</l>
            <l>以斯善自護<caesura/>而等護於彼</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，波斯匿王聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
