<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head xml:lang="sa">ku mā ra dri kṣṭā nta sū tra</head>
        <head xml:lang="bo">gzhon nu dpe'i mdo</head>
        <p>
          From the Derge edition. Derge 296. This is part of the text-cluster of BZA
                              (T.100) sutra 053.
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:lang="bo">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="der.71.sha.295b2"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          sangs rgyas dang/ byang chub sems dpa' thams cad la phyag 'tshal lo/ 'di skad
                                  bdag gis thos pa dus gcig na/ bcom ldan 'das kos la'i ljongs rgyu zhings
                                  shegs pa dang/ mnyan yod du byon nas mnyan yod na rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi
                                  tshal mgon med zas sbyin gyi kun dga' ra ba na bzhugs so/ ko sa la'i rgyal
                                  po gsal rgyal gyis dge sbyong gau ta ma ko sa la'i ljongs rgyu zhing gshegs
                                  pa dang/ mnyan yod du byon nas mnyan yod na rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal
                                  mgon med zas sbyin gyi kun dga' ra ba na bzhugs te/
        </p>
        <p>
          shes ldan gau ta ma de bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs pa'i byang chub
                                  mngon par sangs rgyas par bdag nyid zhal gyis 'che'o zhes thos so/ thos nas
                                  kyang bcom ldan 'das gang na bder song ste phyin nas/ bcom ldan 'das dang
                                  lhan cig mngon du yang dag par dga' ba dang/ yang dag par mgu bar 'gyur ba'i
                                  gtam rnam pa sna tshogs byas te phyogs gcig tu 'dug go/ phyogs gcig tu 'dug
                                  nas ko sa la'i rgyal po gsal rgyal gyis bcom ldan 'das la 'di skad ces gsol
                                  to/
        </p>
        <p>
          kye gau ta ma bdag gis shes ldan gau ta ma bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs
                                  pa'i byang chub mngon par sangs rgyas par bdag nyid zhal gyis 'che'o zhes
                                  thos lags na/ gau ta ma gang dag de skad ces lung bstan pa de dag ji ga dge
                                  sbyong gau ta ma la skur ba 'debs pa ma lags sam/ thal bar smra ba ma lags
                                  sam/ shes ldan gau ta mas gsungs pa bzhin smra pa lags sam/ chos smra ba
                                  lags sam/ chos dang 'thun pa'i chos lung ston pa lags sam/ ji ga de dag gi
                                  drung du pha rol po chos dang 'thun par rtsod pa'i rjes su rtsod pa mchis
                                  na/ smod pa'i chos kyi gnas su mi 'gyur lags sam/
        </p>
        <p>
          rgyal po chen po gang dag de skad smra ba de dag ni de skad du lung ston pa
                                  bden te/ nga la skur pa 'di 'debs pa ma yin/ thal bar smra ba ma yin/ de ni
                                  gsungs pa bzhin smra ba yin/ chos dang 'thun pa'i chos lung ston pa yin te/
                                  de dag gi drung du pha rol po chos dang 'thun pa'i rtsod pa'i rjes su rtsod
                                  pa 'ongs nas smod pa'i chos kyi gnas su mi 'gyur ro/ rgyal po chen po de
                                  ci'i phyir zhe na/ ngas bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs pa'i byang chub
                                  mngon par sangs rgyas so/
        </p>
        <p>
          shes ldan gau ta ma de skad mod kyi/ shes ldan gau ta ma bdag yid mi ches
                                  lags so/ de ci'i slad du zhe na/ kye gau ta ma re zhig rgan zhing rgan pa'i
                                  dge sbyong dang/ bram ze ni 'di dag lags te/ 'di lta ste/ 'od srung rdzogs
                                  byed dang/ kun du rgyu gnag lhas kyi dang/ smra 'dod kyi bu mo'i bu yang dag
                                  rgyal ba can dang/ mi pham skra'i la ba can dang/ ka tya'i bu nog can dang/
                                  gcer bu pa gnyen gyi bu gang lags pa de dag kyang da dung bla na med pa yang
                                  dag par rdzogs pa'i byang chub mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas par bdag
                                  nyid gyar gyis mi mchi lags na/ shes ldan gau ta ma 'khrungs nas ring po ma
                                  lags pa gsar du rab tu 'byung bas lta smos kyang ci 'tshal/
        </p>
        <p>
          rgyal po chen po gzhon nu bzhi po 'di dag la khyad du gsad par mi bya/ zil
                                  gyis mnan par mi bya ste/ bzhi gang zhe na/ rgyal po chen po rgyal rigs
                                  gzhon nu khyad du gsad par mi bya/ gzhon nu la zil gyis mnan par mi bya'o/
                                  rgyal po chen po sbrul gzhon nu la khyad du gsad par mi bya/ gzhon nu la zil
                                  gyis mnan par mi bya'o/ rgyal po chen po me chung ngu la khyad du gas par mi
                                  bya/ zil gyis mnan par mi bya'o/ rgyal po chen po dge slong gzhon nu la
                                  khyad du gsad par mi bya/ gzhon nu la zil gyis mnan par mi bya'o/ de ci'i
                                  phyir zhe na/ dge slong gshon nur gyur kyang de rdzu 'phrul che zhing mthu
                                  che ba'i dgra bcom par 'gyur ro/
        </p>
        <p>
          bcom ldan 'das kyis de skad ces/ bka' stsal nas ni bde gshes kyis/ de skad
                                  ces ni bka' stsal nas/ ston pas gzhan yang 'di skad gsungs/
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>rgyal rigs dpe med ldan pa dang/ rigs btsun grags par ldan pa la/</l>
          <l>blo dang ldan pas de dzhon zhes/ khyad du mi gsad zil mi man na/</l>
          <l>rgyal po rgyal rigs mkhas pa yis/ rgyal srid dag ni thob rgyur nas/</l>
          <l>chad pas gsod pa'i gnas de yod/ de bas de la shin tu gdung/</l>
          <l>de ltar rang gi srog srung zhing/ rang gi don la lta bas ni/</l>
          <l>de ni khyad du mi gsad cing/ de la legs par bag kyang bya/</l>
          <l>gal te grang ngam dgon pa'ng rung/ gang du sbrul ni mthong gyur na/</l>
          <l>blo dang ldan pas de gzhon zhes/ khyad du mi gsad bril mi mnan/</l>
          <l>'di ltar sbrul ni rgyur ba na/ rigs ni rnam pa sna tshogs la/</l>
          <l>glags rnyed nas ni gzhon nus kyang/ skyes pa bud med du ma zin/</l>
          <l>de ltas rang gi srog srung zhing/ rang gi ngon la lta bas ni/</l>
          <l>de ni khyad du mi gsad cing/ de la legs par bag kyang bya/</l>
          <l>'bar ba mang ba za byed pa/ byin za la ma sngon ldan pa de/</l>
          <l>chung yang khyad du mi gsad cing/ mkhas pas zil gyis mnan mi bya/</l>
          <l>nye bar len pas byin za ni/ chung ngu gyur las chen por 'gyur/</l>
          <l>me ltsel 'bar bas myur bar ni/ grong dang grong khyer sreg par byed/</l>
          <l>de phyir bdag srog srung byed pas/ de ni khyad du mi gsad cing/</l>
          <l>bdag nyid don la legs lta bas/ de la legs par bag kyang bya/</l>
          <l>byin bral ma sngon ldan gyur pa'i/ me yis tshang tshing gang bsregs pa/</l>
          <l>de la nyen mtshan 'das gyur pas/ la lar lo ma skye bar 'gyur/</l>
          <l>gang gis tshul khrims ldan pa yi/ dge slong rnyed nas sreg byed pa/</l>
          <l>de la bu dang tsha bo dang/ bgo skal yod par mi 'gyur te/</l>
          <l>ta la'i mgo bzhin mi ring bar/ rigs rgyud dang yang bral bar 'gyur/</l>
          <l>de phyir 'dag srog srung byed pas/ de ni khyad du gsad mi bya/</l>
          <l>bdag nyid don la legs lta bas/ de la legs par bag kyang bya/</l>
          <l>rgyal rigs dpe byad ldan pa dang/ brang 'gro me dang de bzhin du/</l>
          <l>dge slong tshul khrim ldan pa de/ mkhas pas thil gyis mnan mi bya/</l>
          <l>de phyir bdag srog srung byed pas/ de ni khyad du gsad mi bya/</l>
          <l>bdag nyid don la legs lta bas/ de ni legs par spang bar bya/</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          de nas ko sa la'i rgyal po gsal rgyal gyis bcom ldan 'das kyis bka' stsal pa
                                  la mngon par bstod cing rjes su yi rangs pa byas nas/ bcom ldan 'das kyi
                                  zhabs la mko bos phyag 'tshal te/ bcom ldan 'das kyi spyan snga nas phyir
                                  song ngo/ gzhon nu dpe'i mdo rdzogs so//
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
