<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 060. It is found in the 增壹阿含經 Sutra at T.02.0125.0612.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0125.0612c01">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0125.0612c01"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時。佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
        <p>爾時。舍衛城中<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n16"/>婆提長者遇病命終。然彼長者無有子息。所有財寶盡沒入官。爾時。王波斯匿塵土坌身來至世尊所。頭面禮足。在一面坐。</p>
        <p>是時。世尊問王曰。大王。何故塵土坌身來至我所。波斯匿王白世尊曰。此舍衛城內有長者名婆提。今日命終。彼無<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n17"/>子姓。躬往收攝財寶。理使入官。純金八萬斤。況復餘雜物乎。然彼長者存在之日。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n18"/>所食如此之食。極為<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n19"/>弊惡。不食精細。所著衣服垢坌不淨。所乘車騎極為瘦弱。世尊告曰。如是。大王。如王來言。夫慳貪之人得此財貨。不能<choice>
            <sic>貪</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">食</corr>
          </choice>噉。不與父母‧妻子‧僕從‧奴婢。亦復不與朋友‧知識。亦復不與沙門‧婆羅門‧諸尊長者。若有智之士得此財寶。便能惠施廣濟。一切無所愛惜。供給沙門‧婆羅門‧諸高德者。</p>
        <p>時。王波斯匿說曰。此婆提長者命終為生何處。世尊告曰。此婆提長者命終生<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n20"/>涕哭大地獄中。所以然者。此斷善根之人。身壞命終。生<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n20"/>涕哭地獄中。波斯匿王曰。婆提長者斷善根耶。世尊告曰。如是。大王。如王所說。彼長者斷於善根。然彼長者故福已盡。更不造新。王波斯匿曰。彼長者頗有遺餘福乎。世尊告曰。無也。大王。乃無毫釐之餘<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n21"/>有存在者。如彼田家公。但收不種。後<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n22"/>便窮困。漸以命終。所以然者。但食故業。更不造新。此長者亦復如是。但食故福。更不造新福。此長者今夜當在<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n20"/>涕哭地獄中。</p>
        <p>爾時。波斯匿王便懷恐怖。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0612n23"/>收淚而曰。此長者<pb ed="T" n="0613a"/>昔日作何功德福業生在富家。復作何不善根本。不得食此極富之貨。不樂五樂之中。爾時。世尊告波斯匿王曰。過去久遠迦葉佛時。此長者在此舍衛城中為田家子。爾時。佛去世後。有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n01"/>辟支佛出世。往詣此長者家。爾時。此長者見辟支佛在門<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n02"/>外。見已。便生是念。如此尊者出世甚難。我今可以飲食往施此人。爾時。長者便施彼辟支佛<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n03"/>食。辟支佛得食已。便飛在虛空而去。時。彼長者見辟支佛作神足。作是誓願。持此善本之願。使<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n04"/>世世所生之處。不墮三惡趣。常多財<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n05"/>寶。後有悔心。我向所有食。應與奴僕。不與此禿頭道人使食。爾時。田家<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n06"/>長者豈異人乎。莫作是觀。所以然者。爾時田家長者。今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n07"/>此婆提長者是。</p>
        <p>是時施已。發此誓願。持此功德。所生之處不墮惡趣。恒多財饒寶。生富貴之家。無所渴乏。既復施已。後生悔心。我寧與奴僕使食。不與此禿頭道人使食。以此因緣本末。不得食此極有之貨。亦復不樂五樂之中。不自供養。復不與父母‧兄弟‧妻子‧僕從‧朋友‧知識。不施沙門‧婆羅門‧諸尊長者。但食故業。不造新者。是故。大王。若有智之士得此財貨。當廣布施。莫有所惜。復當得<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n08"/>無極之財。如是。大王。當作是學。</p>
        <p>爾時。波斯匿王白世尊曰。自今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0609n27"/>以後。當廣布施<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n09"/>沙門‧婆羅門四部之眾。諸外道‧異學來乞求者。我不堪與。世尊告曰。大王。莫作是念。所以然者。一切眾生皆由食得存。無食便喪。爾時。世尊便說此偈。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <pb ed="T" n="0613b"/>
          <l>念當廣惠施<caesura/>終莫斷施心</l>
          <l>必當值<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n10"/>賢聖<caesura/>度此生死<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n11"/>源</l>
        </lg>
        <p>爾時。波斯匿王白世尊曰。我今倍<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n12"/>復歡慶<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n13"/>於向<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n14"/>如來。所以然者。一切眾生皆由食得存。無食不存。爾時。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0613n15"/>波斯匿王曰。自今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0609n27"/>以後。當廣惠施。無所悋惜。是時。世尊與王說微妙之法。時。王即從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0601n12"/>坐起。頭面禮足。便退而去。</p>
        <p>爾時。王波斯匿聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
