<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 065. It is found in the 增壹阿含經 Sutra at T.02.0125.0768.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0125.0768c06">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0125.0768c06"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時。佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
        <p>爾時。阿難白世尊言。所謂善知識者。即是半梵行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n19"/>
            之人也。將引善道以至無為。
                            佛告阿難。勿作是言。言善知識者。即是半梵行之人。所以然者。夫善知識
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n19"/>之人。即是全梵行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n19"/>之人。與共從事。將視好道。我亦由善知識成無上正真等正覺。以成道果。度脫眾生不可稱計。皆悉免生‧老‧病‧死。以此方便。知夫善知識<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n19"/>之人。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n20"/>全梵行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n19"/>之人也。</p>
        <p>復次。阿難。若善男子‧善女人與善知識共從事者。信根增益。聞‧施‧慧德皆悉備具。猶如月欲盛滿。光明漸增。倍於常時。此亦如是。若有善男子‧善女人親近善知識。信‧聞‧念‧施‧慧皆悉增益。以此方便。知其善知識者即是全梵行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n19"/>之人也。</p>
        <p>若我昔日不與善知識從事。終不為<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n21"/>燈光佛所見授決也。以與善知識從事故。得為與提和竭羅佛所見授決。以此方便。知其善知識者。即是全梵行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n19"/>之人也。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n22"/>若當。阿難。世間無善知識者。則無有尊卑之<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0765n18"/>敘。父母‧師長‧兄弟‧宗親。則與彼猪犬之屬與共一類。造諸惡緣。種地獄罪緣。有善知識故。便別有父母‧師長‧兄弟‧宗親。</p>
        <p>是時。世尊便說此偈。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>善知識非惡<caesura/>親法非為食</l>
          <pb ed="T" n="0769a"/>
          <l>將<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0769n01"/>導於善路<caesura/>此親最尊說</l>
        </lg>
        <p>是故。阿難。勿復更說言。善知識者是半梵行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0768n19"/>之人也。</p>
        <p>爾時。阿難從佛受教聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
