<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1239">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0339b13"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時波斯匿王獨靜思惟，作是念：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>頗有一法，修習、多修習，得現法願滿足，後世願滿足，現法、後世願滿足不？</p>
        </q>
        <p>作是念已，往詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>世尊！我獨靜思惟，作是念：<q who="pasenadi">頗有一法，修習、多修習，得現法願滿足，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0339n04"/>得後世願滿足，現法、後世願滿足不？</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告波斯匿王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>如是，大王！如是，大王！有一法，修習、多修習，得現法願滿足，得後世願滿足，得現法、後世願滿足，謂不放逸善法。不放逸善法修習、多修習，得現法願滿足，得後世願滿足，得現法、後<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0339n05"/>世願滿足。大王！譬如世間所作麁業，彼一切皆依於地而得建立。不放逸善法亦復如是，修習、多修習，得現法願滿足，得後<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0339n06"/>世願滿足，得現法、後法願滿足。如力，如是種子、根、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0339n07"/>堅，陸、水足行、師子、舍宅 亦如是說。是故──大<pb ed="T" n="0339c"/>王！──當住不放逸，當依不放逸。住不放逸，依不放逸已，夫人當作是念：<q who="gotamo">大王住不放逸，依不放逸。我今亦當如是住不放逸，依不放逸。</q>如是夫人，如是大臣、太子、猛將亦如是。國土人民應當念：<q who="gotamo">大王住不放逸，依不放逸。夫人、太子、大臣、猛將住不放逸，依不放逸。我等亦應如是住不放逸，依不放逸。</q>大王！若住不放逸，依不放逸者，則能自護；夫人、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0339n08"/>婇女亦能自保；<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0339n09"/>倉藏財寶增長豐實。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1239a">
            <l>稱譽不放逸<caesura/>毀<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0339n10"/>呰放逸者</l>
            <l>帝釋不放逸<caesura/>能主忉利天</l>
            <l>稱譽不放逸<caesura/>毀<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0339n10"/>呰放逸者</l>
            <l>不放逸具足<caesura/>攝持於二義</l>
            <l>一者現法利<caesura/>二後世亦然</l>
            <l>是名無間等<caesura/>甚深智慧者</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，波斯匿王聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
