<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 067. It is found in the 增壹阿含經 Sutra at T.02.0125.0637.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0125.0637a18">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0125.0637a18"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時。佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">爾時。尊者阿難至世尊所。頭面禮足。在一面住。斯須。復以兩手摩如來足已。復以口鳴如來足上。而作是說。天尊之體。何故乃爾。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n07"/>身極緩<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n08"/>
              爾。如來之身不如本故。
                                  世尊告曰。如是。阿難。如汝所言。今如來身皮肉
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n09"/>已緩。今日之體不如本故。所以然者。夫受形體。為病所逼。若應病眾生。為病所困。應死眾生。為死所逼。今日如來。年<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n09"/>
              已衰微。年過八十。
                                  是時。阿難聞此語已。悲泣
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n10"/>哽噎。不能自勝。並作是語。咄嗟。老至乃至於斯。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>是時。世尊到時。著衣持鉢。入舍衛城乞<pb ed="T" n="0637b"/>食。是時。世尊漸漸乞食。至王波斯匿舍。當於爾時。波斯匿門前。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n11"/>有故壞車數十乘。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n12"/>捨在一面。是時。尊者阿難以見車棄在一面。見已。白世尊曰。此<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n13"/>車王波斯匿車。昔日作時極為精妙。如今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n14"/>
            日觀之。與瓦石同色。
                            世尊告曰。如是。阿難。如汝所言。如今觀所有車。昔日之時極為精妙。金銀所造。今日壞敗。不可復用。如是外物尚壞敗。況復內者。
                                爾時。世尊便說此偈。
          </p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>咄此老病死<caesura/>壞人極盛色</l>
          <l>初時甚悅意<caesura/>今為死使逼</l>
          <l>雖當<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n15"/>壽百歲<caesura/>皆當歸於死</l>
          <l>無<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n16"/>免此患苦<caesura/>盡當歸此道</l>
          <l>如內身所有<caesura/>為死之所驅</l>
          <l>外諸四大者<caesura/>悉<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n17"/>趣於本無</l>
          <l>是故求無死<caesura/>唯有涅槃耳</l>
          <l>彼無死無生<caesura/>都無此諸行</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>爾時。世尊即就波斯匿王坐。是時。王波斯匿與世尊辦種種飲食。觀世尊食竟。王更取一小座。在如來前坐。白世尊曰。云何。世尊。諸佛形體皆金剛數。亦當有老‧病‧死乎。世尊告曰。如是。大王。如大王語。如來亦當有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n18"/>此生‧老‧病‧死。我今亦是人數。父名真淨。母名摩耶。出轉輪聖王種。</p>
        <p>爾時。世尊便說此偈。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>諸佛出於人<caesura/>父名曰真淨</l>
          <l>母名極清妙<caesura/>豪族<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n19"/>剎利種</l>
          <l>死徑<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n20"/>為極困<caesura/>都不觀尊卑</l>
          <l>諸佛尚不免<caesura/>況復餘凡俗</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <pb ed="T" n="0637c"/>爾時。世尊與波斯匿王而說此偈。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>祠祀火為上<caesura/>詩書頌為尊</l>
          <l>人中王為貴<caesura/>眾流海為首</l>
          <l>眾星月為上<caesura/>光明日為先</l>
          <l>八方上下中<caesura/>世界之所載</l>
          <l>天及世人民<caesura/>如來最為尊</l>
          <l>其欲求福祿<caesura/>當供養三佛</l>
        </lg>
        <p>是時。世尊說此偈已。便從座起而去。還<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0636n04"/>
            祇洹精舍。就座而坐。                
                                爾時。世尊告諸比丘。有四法。在世間人所愛敬。云何為四。少壯之年。世間人民之所愛敬。無有病痛。人所愛敬。壽命人所愛敬。恩愛集聚。人所愛敬。是謂。比丘。有此四法。世間人民之所愛敬。
          </p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>復次。比丘復有四法。世間人民所不愛敬。云何為四。比丘當知。少壯之年。若<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n21"/>時老病。世人所不喜。若無病者。後便得病。世人所不喜。若有得壽命。後便命終。世人所不喜。恩愛得集。後復別離。是世人所不喜。是謂。比丘。有此四法與世迴轉。諸天‧世人。乃至轉輪聖王‧諸佛世尊。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n22"/>共有此法。是為。比丘。世間有此四法與世迴轉。</p>
        <p>若不覺此四法時。便流轉生死。周旋五道。云何為四。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n23"/>聖賢戒‧賢聖三昧‧賢聖智慧‧賢聖解脫。是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n24"/>為。比丘。有此四法而不覺知者。則受上四法。我今及汝等。以覺知此賢聖四法。斷生死根。不復受有。如今如來形體衰老。當受此衰耗之報。是故。諸比丘。當求此永寂涅槃。不生‧不老‧不病‧不死。恩愛別離。常念無常之變。如是。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n25"/>比丘。當作是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0637n26"/>念。</p>
        <p>爾時。諸比丘聞佛所<pb ed="T" n="0638a"/>說。歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
