<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1146">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0304b27"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時波斯匿王來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>云何──世尊！──為婆羅門，死<pb ed="T" n="0304c"/>還生自姓婆羅門家？剎利、鞞舍、首陀羅家耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>大王！何得如是？大王！當知有四種人。何等為四？有一種人，從冥入冥。有一種人，從冥入明。有一種人，從明入冥。有一種人，從明入明。大王！云何為一種人從冥入冥？謂有人生卑姓家，若生<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0304n12"/>旃陀羅家、魚獵家、竹作家、車師家及餘種種下賤、工巧業家，貧窮<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0304n13"/>短命，形體<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0304n14"/>憔悴，而復修行卑賤之<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0304n15"/>家，亦復為人下賤作使，是名為冥。處斯冥中，復行身惡行，行口惡行，行意惡行。以是因緣，身壞命終，當生惡趣，墮<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0304n16"/>
              泥梨中。猶如有人從闇入闇，從廁入廁，以血洗血，捨惡受惡。從冥入冥者，亦復如是。是故名為從冥入冥。 
                              云何名為從冥入明？謂有世人生卑姓家，……（乃至）為人作諸鄙業，是名為冥。然其彼人於此冥中，行身善行，行口善行，行意善行。以是因緣，身壞命終，生於善趣，受天化生。譬如有人登床跨馬，從馬昇象。從冥入明，亦復如是。是名有人從冥入明。
                                  云何有人從明入冥？謂有世人生富樂家，若剎利大姓、婆羅門大姓家、長者大姓家及餘種種富樂家生，多諸錢財、奴婢、客使，廣集知識，受身端正，聰明黠慧，是名為明。於此明中，行身惡行，行口惡行，行意惡行。以是因緣，身壞命終，生於惡趣，墮
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0304n16"/>
              泥梨中。譬如有人從高樓下，乘於大象，下象乘馬，下馬乘輿，下輿坐床，下床墮地，從地落坑。從明入冥者，亦復如是 。
                                  云何有人從明入明？謂有世人生富樂家，……（乃
            <pb ed="T" n="0305a"/>至）形相端嚴，是名為明。於此明中，行身善行，行口善行，行意善行。以是因緣，身壞命終，生於善趣，受天化生。譬如有人從樓觀至樓觀。如是……（乃至）從床至床。從明入明者，亦復如是。是名有人從明入明。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1146a">
            <l>貧窮困苦者<caesura/>不信增瞋恨</l>
            <l>慳貪惡邪想<caesura/>癡惑不恭敬</l>
            <l>見沙門道士<caesura/>持戒多聞者</l>
            <l>毀<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n01"/>呰而不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n02"/>譽<caesura/>障他施及受</l>
            <l>如斯等士夫<caesura/>從此至他世</l>
            <l>當墮<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0304n16"/>泥梨中<caesura/>從冥入於冥</l>
            <l>若有貧窮人<caesura/>信心少瞋<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n03"/>恨</l>
            <l>常生慚愧心<caesura/>惠施離慳<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n04"/>垢</l>
            <l>見沙門梵志<caesura/>持戒多聞者</l>
            <l>謙虛而問訊<caesura/>隨宜善供給</l>
            <l>勸人令施與<caesura/>歎施及受者</l>
            <l>如是修善人<caesura/>從此至他世</l>
            <l>善趣上<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n05"/>生天<caesura/>從冥而入明</l>
            <l>有富樂士夫<caesura/>不信多瞋恨</l>
            <l>慳貪<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n06"/>疾惡想<caesura/>邪惑不恭敬</l>
            <l>見沙門梵志<caesura/>毀<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n01"/>呰而不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n02"/>譽</l>
            <l>障他人施惠<caesura/>亦斷受施者</l>
            <l>如是惡士夫<caesura/>從此至他世</l>
            <l>當生苦地獄<caesura/>從明入冥中</l>
            <l>若有富士夫<caesura/>信心不瞋恨</l>
            <l>常起慚愧心<caesura/>惠施離瞋<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n07"/>姤</l>
            <l>見沙門梵志<caesura/>持戒多聞者</l>
            <l>先奉迎問訊<caesura/>隨宜給所須</l>
            <pb ed="T" n="0305b"/>
            <l>勸人令供養<caesura/>歎施及受者</l>
            <l>如是等士夫<caesura/>從此至他世</l>
            <l>生三十三天<caesura/>從明而入明</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，波斯匿王聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
