<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1147">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0305b06"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時波斯匿王<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n09"/>日日身蒙塵土，來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面。佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>大王！從何所來？</p>
        </q>
        <p>波斯匿王白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>世尊！<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n10"/>彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n11"/>灌頂王法，人中自在，精勤方便。王領大地，統理王事，周行觀察，而來至此。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告大王：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>今問大王，隨意答我。譬如有人從東方來，有信有緣，未曾虛妄，而白王言：<q who="puriso">我東方來，見一石山，極方廣大，不穿不壞，亦無缺壞，磨地而來。一切眾生、草木之類，悉磨令碎。</q>南、西、北方，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n12"/>亦有人來，有信有緣，亦不虛妄，而白王言：<q who="puriso">我見石山，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n13"/>方廣高大，不斷不壞，亦不缺壞，磨地而來。眾生、草木，悉皆磨碎。</q>大王！於意云何：如是像貌，大恐怖事，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n14"/>嶮惡相殺，眾生運盡。人道難得，當作何計？</p>
        </q>
        <p>王白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>若如是者，更無餘計。唯當修善，於佛法、律專心方便。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告大王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>何故說言：嶮惡恐怖，於世卒起，眾生運盡。人身難得，唯當行法、行義、行福，於佛法教，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n15"/>專精方便？何以不言：灌頂王位，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n16"/>眾人<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0305n17"/>人首，堪能自在。王於大地，事務眾人，當須營理耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>王白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p>世尊！為復閑時言：灌頂王位，為眾人首。王於大地，多所經營，以言鬪言，以財鬪財，以象鬪象，以車鬪車，以步鬪步。<pb ed="T" n="0305c"/>當於爾時無有自在，若勝若伏。是故我說：嶮惡恐怖，卒起之時，眾生運盡。人身難得，無有餘計，唯有行義、行法、行福，於佛法教，專心歸依。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告大王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>如是，如是，經常磨迮，謂惡劫、老、病、苦，磨迮眾生，當作何計？正當修義、修法、修福、修善、修慈，於佛法中精勤方便。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1147a">
            <l>如有大石山<caesura/>高廣無缺壞</l>
            <l>周遍四方來<caesura/>磨迮此大地</l>
            <l>非兵馬呪術<caesura/>力所能防禦</l>
            <l>惡劫老病死<caesura/>常磨迮眾生</l>
            <l>四種大族姓<caesura/>栴陀羅獵師</l>
            <l>在家及出家<caesura/>持戒犯戒者</l>
            <l>一切皆磨迮<caesura/>無能救護者</l>
            <l>是故慧士夫<caesura/>觀察自己利</l>
            <l>建立清淨信<caesura/>信佛法僧寶</l>
            <l>身口心清淨<caesura/>隨順於正法</l>
            <l>現世名稱流<caesura/>終則生天上</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，波斯匿王聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
