<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1149">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0306a21"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時波斯匿王為首，并七國王及諸大臣悉共集會，作如是論議：</p>
        <q who="rajano">
          <p>五欲之中，何者第一？</p>
        </q>
        <p>有一人言：</p>
        <q who="ekacca">
          <p>色最第一。</p>
        </q>
        <p>又復有稱聲、香、味、觸為第一者。中有人言：</p>
        <q who="ekacca">
          <p>我等人人各說第一，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n09"/>竟無定<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n10"/>判。當詣世尊，問<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n11"/>如此義。如世尊說，當共憶持。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時波斯匿王為首，與七國王、大臣、眷屬來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="rajano">
          <p>世尊！我等七王與諸大<pb ed="T" n="0306b"/>臣如是論議：<q who="rajano">五欲功德，何者為勝？</q>其中有言：<q who="ekacca">色勝</q>；有言：<q who="ekacca">聲勝</q>；有言：<q who="ekacca">香勝</q>；有言：<q who="ekacca">味勝</q>；有言：<q who="ekacca">觸勝</q>，竟無決定。來問世尊，竟何者勝？</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告諸王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>各隨意適，我悉有餘說。以是因緣，我說五欲功德。然自有人於色適意，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n12"/>止愛一色，滿其志願，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n13"/>正使過上有諸勝色，非其所愛，不觸不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n14"/>視，言：<q who="gotamo">
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n15"/>己所愛最為第一，無過其上。</q>如愛色者，聲、香、味、觸，亦皆如是。當其所愛，輒言最勝，歡喜樂著。雖更有勝過其上者，非其所欲，不觸不視：<q who="gotamo">唯我愛者，最勝最妙，無比無上。</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時座中有一優婆塞，名曰<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n16"/>栴檀，從座起，整衣服，偏袒右肩，合掌白佛：</p>
        <q who="candano">
          <p>善說，世尊！善說，善逝！</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告優婆塞：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>善說，栴檀！快說，栴檀！</p>
        </q>
        <p>時栴檀優婆塞即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="candano">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1149a">
            <l>央伽族姓王<caesura/>服<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n17"/>珠瓔珞鎧</l>
            <l>摩<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n18"/>竭眾慶集<caesura/>如來出其國</l>
            <l>名聞普流布<caesura/>猶如雪山王</l>
            <l>如淨<choice>
                <sic>永</sic>
                <corr resp="CBETA">水</corr>
              </choice>蓮華<caesura/>清淨無瑕穢</l>
            <l>隨日光開敷<caesura/>芬香熏其國</l>
            <l>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n19"/>央耆國明顯<caesura/>猶如空中日</l>
            <l>觀如來慧力<caesura/>如夜然炬火</l>
            <l>為眼為大明<caesura/>來者為決疑</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>時諸國王歎言：</p>
        <q who="rajano">
          <p>善說，栴檀優婆塞！</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時七王脫七寶上衣，奉優婆塞。時彼七王聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，從座起去。爾時栴檀優婆塞知諸王去已，從座起，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0306n20"/>整衣服，偏袒右肩，合掌白佛：</p>
        <q who="candano">
          <p>今七國王遺我七領上衣。唯願世尊受此七衣，以哀愍故！</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊為哀愍故，受其七衣。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>栴檀優<pb ed="T" n="0306c"/>婆塞歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
