<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 072. It is found in the 增壹阿含經 Sutra at T.02.0125.0681.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0125.0681c16">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0125.0681c16"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時。佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
        <p>爾時。五大國王<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0681n25"/>波斯匿為首。集在園觀之中。各作此論。<seg type="not-parallel">云何為五王。所謂波斯匿王‧毘沙王‧優填王‧惡生王‧優陀延王。</seg>
            爾時。五王集在一處。各作此論。諸賢當知。如來說此五欲。云何為五。若眼見色甚愛敬念。世人所希望。若耳聞聲‧鼻嗅香‧舌知味‧身知細滑。如來說此五欲。此五欲中何者最妙。為眼見色妙耶。為耳聞聲妙耶。為鼻嗅香妙耶。為舌知味妙耶。為身知細滑妙耶。此五事何者為最妙。
                                其中或有國王而作是說。色最為妙。或有作是論。聲最為妙。或有作是論。香最為
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0681n26"/>勝。或有作是論。味最為妙。或有作<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0681n27"/>是論。細滑<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0681n28"/>為最勝。<seg type="not-parallel">是<pb ed="T" n="0682a"/>時。言色妙者。優陀延王之所說也。言聲妙者。優填王之所論也。言香妙者。惡生王之所論也。言味妙者。波斯匿王之所論也。言細滑妙者。毘沙王之所<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n01"/>論也。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>是時。五王各相謂言。我等<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n02"/>
            共論此五欲。然復不知何者為妙。
                            是時。波斯匿王語四王曰。今如來近在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。我等盡共至世尊所。問斯義。若世尊有所教勅。當共奉行。
                                是時。諸王聞波斯匿王語已。便共相將至世尊所。頭面禮足。在一面坐。是時。波斯匿王
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n03"/>以所共論五欲者。具白如來。</p>
        <p>爾時。世尊告諸五王曰。諸王所論各隨時宜。所以然者。夫人性行<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n04"/>深著色者。覩無厭足。此人於色最妙‧最上。無復過者。爾時。彼人不著聲‧香‧味‧細滑之法。五欲之中色為最妙。</p>
        <p>若復有人性行著聲。彼聞聲已。極懷歡喜而無厭足。此人於聲最妙‧最上。五欲之中聲最為妙。</p>
        <p>若復有人性行著香。彼聞香已。極懷歡喜而無厭足。此人於香最妙‧最上。五欲之中香最為妙。</p>
        <p>若復有人性行著味。彼知味已。極懷歡喜而無厭足。此人於味最妙‧最上。五欲之中味最為妙。</p>
        <p>若復有人性行著細滑。彼得細滑已。極懷歡喜而無厭足。此人於細滑最<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n05"/>上‧最妙。五欲之中細滑最為妙。</p>
        <p>若復彼人心以著色。爾時<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n06"/>彼人不著聲‧香‧味‧細滑之法。若復彼人性行著聲。爾時彼人不著色‧香‧味‧細滑之法。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n07"/>若復彼人性行著香。爾時彼人不著色‧<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n08"/>聲‧味‧細滑之法。若復彼人性行著味。爾時<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n09"/>彼人不著色‧聲‧<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n10"/>香‧細滑<pb ed="T" n="0682b"/>之法。若復彼人性行著細滑。爾時<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n11"/>彼人不著色‧聲‧香‧味之法。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>是時。世尊便說此偈。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>欲意熾盛時<caesura/>所欲必可<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n12"/>克</l>
          <l>得已倍歡喜<caesura/>所願無有疑</l>
          <l>彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n13"/>以得此欲<caesura/>貪欲意不解</l>
          <l>以此為歡喜<caesura/>緣之最為妙</l>
          <l>若<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n14"/>復聽聲時<caesura/>所欲必可<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n12"/>克</l>
          <l>聞已倍歡喜<caesura/>所願無有疑</l>
          <l>彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n13"/>以得此聲<caesura/>貪之意不解</l>
          <l>以此為歡喜<caesura/>從之<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n15"/>最為妙</l>
          <l>若復嗅香時<caesura/>所欲必可<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n12"/>克</l>
          <l>嗅已倍歡喜<caesura/>所<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n16"/>欲無有疑</l>
          <l>彼以得此香<caesura/>貪之意不解</l>
          <l>以此為歡喜<caesura/>從之最為妙</l>
          <l>若復得味時<caesura/>所欲必可<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n12"/>克</l>
          <l>得已倍歡喜<caesura/>所欲無有疑</l>
          <l>彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n13"/>以得此味<caesura/>貪之意不解</l>
          <l>以此為歡喜<caesura/>從之最為妙</l>
          <l>若得細滑時<caesura/>所欲必可<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n12"/>克</l>
          <l>得已倍歡喜<caesura/>所欲無疑難</l>
          <l>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n17"/>彼以得細滑<caesura/>貪之意不解</l>
          <l>以此為歡喜<caesura/>從之最為妙</l>
        </lg>
        <p>是故。大王。若言色妙者。當平等論之。所以然者。於色有氣<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n18"/>味。若色無味者。眾生終不染著。以其有味故。五欲之中色為最妙。然色有過失。若當色無過失。眾生則<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n19"/>無厭患。以其有過失故。眾生厭患之。然色有出要。若當色無出要者。此眾生類不得出生死之海。以其出要故。眾生得至無畏涅槃<pb ed="T" n="0682c"/>城中。五欲之中色為最妙。</p>
        <p>然復。大王。若言聲妙者。當平等論之。所以然者。於聲有氣味故。若聲無味者。眾生終不染著。以其有味故。五欲之中聲為最妙。然聲有過失。若當聲無過失。眾生則<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n19"/>無厭患。以其有過失故。眾生厭患之。然聲有出要。若當聲無出要者。此眾生類不得出生死之海。以其出要故。眾生得至無畏涅槃城中。五欲之中聲為最妙。</p>
        <p>大王當知。若言香妙者。當平等論之。所以然者。於香有氣味故。若香無氣味者。眾生之類終不染著。以其有味故。五欲之中香為最妙。然香有過失。若香無過失者。眾生則不厭患。以其有過失故。眾生厭患之。然香有出要。若當香無出要者。此眾生類不得出生死之海。以其出要故。眾生得至無畏涅槃城中。五欲之中香為最妙。</p>
        <p>然復。大王。若言味妙者。當平等論之。所以然者。於味有氣味故。若味無氣味者。眾生之類終不染著。以其有氣味故。五欲之中味為最妙。然味有過失。若當味無過失者。眾生則不厭患。以其有過失故。眾生厭患之。然味有出要。若當味無出要者。此眾生類不得出生死之海。以其出要故。眾生得至無畏涅槃城<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n20"/>中。味為最妙。</p>
        <p>然復。大王當知。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n21"/>言細滑妙者。當平等論之。所以然者。於細<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n22"/>滑無氣味者。眾<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n23"/>生終不染著。以其有味故。五欲之中細滑為最妙。然細滑有過失。若細滑無過失者。眾生之類則不厭患之。以其有過失故。眾生厭患之。<pb ed="T" n="0683a"/>然細滑有出要。若當細滑無出要者。此眾生類不得出生死之海。以其出要故。眾生得至無畏涅槃城中。五欲之中細滑<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0682n01"/>為最妙。是故。大王。所樂之處。心即染著。如是。大王。當作是知。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="parallel">爾時。五王聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
