<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1178">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0317b19"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住彌絺羅國菴羅園中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有婆四吒婆羅門尼，有六子相續命終，念子發狂，裸形被髮，隨路而走，至彌絺羅菴羅園中。爾時世尊無量大眾圍繞說法。婆四吒婆羅門尼遙見世尊。見已，即得本心，慚愧羞恥，歛身蹲坐。爾時世尊告尊者阿難：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>取汝鬱多羅僧，與彼婆四吒婆羅門尼，令著聽法。</p>
          </q>尊者阿難即受佛教，取衣令著。時<pb ed="T" n="0317c"/>婆羅門尼得衣著已，至於佛前，稽首禮佛，退坐一面。爾時世尊為其說法，示、教、照、喜已，如佛常法說法次第，……（乃至）信心清淨，受三自歸，聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。彼婆四吒優婆夷於後時第七子忽復命終，彼優婆夷都不啼哭，憂、悲、惱、苦。時婆四吒優婆夷夫說偈而告婆四吒優婆夷言：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1178a">
            <l>先諸子命終<caesura/>念子生憂苦</l>
            <l>晝夜不飲食<caesura/>乃至發狂亂</l>
            <l>今喪<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0317n21"/>弟七子<caesura/>而不生憂苦</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>婆四吒優婆夷即復說偈答其夫言：</p>
        <q who="vasetthi">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1178b">
            <l>兒孫有千數<caesura/>因緣和合生</l>
            <l>長夜遷過去<caesura/>我與君亦然</l>
            <l>子孫及宗族<caesura/>其數無限量</l>
            <l>彼彼所生處<caesura/>更互相殘食</l>
            <l>若知生<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0317n22"/>要者<caesura/>何足生憂苦</l>
            <l>我已知出離<caesura/>生死存亡相</l>
            <l>不復生憂苦<caesura/>入佛正教故</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>時婆四吒優婆夷夫說偈歎<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0317n23"/>曰：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1178c">
            <l>未曾所聞法<caesura/>而今聞汝說</l>
            <l>何處聞說法<caesura/>不念子憂悲</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>婆四吒優婆夷<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0317n24"/>說偈答言：</p>
        <q who="vasetthi">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1178d">
            <l>今日等正覺<caesura/>在彌絺羅國</l>
            <l>菴羅樹園中<caesura/>永離一切苦</l>
            <l>演說一切苦<caesura/>苦<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0317n25"/>習苦寂滅</l>
            <l>賢聖八正道<caesura/>安隱趣涅槃</l>
            <l>則是我大師<caesura/>深樂其正教</l>
            <l>我已知正法<caesura/>能開子憂苦</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>其夫婆羅門復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <pb ed="T" n="0318a"/>
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1178e">
            <l>我今亦當往<caesura/>彌絺菴羅園</l>
            <l>彼世尊亦當<caesura/>開我子憂苦</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>優婆夷復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="vasetthi">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1178f">
            <l>當觀等正覺<caesura/>柔軟金色身</l>
            <l>不調者能調<caesura/>廣度海流人</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時婆羅門即嚴駕乘於馬車，詣彌絺<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0318n01"/>羅菴羅園，遙見世尊，轉增信樂，詣大師前。彼時大師即為說偈，開其法眼，苦、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0317n25"/>習、滅、道，正向涅槃。彼即見法，成無間等。既知法已，請求出家。時婆羅門即得出家，獨靜思惟，……（乃至）得阿羅漢。世尊記說，於第三夜逮得三明。得三明已，佛即告之：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>命遣御者乘車還家，告婆四吒優婆夷，令發隨喜，語言：<q who="sakko">婆羅門往見世尊，得淨信心，奉事大師。即為說法，為開法眼，見苦聖諦、苦集、苦滅、賢聖八道，安趣涅槃，成無間等。既知法已，即求出家。世尊記說，於第三夜具足三明。</q>
            </p>
          </q>時彼御者奉教疾還。時婆四吒優婆夷遙見御者空車而還，即遙問言：<q who="vasetthi">
            <p>婆羅門為見佛不？佛為說法，開示法眼，見聖諦不？</p>
          </q>御者白言：<q who="sakko">
            <p>婆羅門已見世尊，得淨信心，奉事大師。為開法眼，說四聖諦，成無間等。既知法已，即求出家，專精思惟。世尊記說，於第三夜具足三明。</p>
          </q>時優婆夷心即隨喜，語御者言：<q who="vasetthi">
            <p>車馬屬汝，加復賜汝金錢一千已，汝傳信言：<q who="sakko">婆羅門宿闍諦已得三明。</q>令我歡喜故。</p>
          </q>御者白言：<q who="sakko">
            <p>我今何用車馬、金錢為？車馬、金錢還優婆夷。我今當還婆羅門所，隨彼出家！</p>
          </q>優婆夷言：<q who="vasetthi">
            <p>汝意如此，便可速還。不久亦當如彼所得，<pb ed="T" n="0318b"/>具足三明，隨後出家。</p>
          </q>御者白言：<q who="sakko">
            <p>如是，優婆夷！如彼出家，我亦當然。</p>
          </q>優婆夷言：<q who="vasetthi">
            <p>汝父出家，汝隨出家，我今不久亦當隨去。如空野大龍，乘虛而遊，其餘諸龍、龍子、龍女，悉皆隨去。我亦如是，執持衣鉢，易養、易滿。</p>
          </q>御者白言：<q who="sakko">
            <p>優婆夷！若如是者，所願必果。不久當見優婆夷少欲知足，執持衣鉢，人所棄者，乞受而食，剃髮染衣，於陰、界、入斷除愛欲，離貪繫縛，盡諸有漏。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>彼婆羅門及其御者、婆四吒優婆夷、優婆夷女孫陀槃梨悉皆出家，究竟苦邊。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
