<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1183">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0319c27"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在拘薩羅人間遊行，夜宿一娑羅林中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有一婆羅門，近彼林側，與五百年少婆羅門共。彼婆羅門常稱歎、欽想，欲見世尊：<q who="brahmana">
            <p>何時遊於此林？我因得見<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n01"/>遇，問所疑。頗有閑暇為我記說？</p>
          </q>時彼婆羅門年少弟子為採薪故，入於林中，遙見世尊坐一樹下，儀容端正，諸根寂靜；其心寂定，形若金山，光明徹照。見已，作是念：<q who="brahmana">
            <p>我<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n02"/>和上婆羅門常稱歎、欽仰，欲見瞿曇，問其所疑。今此沙門瞿曇到此林中，我當疾往，白<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n02"/>和上令知。</p>
          </q>即持薪束，疾還學堂。捨薪束已，詣<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n02"/>和上所，白言：<q who="brahmana">
            <p>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n02"/>和上！當知：<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n02"/>和上由來常所稱歎、欽仰、欲見沙門瞿曇，脫到此林，當問所疑。今日瞿曇已到此林，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n02"/>和上知時。</p>
          </q>時婆羅門即詣世尊所，面相問訊，慰勞已，退坐一面，而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahmano">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1183a">
            <l>獨入此恐怖<caesura/>深邃叢林中</l>
            <l>堅住不傾動<caesura/>善修正勤法</l>
            <l>無歌舞音樂<caesura/>寂默住空閑</l>
            <l>我所未曾見<caesura/>獨樂深林者</l>
            <l>欲求於世間<caesura/>自在增上主</l>
            <l>為三十三天<caesura/>天上自在樂</l>
            <l>何故深林中<caesura/>苦行自枯槁</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊說偈答言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1183b">
            <l>
              <choice>
                <sic>苦</sic>
                <corr resp="CBETA">若</corr>
              </choice>欲種種求<caesura/>諸界多種著</l>
            <l>彼一切皆是<caesura/>愚癡之根本</l>
            <l>如是一切求<caesura/>我久悉已吐</l>
            <l>不求不諂偽<caesura/>一切無所觸</l>
            <l>於一切諸法<caesura/>唯一清淨觀</l>
            <l>得無上菩提<caesura/>禪思修<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n03"/>不樂</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>婆羅門復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1183c">
            <l>我今敬禮汝<caesura/>大寂牟尼尊</l>
            <l>禪思之妙王<caesura/>覺無邊大覺</l>
            <l>如來天人救<caesura/>巍巍若金山</l>
            <l>解脫於叢林<caesura/>於林永不著</l>
            <l>已拔深利刺<caesura/>清淨無餘跡</l>
            <l>論師之上首<caesura/>言說最勝辯</l>
            <l>人中雄師子<caesura/>震吼於深林</l>
            <l>顯現苦聖諦<caesura/>集滅八正道</l>
            <l>能盡眾苦聚<caesura/>乘出淨無垢</l>
            <l>自脫一切苦<caesura/>濟彼苦眾生</l>
            <l>安樂眾生故<caesura/>演說於正法</l>
            <l>已斷於恩愛<caesura/>遠離於欲網</l>
            <l>斷除於一切<caesura/>有愛之結縛</l>
            <l>如水生蓮花<caesura/>塵水不染著</l>
            <l>如日停虛空<caesura/>清淨無雲翳</l>
            <l>善哉我今日<caesura/>至拘薩羅林</l>
            <l>得見於大師<caesura/>兩足之勝尊</l>
            <l>大林大精進<caesura/>得第一廣度</l>
            <l>調御師之首<caesura/>敬禮無所畏</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>時婆羅門廣說斯偈，讚歎佛已，聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
