<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1184">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0320b21"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n05"/>拘薩羅人間遊行，宿於<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n06"/>孫陀利河側。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊剃髮未久，於後夜時結跏趺坐，正身思惟，繫念在前，以衣覆頭。</p>
        <p>時孫陀利河側有婆羅門住止，夜起持祠，餘食不盡，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0321n07"/>時至河邊，欲求大德婆羅門以奉之。爾時世尊聞河邊婆羅<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n08"/>門聲。聞已，謦咳作聲，却衣現頭。時孫陀利河側婆羅門見佛已，作是念：<q who="brahmano">
            <p>是剃頭沙門，非婆羅門。</p>
          </q>欲持食還去。彼婆羅門復作是<pb ed="T" n="0320c"/>念：<q who="brahmano">
            <p>非獨沙門是剃頭者，婆羅門中亦有剃頭。應往至彼，問其所生。</p>
          </q>時孫陀利河側婆羅門詣世尊所，而問之言：<q who="brahmano">
            <p>為何姓生？</p>
          </q>爾時世尊即說偈言：
                </p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1184a">
            <l>汝莫<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0320n09"/>問所生<caesura/>但當問所行</l>
            <l>刻木為鑽燧<caesura/>亦能生於火</l>
            <l>下賤種姓中<caesura/>生堅固牟尼</l>
            <l>智慧有慚愧<caesura/>精進善調伏</l>
            <l>究竟大明際<caesura/>清淨修梵行</l>
            <l>而今正是時<caesura/>應奉施餘食</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>時孫陀利河側婆羅門復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahmano">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1184b">
            <l>我今吉良日<caesura/>求福修供養</l>
            <l>遇得見大士<caesura/>三時最勝尊</l>
            <l>若不見佛者<caesura/>當更施餘人</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時孫陀利河側婆羅門轉得信心，即持餘食以奉世尊。世尊不受，以說偈得故。（如上，因說偈而得食廣說。）孫陀利河側婆羅門白佛言：<q who="brahmano">
            <p>世尊！今此施食，當置何所？</p>
          </q>佛告婆羅門：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我不見諸天、魔、梵、沙門、婆羅門、天神、世人有能食此食，令身安隱者。汝持此食，去著無虫水中及少生草地。</p>
          </q>時婆羅門即持此食，著無虫水中。水即烟起涌沸，啾啾作聲。如燒鐵丸，投之冷水，烟起涌沸，啾啾作聲。如是彼食著無虫水中，烟起涌沸，啾啾作聲。孫陀利河側婆羅門心欲恐怖，身毛皆竪，謂為災變，馳走上岸，集聚乾木，供養祠火，令息災恠。世尊見彼集聚乾木，供養祠火，望息災恠。見已，即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1184c">
            <l> 婆羅門祠火<caesura/>焚燒乾草木</l>
            <pb ed="T" n="0321a"/>
            <l>莫呼是淨道<caesura/>能却諸災患</l>
            <l>此則惡供養<caesura/>而謂為<g ref="g042">[烈-列+(里*吉)]</g>慧</l>
            <l>作如是因緣<caesura/>外道取修淨</l>
            <l>汝今棄<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0321n01"/>薪火<caesura/>起內火熾然</l>
            <l>常修不放逸<caesura/>常<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0321n02"/>富於供養</l>
            <l>處處<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0321n03"/>興淨信<caesura/>廣施設大會</l>
            <l>心意為束薪<caesura/>瞋恚黑烟起</l>
            <l>妄語為塵味<caesura/>口舌為木杓</l>
            <l>胸懷燃火處<caesura/>欲火常熾然</l>
            <l>當善自調伏<caesura/>消滅士夫火</l>
            <l>正信為大河<caesura/>淨戒為度濟</l>
            <l>澄淨清流水<caesura/>智者之所歎</l>
            <l>人中淨天德<caesura/>當於中洗浴</l>
            <l>涉水不著身<caesura/>安樂度彼岸</l>
            <l>正法為深淵<caesura/>福德為下濟</l>
            <l>澄淨水充滿<caesura/>智者所讚嘆</l>
            <l>人中天淨德<caesura/>當於中洗浴</l>
            <l>涉水不著身<caesura/>安樂度彼岸</l>
            <l>真諦善調御<caesura/>攝護修梵行</l>
            <l>慈悲為苦行<caesura/>真實心清淨</l>
            <l>沐浴以正法<caesura/>智者所稱歎</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>爾時孫陀利河側婆羅門聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，復道而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
