<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1189">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0322a28"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住欝毘羅聚落尼連禪河側菩提樹下，成佛未久。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊獨<pb ed="T" n="0322b"/>靜思惟，作是念：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>有一乘道，能淨眾生，度諸憂悲，滅除苦惱，得真如法，謂四念處。何等為四？身身觀念處，受、心、法法觀念處。若有人不樂四念處者，則不樂如聖法。不樂如聖法者，則不樂如聖道。不樂如聖道者，則不樂甘露法。不樂甘露法者，則不解脫生、老、病、死、憂、悲、惱、苦。若樂修四念處者，則樂修如聖法。樂修如聖法者，則樂如聖道。樂如聖道者，則樂甘露法。樂甘露法者，得解脫生、老、病、死、憂、悲、惱、苦。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p> 爾時娑婆世界主梵天王知佛心念已，譬如力士，屈伸臂頃，於梵天沒，住於佛前，作是歎言：<q who="brahma">
            <p>如是，世尊！如是，善逝！有一乘道，能淨眾生，謂四念處，……（乃至）解脫生、老、病、死、憂、悲、惱、苦。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時梵天王復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1189a">
            <l>謂有一乘道<caesura/>見生諸有邊</l>
            <l>演說於正法<caesura/>安慰苦眾生</l>
            <l>過去諸世尊<caesura/>以乘斯道度</l>
            <l>當來諸世尊<caesura/>亦<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0322n03"/>度乘斯道</l>
            <l>現在尊正覺<caesura/>乘此度海流</l>
            <l>究竟生死際<caesura/>調伏心清淨</l>
            <l>於生死輪轉<caesura/>悉已永消盡</l>
            <l>知種種諸界<caesura/>慧眼顯正道</l>
            <l>譬若恒水流<caesura/>悉歸趣大海</l>
            <l>激流浚漂遠<caesura/>正道亦如是</l>
            <l>廣智善顯示<caesura/>逮得甘露法</l>
            <l>殊勝正法輪<caesura/>本所未曾聞</l>
            <l>哀愍眾生故<caesura/>而為眾生轉</l>
            <l>覆護天人眾<caesura/>令度有彼岸</l>
            <l>是故諸眾生<caesura/>咸皆稽首禮</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0322n04"/>爾時梵天王聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，稽首佛足，即沒不現。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
