<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1192">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0323a12"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住迦毘羅衛迦毘羅衛林中，與五百比丘俱，皆是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0323n02"/>羅漢，諸漏已盡，所作已作，離諸重擔，逮得<choice>
            <sic>已</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">己</corr>
          </choice>利，盡諸有結，正智，心善解脫。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊為諸大眾說涅槃相應法。時有十方世界大眾威力諸天，皆悉來會，供養世尊及比丘僧。復有諸梵天王住於梵世，作是念：<q who="brahma">
            <p>今日佛住迦毘羅衛國。……（如上廣說。乃至）供養世尊及諸大眾。我今當往，各各讚歎！</p>
          </q>作是念已，譬如力士，屈伸臂頃，從梵天沒，住於佛前。</p>
        <p>第一梵天即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1192a">
            <l>於此大林中<caesura/>大眾普雲集</l>
            <l>十方諸天眾<caesura/>皆悉來<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0323n03"/>恭敬</l>
            <l>故我遠來禮<caesura/>最勝難伏僧</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>第二梵天復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1192b">
            <l>是諸比丘僧<caesura/>真實心精進</l>
            <l>於此大林中<caesura/>攝諸根求度</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>第三梵天次說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1192c">
            <pb ed="T" n="0323b"/>
            <l>善方便消融<caesura/>恩愛深利刺</l>
            <l>堅固不傾動<caesura/>如因陀羅幢</l>
            <l>度深塹水流<caesura/>清淨不求欲</l>
            <l>善度之導師<caesura/>諸調伏大龍</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>第四梵天次說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1192d">
            <l>歸依於佛者<caesura/>終不墮惡趣</l>
            <l>能斷人中身<caesura/>得天身受樂</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>各說偈已，四梵<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0323n04"/>天身即沒不現。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
