<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 110. It is found in the 大般涅槃經後分 Sutra at T.12.0377.0900.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T12.0377.0900a08">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t12.0377.0900a08"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時須跋陀羅。從佛聞說大般涅槃甚深妙法。而得法眼見法清淨。愛護正法已捨邪見。於佛法中深信堅固。即從如來欲求出家。佛言。善哉善哉。須跋陀羅善。來比丘。悅可聖心善入佛道。於是須跋陀羅。歡喜踊躍忻慶無量。即時<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0900n07"/>鬚髮自落而作沙門。法性智水灌注心<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0900n08"/>原。無復縛著。漏盡意解得羅漢果。</p>
        <p>須跋陀羅既證果已。即前佛所瞻仰尊顏頭面禮足。偏袒右肩右膝著地長跪合掌。<seg type="not-parallel">悲喜交流深自悔責在昔罪咎。而白佛言。世尊。恨我毒身久劫已來常相欺惑。令我長沒無明邪見。淪溺三界外道法中。痛哉苦哉為害滋甚。今大喜慶。蒙如來恩得入正法。世尊。智慧大海慈愍無量。竊自惟忖。累劫碎軀未能報此須臾之恩。須跋陀羅說是語已。悲泣流淚不能自裁。復白佛言。世尊。我年老邁餘命無幾。未脫眾苦行苦遷逼。唯願世尊。少住教<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0900n09"/>誡哀愍救護莫般涅槃。爾時世尊默然不許。須跋陀羅不果所請。愁憂熱惱高聲唱曰。苦哉苦哉。世間<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0900n10"/>虛空。世間<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0900n10"/>虛空。如何於今大怖即至熱惱流行。哀哉哀哉。眾生福盡正慧眼滅。復更流淚悲號哽咽。遍體血現發聲大哭。於<pb ed="T" n="0900b"/>如來前舉身投地。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0900n11"/>慌亂濁心昏迷悶絕。久乃蘇醒涕淚哽咽。而</seg>白佛言。世尊。我今不忍見於如來入般涅槃。中心痛切難任裁抑。我自何能與此坏器毒身共住。今前寧可先自速滅。唯願世尊。後當涅槃。爾時須跋陀羅。說是語已悲戀哽咽。於是時頃即入涅槃。
                </p>
      </div>
      <anchor type="gap" n="t12.0377.0900b06"/>
      <gap resp="t.100" reason="longNonParallel"/>
      <anchor type="continued" n="t12.0377.0905c14"/>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>
          <seg type="parallel">爾時娑婆世界主尸棄大梵天王。知佛已入涅槃。與諸<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0905n15"/>天眾即從初禪飛空而下。</seg>舉聲大哭流淚悲<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0905n16"/>咽。投如來前悶絕躄地。久乃穌醒哀不自勝。<seg type="parallel">即於佛前以偈悲歎。</seg>
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>世尊往昔本誓願<caesura/>為我等故居忍土</l>
          <l>乃隱無量自在力<caesura/>貧所樂法度眾生</l>
          <l>方便逐宜隨應說<caesura/>眾生無不受安樂</l>
          <l>誘進令出三有苦<caesura/>究竟皆至涅槃道</l>
          <l>如來慈母育眾生<caesura/>普飲眾生大悲乳</l>
          <l>何期一旦忽捨離<caesura/>人天孤露無所依</l>
          <l>痛哉眾生善種芽<caesura/>無天甘露令增長</l>
          <l>善芽漸漸衰滅已<caesura/>罪業相牽墮惡道</l>
          <l>奈何世界悉空虛<caesura/>眾生正慧眼已滅</l>
          <l>既行無明黑闇中<caesura/>墮落三有淪溺苦</l>
          <l>奈何眾生罪無救<caesura/>願依舍利得解脫</l>
          <pb ed="T" n="0906a"/>
          <l>勸請如來大悲力<caesura/>救護令我脫苦地</l>
          <l>何<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n01"/>其痛哉此惡世<caesura/>如來棄我入涅槃</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <seg type="parallel">爾時釋提桓因。</seg>與諸大眾從空而下唱言。苦哉苦哉。發聲大哭悲泣流淚。投如來前悶絕躄地。久乃穌醒悲哀哽咽。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n02"/>胡跪佛前。<seg type="parallel">說偈哀歎。</seg>
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>如來歷劫行苦行<caesura/>普為我等群生故</l>
          <l>得成無上正覺道<caesura/>等育眾生如一子</l>
          <l>施法藥中為上藥<caesura/>療病醫中為勝醫</l>
          <l>大慈悲雲蔭眾生<caesura/>甘露慧雨雨一切</l>
          <l>慧日光照無明闇<caesura/>無明眾生見聖道</l>
          <l>聖月慈光照六趣<caesura/>三有蒙光脫眾苦</l>
          <l>何期於今捨大<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n03"/>慈<caesura/>已入涅槃眾不見</l>
          <l>本誓大悲今何在<caesura/>棄捨眾生如涕唾</l>
          <l>我等一切諸眾生<caesura/>如犢失母必當死</l>
          <l>四眾互相執手哭<caesura/>搥胸大哀動三界</l>
          <l>苦哉苦哉諸有人<caesura/>如何一旦盡孤露</l>
          <l>我等福盡苦何甚<caesura/>善芽燋燃無復潤</l>
          <l>唯願法寶舍利光<caesura/>照我令脫三有苦</l>
          <l>哀哉痛哉我等眾<caesura/>幾何重得見如來</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <seg type="parallel">爾時樓逗。</seg>悲哀號泣傷悼無量。胡跪佛前。<seg type="parallel">以偈悲<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n04"/>讚。</seg>
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>正覺法王育我等<caesura/>飲我法乳長法身</l>
          <l>眾生法身未成立<caesura/>又復慧命少資糧</l>
          <l>應以八音常演暢<caesura/>令眾聞已悉悟道</l>
          <l>常放大慈五色光<caesura/>令眾蒙光皆解脫</l>
          <l>如何今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n05"/>日永涅槃<caesura/>行苦眾生何依趣</l>
          <l>苦哉世尊捨大悲<caesura/>我等孤窮必當死</l>
          <l>雖知世尊現方便<caesura/>我等無能不悲哀</l>
          <pb ed="T" n="0906b"/>
          <l>四眾迷悶昏失心<caesura/>哀動天地震三界</l>
          <l>世尊獨處大安樂<caesura/>眾生大苦欲何之</l>
          <l>世尊往昔為我等<caesura/>眾劫捨頭截手足</l>
          <l>得成無上正覺道<caesura/>不久住世即涅槃</l>
          <l>我及四眾處無明<caesura/>魔王欣慶捨甲冑</l>
          <l>哀哉世尊願大悲<caesura/>舍利慈光攝我等</l>
          <l>伏請世尊愍四眾<caesura/>法寶流潤願不窮</l>
          <l>我等不能即殞滅<caesura/>苟存餘命能幾何</l>
          <l>苦哉痛切難堪忍<caesura/>重見世尊無復期</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <seg type="parallel">爾時阿難。</seg>悶絕漸醒舉手拍頭。搥胸哽咽悲泣流淚。哀不自勝。長跪佛前。<seg type="parallel">以偈悲歎。</seg>
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>我昔與佛誓願力<caesura/>幸共同生釋種中</l>
          <l>如來得成正覺道<caesura/>我為侍者二十載</l>
          <l>深心敬養情<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n06"/>未足<caesura/>一旦見棄入涅槃</l>
          <l>痛哉哀哉荼毒苦<caesura/>無極長夜痛切心</l>
          <l>我身未脫諸有網<caesura/>無明之<g>[穀-禾+卵]</g>未出離</l>
          <l>世尊慧<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n07"/>
            <g>[此/束]</g>未啄破<caesura/>如何見捨疾涅槃</l>
          <l>我如初生之嬰兒<caesura/>失母不久必當死</l>
          <l>世尊如何見放捨<caesura/>獨出三界受安樂</l>
          <l>我今懺悔於世尊<caesura/>侍佛已來二十年</l>
          <l>四威儀中多懈<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n08"/>墮<caesura/>不能悅可大聖心</l>
          <l>願正覺尊大慈悲<caesura/>施我甘露令安樂</l>
          <l>我願窮盡未來際<caesura/>常覲世尊為侍者</l>
          <l>唯願世尊大慈光<caesura/>一切世界攝受我</l>
          <l>痛哉痛哉不可說<caesura/>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n09"/>喑咽何能陳聖<anchor type="variant" n="fnT12p0906n10"/>恩</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
