<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 110. It is found in the 長阿含遊行經 Sutra at T.01.0001.0021.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0001.0021a02">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0001.0021a02"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時。世尊入拘尸城。向本生處末羅雙樹間。告阿難曰。汝為如來於雙樹間敷置牀座。使頭<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0021n02"/>北首。<seg type="not-parallel">面向<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0021n03"/>西方。所以然者。吾法流布。當久住北方。</seg>對曰。唯然。即敷座。令<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0021n02"/>北首。爾時。世尊自四<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0020n03"/>牒僧伽梨。偃右脇如師子王。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0021n04"/>累足而臥。</p>
      </div>
      <anchor type="gap" n="t01.0001.0021a07"/>
      <gap resp="t.100" reason="longNonParallel"/>
      <anchor type="continued" n="t01.0001.0025a01"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>是時。拘尸城內。有一梵志。名曰<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n01"/>須跋。年百二十。耆舊多智。聞沙門瞿曇今夜於雙樹間當取滅度。自念言。吾於法有疑。唯有瞿曇能<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n02"/>解我意。今當及時自力而行。即於其夜。出拘尸城。詣雙樹間。至阿難所。問訊<choice>
            <sic>巳</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">已</corr>
          </choice>。一面立。白阿難曰。我聞瞿曇沙門今夜當取滅度。故來至此。求一相見。我於法有疑。願見瞿曇。一決我意。寧有閑暇得相見不。阿難報言。止。止。須跋。佛身有疾。無勞擾也。須跋固請。乃至再三。吾聞如來時一出世。如優曇鉢花時時乃出。故來求現。欲決所疑。寧有閑暇暫相見不。阿難<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n03"/>答如初。佛<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n04"/>身有疾。無勞擾也。</p>
        <p>時。佛告<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n05"/>阿難。汝勿遮止。聽使來入。此欲決疑。無嬈亂也。設聞我法。必得開解。阿難乃告須跋。汝欲覲佛。宜知是時。須跋即入。問訊<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n06"/>已。一面坐。而白佛言。我於法有疑。寧有閑暇一決所滯不。佛言。恣汝所問。須跋即問。云何。瞿曇。諸有別眾。自稱為師。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n07"/>不蘭迦葉．<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n08"/>末伽梨憍舍利．<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n09"/>阿浮陀翅舍金披羅．<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n10"/>波浮迦旃．<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n11"/>薩若毘耶梨弗．<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n12"/>尼揵子。此諸師等。各有異法。瞿曇沙門能盡知耶。不盡知耶。佛言。止。止。用論此為。吾悉知耳。今當為汝說深妙法。諦聽。諦聽。善思念之。須跋受教。佛告之曰。若諸法中。無八聖道者。則無第一沙門果。第二．第三．第四沙門果。須跋。以諸法中有八聖道故。便有第一沙門果。第二．第三．第四沙門果。須跋。今我法中有八聖道。有第一沙門<pb ed="T" n="0025b"/>果。第二．第三．第四沙門果。外道異眾無沙門果。爾時。世尊為須跋而說頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>我年二十九<caesura/>出家求善道</l>
          <l>須跋我成佛<caesura/>今已五十年</l>
          <l>戒定智慧行<caesura/>獨處而思惟</l>
          <l>今說法之要<caesura/>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n13"/>此外無沙門</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">佛告須跋。若諸比丘皆能自攝者。則此世間羅漢不空。</seg>是時。須跋白阿難言。諸有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n14"/>從沙門瞿曇已行梵行。今行．當行者。為得大利。阿難。汝於如來所修行梵行。亦得大利。我得面覲如來。諮問所疑。亦得大利。今者。如來則為以弟子<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n15"/>莂而<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0025n16"/>別我已。即白佛言。我今寧得於如來法中出家受具戒不。<seg type="not-parallel">佛告須跋。若有異學梵志於我法中修梵行者。當試四月。觀其人行。察其志性。具諸威儀無漏失者。則於我法得受具戒。須跋。當知在人行耳。須跋復白言。外道異學於佛法中當試四月。觀其人行。察其志性。具諸威儀無漏失者。乃得具戒。今我能於佛正法中四歲使役。具諸威儀。無有漏失。乃受具戒。佛告須跋。我先已說在人行耳。</seg>於是。須跋即於其夜。出家受戒。淨修梵行。於現法中。自身作證。生死已盡。梵行已立。所作已辦。得如實智。更不受有。時夜未久。即成羅漢。是為如來最後弟子。便先滅度而佛後焉。</p>
      </div>
      <anchor type="gap" n="t01.0001.0025b26"/>
      <gap resp="t.100" reason="longNonParallel"/>
      <anchor type="continued" n="t01.0001.0026c11"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>時。忉利天於虛空中。以<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0026n20"/>文陀羅花．優鉢羅．<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0026n21"/>波頭摩．<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0026n22"/>拘摩頭．分陀利花散如來上。及散眾會。又以天末<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0026n23"/>栴檀而散佛上。及散大眾。佛滅度已。時梵天王於虛空中以偈頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>一切昏萌類<caesura/>皆當捨諸陰</l>
          <l>佛為無上尊<caesura/>世間無等倫</l>
          <l>如來大聖雄<caesura/>有無畏神力</l>
          <l>世尊應久住<caesura/>而今般<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0026n24"/>涅槃</l>
        </lg>
        <p>爾時。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0026n25"/>釋提桓因復作頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>陰行無有常<caesura/>但為興衰法</l>
          <l>生者無不死<caesura/>佛滅之為樂</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>爾時。毘沙門王復作頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>福樹大叢林<caesura/>無上福娑羅</l>
          <l>受供之良田<caesura/>雙樹間滅度</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>爾時。阿那律復作頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>佛以無為住<caesura/>不用出入息</l>
          <l>本由寂滅來<caesura/>靈曜於是沒</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>爾時。梵<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0026n26"/>摩那比丘復作頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <pb ed="T" n="0026a"/>
          <l>不以懈慢心<caesura/>約己修上慧</l>
          <l>無著無所染<caesura/>離<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0027n01"/>愛無上尊</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <seg type="parallel">爾時。阿難比丘復作頌曰。</seg>
        </p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>天人懷恐怖<caesura/>衣毛為之竪</l>
          <l>一切皆成就<caesura/>正覺取滅度</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
