<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 110. It is found in the 般泥洹經 Sutra at T.01.0006.0184.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0006.0184c19">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0006.0184c19"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>彼時佛勑賢者阿難。汝於蘇連雙樹間。施<choice>
            <sic>蠅</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">繩</corr>
          </choice>牀令北首。我夜半當滅度。受教即施。還白已具。佛到雙樹。就繩牀側右脇而臥。</p>
      </div>
      <anchor type="gap" n="t01.0006.0184c21"/>
      <gap resp="t.100" reason="longNonParallel"/>
      <anchor type="continued" n="t01.0006.0187b06"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>是時城中。有老異學。年百二十。名曰須跋。聞佛夜半當取滅度。自念。吾有法望之疑。常願瞿曇一解。我意當及。是時即起。自力行到雙樹。白阿難言。吾聞瞿曇。<choice>
            <sic>斯</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">期</corr>
          </choice>在夜半。請見決疑。阿難言。止止須跋。無擾佛也。須跋固請至再三曰。吾聞。佛為如來至真正諦覺明行成已善逝世間解無上士<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0187n10"/>導法御天人師號佛眾祐。甚難遭值。如漚曇華。百千萬世時時一有。願一見<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0187n11"/>折所疑。阿難以為勞擾如來。故不欲通。佛神心徹聽。清淨過人。從裏知之。即勅阿難。勿禁止聽使入。<seg type="not-parallel">是為最後。當度異學須跋者也。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>須跋得入。忻然悅豫。善心生焉。見佛歡喜。禮問恭辭。氣重揖讓畢一面住。白佛言。欲有所問。豈有閑暇。一決其疑。佛言。便問。恣汝所欲。聞可得解。須跋問曰。今世學者。各自稱師。有古龜氏。有無失氏。有志行氏。有白鷺子氏。有延壽氏。有計金樊氏。有多積願氏。有尼犍子。彼八子者。有所述乎。自知之也。</p>
        <p>佛告須跋。<seg type="not-parallel">彼與佛異。子曹自作貪生猗想。以邪之道。一曰邪見。不知今世後世。所作自得。好以卜占享祀求福。二曰邪思。念在愛欲。有諍怒心。三曰邪言。虛偽諂諛。佞讒綺語。四曰邪行。殺生貪取。有婬<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0184n07"/>妷意。五曰邪命。求<pb ed="T" n="0187c"/>利衣食。不以正道。六曰邪治。惡不能止。善不能行。七曰邪志。志貪常樂。痛身謂淨。八曰邪定。專意所望。不見出要。如是須跋。</seg>昔我出家。十有二年。道成得佛。開說經法。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0187n12"/>但五十載。自從捨家。有戒有定有慧有解。得度知見。說正道者。唯佛沙門。非凡異也。吾本所履。有八真道。第一沙門。亦從是得。二三至四。皆從是成。若不見此八真道者。彼為不得沙門四道。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">所謂八真道者。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0187n13"/>一為正見。見今世後世。作善有福。為惡得殃。知苦知<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0187n14"/>習。滅行得道。二為正思。思樂出家。去諍怒心。三為正言。言諦至誠。柔軟忠信。四為正行。不殺不邪。無有婬心。五為正命。求利衣食。以道不邪。六為正治。抑制惡行。發起善意。七為正志。志惟四觀身痛意法。解非常苦非身非淨。八為正定。一向無為。成四禪行。</seg>沙門梵志。履此八正。乃成四道。能師子吼。我賢弟子。行無放逸世間意滅。故得羅漢。於是須跋。謂阿難言。快哉賢者。是利弘美。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0187n15"/>寔未曾有。蓋上弟子。得值此者。不亦妙乎。今受聖恩。乃聞是法。願得捨家。受成就戒。阿難白佛。異學須跋。願受眾祐自然法律。捨家就戒沙門之行。佛以可其就戒之志曰。是吾<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0187n16"/>未後得證見淨者。異學須跋也。即授戒為比丘。一心受不放逸。以健制以志惟以斷却。如所欲下鬚髮被袈裟。以家之信離家。為道得法。意具淨行。自知作證。成解究暢。為行如應。已意通知。賢者須跋已度世得應真。坐自念。吾不能待佛般泥洹。<pb ed="T" n="0188a"/>便先滅度。而佛後焉。</p>
      </div>
      <anchor type="gap" n="t01.0006.0188a01"/>
      <gap resp="t.100" reason="longNonParallel"/>
      <anchor type="continued" n="t01.0006.0188c04"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          <seg type="parallel">從一禪思復至三禪。便從四禪反於無知棄所受餘泥洹之情。便般泥洹。</seg>當此之時。地大震動。諸天龍神。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0185n04"/>側塞空中。散華如雨。莫不歎慕。而來供養。時第二天帝釋。下說頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>陰行無有常<caesura/>但為興衰法</l>
          <l>生者無不死<caesura/>佛滅<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0188n10"/>之為樂</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>第七梵天下說頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>妙哉佛已棄<caesura/>一切世間猗</l>
          <l>廣遺清淨教<caesura/>三界中無比</l>
          <l>神真力無畏<caesura/>光明滅於茲</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>賢者阿那律說頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>佛已無為住<caesura/>不用出入息</l>
          <l>本由自然來<caesura/>靈耀於是沒</l>
          <l part="I">意淨無所著</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <lg met="5">
          <l part="F">為人受斯疾</l>
          <l>施<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0188n11"/>惠教已遍<caesura/>乃退歸寂滅</l>
          <l>惟茲遇佛者<caesura/>莫不蒙恩澤</l>
          <l>今已淪清虛<caesura/>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0188n12"/>求了時復出</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
