<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 110. It is found in the 佛般泥洹經 Sutra at T.01.0005.0169.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0005.0169a10">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0005.0169a10"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>佛告阿難疾去為佛於鹽呵<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0169n01"/>沙。施牀使北首。今日夜半。佛當般泥洹。阿難奉命。之彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0169n02"/>施牀牀頭北首畢。還白言。施牀已竟。佛起至鹽呵<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0169n03"/>沙。得牀<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0169n04"/>猗右脇臥。</p>
      </div>
      <anchor type="gap" n="t01.0005.0169a14"/>
      <gap resp="t.100" reason="longNonParallel"/>
      <anchor type="continued" n="t01.0005.0171c08"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>國有耆年。字曰須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔。年百二十。時在城中。夜臥覺寤。見佛光明。照一城中。家無一人即出城。疾到佛所。向阿難曰。以吾啟聞。吾有疑心於世尊。阿難曰。夜以且半。佛當善逝。且莫煩擾。須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔對曰。不可以聞<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n24"/>乎。吾聞無數世乃有一佛耳。今詣質疑。而不以聞吾之所疑。唯佛而釋。餘莫能也。阿難曰。且止不須問矣。佛知須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔在外欲質所疑。呼阿難問。何以不啟須拔疑事。阿難對曰。見夜且半。佛當滅度。懼其來入語言煩擾佛。今當棄三有欲界就無為道佛言。將須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔入有疑當問。阿難即將須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔入。須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔聞當入。其心喜踊。身皆為動。前以頭面<g ref="g037">[(禾*尤)/上/日]</g>首佛足。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">佛見須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔年老息微。賜机使坐。佛問須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔。爾有何疑。對曰。佛為三界天中之天。神聖無量。至尊難雙。開化導引四十九年。仙聖梵釋。靡不<g ref="g037">[(禾*尤)/上/日]</g>首。吾有同志八人。</seg>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n25"/>有故龜氏。有無先氏。有志行氏。有白鷺子氏。有延壽氏。有計金樊氏。有多積願氏。有尼揵子。<seg type="not-parallel">彼八人<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n26"/>智。無螢燭之明。善無<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n27"/>沛生絲髮之潤。內懷三毒。外為欲走。坐作虛論。妄書非真不詣稟化將有緣乎。佛告須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔。子曹經意。與佛<pb ed="T" n="0172a"/>經違。為生死之路。求富貴之耶。吾道之志<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0172n01"/>斷求念空。不願世榮淡泊無為。以斯為樂。須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔曰。何謂無為之道乎。佛言。滅有歸本。不復生死。謂之無為也。若曹志趣。皆有八惡。何謂為八。祠祀鬼神。卜問<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0172n02"/>虛殺。是為一。處家貪餮。不奉孝道。貪<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0172n03"/>愛萬邪。欲無舍止。是為二。兩舌惡罵妄言綺語。未<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0172n04"/>常陳善令愚去惡。是為三。殺盜婬泆。是為四。常懷怒心。不孝二親。輕慢兄弟妻子九族。心邪行穢。無善勸導。常自憍大。欲人畏敬。是為五。晝夜懷邪。不畏法律。輕慢賢者。尊貴穢濁。遠避真正。交隨惡人。是為六。聞有賢智明經沙門梵志。豫懷憎嫉。虛偽作謗。是為七。不敬先祖盡孝于親。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0172n05"/>弃賢明而<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0172n06"/>反賊。毀仁正。不覺流俗穢濁可耻。斯謂八惡若自陳云。世尊說經。四十九載。有八人不詣稟化。子曹皆懷斯<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0172n07"/>八惡。豈樂清化乎。正使來者。佛亦不受。須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔若心有斯八惡。慎無問佛。</seg>執斯八戒可得溝港頻來不還應真。行斯八戒。當正爾心。乃為佛弟子。其有凡人。擅作師導教化之首。違斯八戒。皆是妖蠱。當遠棄避。慎無聽受。</p>
        <p>世尊曰。吾今於三界中。獨言獨步。莫有等雙。爾之所疑。便問無嫌。須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔<g ref="g037">[(禾*尤)/上/日]</g>首。長跪而曰。誠如佛言。幾亡吾身。又墮狂愚。世尊又曰。若解八戒未乎。對曰已解。重<g ref="g037">[(禾*尤)/上/日]</g>首曰。吾欲捐下賤之操。執沙門清淨之行。世尊又曰。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0172n08"/>爾誠不。對曰。願佛加哀。受我為沙門。須<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0171n23"/>拔髮自然墮地。袈裟著體。精心思教。霍然無想。一心清淨。喻明月珠。即得應<pb ed="T" n="0172b"/>真道。重自思念。吾不能使吾師於前泥洹也。即時先佛。取泥洹道。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
