<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 113. It is found in the 增壹阿含經 Sutra at T.02.0125.0673.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0125.0673b01">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0125.0673b01"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時。佛在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
        <p>爾時。目連弟子．阿難弟子二人共談。我等二人同聲經唄。誰者為勝。是時。眾多比丘聞此二人各各共論。聞已。便往至世尊所。頭面禮足。在一面坐。爾時。眾多比丘白世尊言。今有二人共論。我等二人共誦經唄。何者為妙。爾時。世尊告一比丘。汝往呼此二比丘使來。比丘對曰。如是。世尊。比丘從佛受教。即往至彼二人所。語彼二人曰。世尊喚卿。是時。二人聞比丘語已。即至世尊所。頭面禮足。在一面住。爾時。世尊告二人曰。汝等愚人實有此語。我等共誦經唄。何者為妙。二人對曰。如是。世尊。世尊告曰。汝等頗聞我說此法共<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n07"/>競諍乎。如此之法。何異梵志。諸比丘對曰。不聞如來而說此法。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>世尊告曰。我由來不與諸比丘而說此法。當諍勝負耶。然我今日<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n08"/>所說法。欲有降伏。有所教化。若有比丘受法之時。當念思惟四緣之法。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n09"/>
            意與契經．阿毘曇．律共相應不。設共相應者。當念奉行。
                            爾時。世尊便說此偈。
          </p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>多<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n10"/>誦無益事<caesura/>此法非為妙</l>
          <l>猶<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n11"/>算<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n12"/>牛頭數<caesura/>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n13"/>非此沙門要</l>
          <l>若少多誦習<caesura/>於法而行法</l>
          <l>此法極為上<caesura/>可謂沙門法</l>
        </lg>
        <lg met="4">
          <l>雖誦千章<caesura/>不義何益</l>
          <l>不如一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n14"/>句<caesura/>聞可得道</l>
          <l>雖誦千言<caesura/>不義何益</l>
          <l>不如一義<caesura/>聞可得道</l>
          <l>千千為<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n15"/>敵<caesura/>一夫勝之</l>
          <l>未若自勝<caesura/>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n16"/>已忍者上</l>
        </lg>
        <pb ed="T" n="0673c"/>
        <p>是故。諸比丘。自今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0665n22"/>以後。未復諍訟有勝負心。所以然者。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n17"/>念當降伏一切人民。若復比丘有勝負心。共諍訟心而共競者。即以法．律治彼。比丘。以是之故。當自修行。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n18"/>故。二比丘聞佛此語已。即從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0671n32"/>坐起。禮世尊足。而求<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n19"/>悔過。自今已後。更不復為。唯願世尊受其<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n19"/>悔過。世尊告曰。大法之中快得<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n20"/>改過。自知有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n21"/>諍競之心。聽汝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT03p0673n19"/>悔過。諸比丘。更莫復爾。如是。諸比丘。當作是學。爾時。諸比丘聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
