<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1140">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0301a20"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時尊者摩訶迦葉住舍衛國東園鹿子母講堂，晡時從禪覺，來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面。爾時世尊告摩訶迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>汝當為諸比丘說法、教<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0300n06"/>誡、教授。所以者何？我常為諸比丘說法、教<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0300n06"/>誡、教授，汝亦應爾。</p>
        </q>
        <p>尊者摩訶迦葉白佛言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p>世尊！今諸比丘難可為說法、教<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0300n06"/>誡、教授。有諸比丘，聞所說法不忍、不喜。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告摩訶迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>汝何因緣作如是說？</p>
        </q>
        <p>摩訶迦葉白佛言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p>世尊是法根、法眼、法<pb ed="T" n="0301b"/>依。唯願──世尊！──為諸比丘說法！諸比丘聞已，當受奉行！</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>諦聽！善思！當為汝說。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>昔日<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0301n04"/>阿練若比丘於阿練若比丘所歎說阿練若法，於乞食比丘所歎說乞食功德，於糞掃衣比丘所歎說糞掃衣功德。若少欲知足，修行遠離，精勤方便，正念正定，智慧漏盡，身作證比丘所隨其所行，讚歎稱說。迦葉！若於阿練若所歎說阿練若法，……（乃至）漏盡比丘所歎說漏盡身作證，若見其人，悉共語言：<q who="bhikkhu">隨宜慰勞善來者！汝名何等？為誰弟子？</q>讓座令坐，歎其賢善。如其法<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0301n05"/>像類，有沙門義，有沙門欲。如是讚<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0301n06"/>嘆時。若彼同住同遊者。則便決定隨順彼行。不久亦當同其所見。同其所欲。佛告迦葉。若是年少比丘見彼阿練若比丘來讚歎阿練若法。乃至漏盡身作證。彼年少比丘應起出迎。恭敬禮拜問訊。乃至彼同住者。不久當得自義饒益。如是恭敬者。長夜當得安樂饒益。佛告迦葉。今日比丘見彼來者。知見大德。能感財利．衣被．飲食．床臥．湯藥者。與共言語。恭敬問訊。歎言善來。何某名字。為誰弟子。歎其福德。能感大利．衣被．飲食．臥具．湯藥。若與尊者相習近者。亦當豐足衣被．飲食．臥具．湯藥。若復年少比丘見彼來者。大智大德。能感財利．衣被．飲食．臥具．湯藥者。疾起出迎。恭敬問訊。歎言善來大智大德。能感大利．衣被．飲食．臥具．湯藥。迦葉。如是年少比丘。長夜當得非義不饒益苦。如是。迦葉。斯等比丘為沙門患。為梵行溺。為大映障．惡不善法．煩惱之患。重受諸有。<pb ed="T" n="0301c"/>熾燃生死。未來苦報。生．老．病．死．憂．悲．苦惱。是故。迦葉。當如是學。為阿練若。於阿練若所。稱譽讚歎糞掃衣．乞食。少欲知足。修行遠離。精勤方便。正念正定。正智漏盡。身作證者。稱譽讚歎。當如是學。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，尊者摩訶迦葉聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
