<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1143">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0302b02"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城迦蘭陀竹園。尊者摩訶迦葉、尊者阿難住耆闍崛山。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時尊者阿難詣尊者摩訶迦葉所，語尊者摩訶迦葉言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>今可共出耆闍崛山，入王舍城乞食。</p>
        </q>
        <p>尊者摩訶迦葉默然而許。時尊者摩訶迦葉、尊者阿難著衣持鉢，入王舍城乞食。尊者阿難語尊者摩訶迦葉：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>日時太早，可共暫過比丘尼精舍。</p>
        </q>
        <p>即便往過。時諸比丘尼遙見尊者摩訶迦葉、尊者阿難從遠而來，疾敷床座，請令就坐。時諸比丘尼禮尊者摩訶迦葉、阿難足已，退坐一面。尊者摩訶迦葉為諸比丘尼種種說法，示、教、照、喜。示、教、照、喜已，時<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n07"/>偷羅難陀比丘尼不喜悅，說如是惡言：</p>
        <q who="thullananda">
          <p>云何<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n08"/>阿梨摩訶迦葉於阿梨阿難──鞞提<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n09"/>訶牟尼──前為比丘尼說法？譬如販針兒於針師家賣。阿梨摩訶迦葉亦復如是，於阿梨阿難──鞞提訶牟尼──前為諸比丘尼說法！</p>
        </q>
        <p>尊者摩訶迦葉聞偷羅難陀比丘尼心不喜悅，口說惡言。聞已，語尊者阿難：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p>汝看是偷羅難陀比丘尼心不喜悅，口說惡言：云何──阿難！──我是販針兒，汝是針師，於汝前賣耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>尊者阿難語尊者摩訶迦葉：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>且止！當<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n10"/>忍！此愚癡老嫗，智慧薄少，不曾修習故。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p>阿難！汝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n11"/>豈聞世尊．如來．應．等正覺所<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n12"/>知見，於大眾中說月譬經，教<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0300n06"/>誡、教授比丘當如月譬住，常如新學，……（如是廣說）為說阿難如月譬住，常如新學耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>阿難答言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>不也，尊者摩訶迦葉！</p>
        </q>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p>阿難！汝聞世尊．如來．應．等正覺所知、所<pb ed="T" n="0302c"/>見，說言：<q who="anando">比丘！當如月譬住，常如新學，其唯摩訶迦葉比丘！</q>？</p>
        </q>
        <p>阿難答言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>如是！尊者摩訶迦葉。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p>阿難！汝曾為世尊．如來．應．等正覺所知、所見，於無量大眾中請汝來坐耶？又復世尊以同己廣大之德稱歎汝：<q who="gotamo">阿難離欲、惡不善法，……（乃至）漏盡通。</q>稱<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n13"/>歎？</p>
        </q>
        <p>答言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>不也，尊者摩訶迦葉！</p>
        </q>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p>如是，阿難！世尊．如來．應．等正覺於無量大眾中，口自說言：<q who="gotamo">復<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n14"/>於大眾中以同己廣大功德，離欲、惡不善法，……（乃至）漏盡通，稱歎摩訶迦葉耶？</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>阿難答言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p>如是，尊者摩訶迦葉！</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>時摩訶迦葉於比丘尼眾中師子吼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0302n15"/>已。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
