<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-905">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0226a13"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城迦蘭陀竹園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時尊者<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0226n04"/>摩訶迦葉、尊者<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0226n05"/>舍利弗住耆闍崛山中。時有眾多外道出家，詣尊者舍利弗，與尊者面相問訊，慰勞已，退坐一面，語尊者舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p>云何──舍利弗！──<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0226n06"/>如來有後生死耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p>諸外道！世尊說言：『此是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0226n07"/>無記。』</p>
        </q>
        <p>又問：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p>云何──舍利弗！──如來無後生死耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>舍利弗答言：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p>諸外道！世尊說言：『此是無記。』</p>
        </q>
        <p>又問：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p>舍利弗！如來有後生死，無後生死耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>舍利弗答言：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p>世尊說言：『此是無記。』</p>
        </q>
        <p>又問舍利弗：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p>如來非有後生死，非無後生死耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>舍利弗答言：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p>諸外道！世尊說言：『此是無記。』</p>
        </q>
        <p>諸外道出家又問尊者舍利弗：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p>云何所問：『如來有後生死，無後生死，有後無後，非有後非無後？』一切答言：「世尊<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0226n08"/>說：『此是無記。』？云何為上座如愚如癡，不善不辯，如嬰兒無自性智！</p>
        </q>
        <p>作此語已，從坐起去。</p>
        <p>爾時尊者摩訶<pb ed="T" n="0226b"/>迦葉、尊者舍利弗相去不遠，各坐樹下，晝日禪思。尊者舍利弗知諸外道出家去已，詣尊者摩訶迦葉所，共相問訊，慰勞已，退坐一面，以向與諸外道出家所論說事具白尊者摩訶迦葉：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p>尊者摩訶迦葉！何因何緣世尊不記說後有生死，後無生死，後有後無，非有非無生死耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p>尊者摩訶迦葉語舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p>若說如來後有生死者，是則為色。若說如來無後生死，是則為色。若說如來有後生死、無後生死，是則為色。若說如來非有後、非無後生死，是則為色。如來者，色已盡，心善解脫。言有後生死者，此則不然。無後生死、有後無後、非有後非無後生死，此亦不然。如來者，色已盡，心善解脫，甚深廣大，無量無數，寂滅涅槃。舍利弗！若說如來有後生死者，是則為受、為想、為行、為識、為動、為慮、為虛誑、為有為、為愛、……（乃至）非有非無後有亦如是說。如來者，愛已盡，心善解脫，是故說後有者不然。後無、後有無、後非有非無者不然。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0226n09"/>如來者，愛已盡，心善解脫，甚深廣大，無量無數，寂滅涅槃。舍利弗！如是因，如是緣故，有問世尊：如來若有、若無、若有無、若非有非無後生死，不可記說。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>時二正士共論議已，各還本處。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
