<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0912">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0228c15"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住瞻婆國揭伽池側。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有王頂聚落主來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面。</p>
        <p>爾時世尊告王頂聚落主：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>今者眾生依於二邊。何等為二？一者樂著卑下、田舍、常人凡夫五欲。二者自苦方便，不正、非義饒益。聚落主！有三種樂受欲樂：卑下、田舍、常人凡夫。有三種自苦方便，不正、非義饒益。
                 聚落主！何等為三種卑下、田舍、常人凡夫樂受欲樂？有受欲者，非法濫取，不以安樂自供，不供養父母、給足兄弟、妻子、奴婢、眷屬、朋友、知識，亦不隨時供養沙門、婆羅門，仰求勝處安樂果報、未來生天，是名世間第一受欲。
                 復次──聚落主！──受欲樂者，以法、非法濫取財物，以樂自供，供養父母，給足兄弟、妻子、奴婢、眷屬、朋友、知識，而不隨時供養沙門、婆羅門，<pb ed="T" n="0229a"/>
              仰求勝處安樂果報、未來生天，是名第二受欲樂者。
                               復次──聚落主！──有受欲樂者，以法求財，不以濫取，以樂自供，供養父母，給足兄弟、妻子、奴婢、眷屬、知識，隨時供養沙門、婆羅門，仰求勝處安樂果報、未來生天，是名第三受欲樂者。
                               聚落主！我不一向
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n01"/>
              說受欲平等。我說受欲者其人卑下，我說受欲者是其中人，我說受欲者是其勝人。
                               何等為卑下受欲者？謂非法濫取，（……乃至）不仰求勝處安樂果報、未來生天，是名我說卑下者受欲。
                                   何等為中人受欲？謂受欲者以法、非法而求財物，（……乃至）不求未來生天，是名我說第二中人受欲。
                                   何等為我說勝人受欲？謂彼以法求財，（……乃至）未來生天，是名我說第三勝人受欲。
                               何等為三種自苦方便，是苦非法、不正、非義饒益？有一自苦枯槁活，初始犯戒、污戒，彼修種種苦行，精勤方便住處住。彼不能現法得離熾然、過人法、勝妙知見安樂住。聚落主！是名第一自苦方便枯槁活。
                                   復次自苦方便枯槁活，始不犯戒、污戒，而修種種苦行，亦不由此現法得離熾然、過人法、勝妙知見安樂住。是名第二自苦方便枯槁活。
                                   復次自苦方便枯槁活，不初始犯戒、污戒，然修種種苦行方便，亦不能現法離熾然、得過人法、勝妙知見安樂住，是名第三自苦方便枯槁活。
                               聚落主！我不說一切自苦方便枯槁活悉等。我說有自苦方便是卑劣人，有說自苦方便是中人，有說自苦方便是勝人。
                                   何等自苦方便卑劣人？若彼自苦方便，初始犯戒、
            <pb ed="T" n="0229b"/>
              污戒，（……乃至）不得勝妙知見安樂住，是名我說自苦方便卑劣人。
                                   何等為自苦方便中人？若彼自苦方便，不初始犯戒、污戒，（……乃至）不得勝妙知見安樂住，是名我說自苦方便中間人。
                                   何等為自苦方便勝人？若彼自苦方便枯槁活，不初始犯戒、污戒，（……乃至）不得勝妙知見安樂住，是名我說自苦方便勝人。
                               聚落主！是名三種自苦方便，是苦非法、不正、非義饒益。
                               聚落主！有道有跡，
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n02"/>不向三種受欲隨順方便：卑下、田舍、常人凡夫；不向三種自苦方便；是苦非法、不正、非義饒益。聚落主！何等為道，何等為跡，不向三種受欲、三種自苦方便？聚落主！為欲貪障<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n03"/>閡故，或欲自害，或欲害他，或欲俱害，現法後世得斯罪報，心法憂苦。瞋恚、癡所障，或欲自害，或欲害他，或欲俱害，現法後世得斯罪報，心法憂苦。若離貪障，不欲方便自害、害他、自他俱害，不現法後世受斯罪報，彼心、心法常受喜樂。如是離瞋恚、愚癡障<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n03"/>閡，不欲自害，不欲害他、自他俱害，不現法後世受斯罪報，彼心、心法常受安樂。於現法中，遠離熾然，不待時節，親近涅槃。即此身現緣自覺知。聚落主。如此現法永離熾然。不待時節。親近涅槃，即此現身緣自覺知者，為八聖道：正見、（……乃至）正定。</p>
        </q>
        <p>當其世尊說是法時，王頂聚落主遠塵離垢，得法眼淨。時王頂聚落主見法，得法，知法，深入於法，度疑不由於他，於正法、律得無所畏，即從坐起，整衣服，合掌白佛：<q who="rasiya">
            <p>我今已度。世尊！歸佛、歸法、歸比<pb ed="T" n="0229c"/>丘僧。從今盡壽為優婆塞。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>時聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
