<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0913">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0229c03"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n05"/>力士人間遊行，到<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n06"/>欝鞞羅住處鸚鵡閻浮林。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n07"/>竭曇聚落主，聞沙門瞿曇在力士人間遊行，至欝鞞羅聚落鸚鵡閻浮林，說現法苦集、苦沒。<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>我當往詣彼沙門瞿曇！若我詣沙門瞿曇者，彼必為我說現<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n08"/>法苦集、苦沒。</p>
          </q>即往彼欝鞞羅聚落，詣世尊所，稽首禮足，退坐一面，白佛言：<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>世尊！我聞世尊常為人說現法苦集、苦沒。善哉！世尊！為我說現法苦集、苦沒。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我若說過去法苦集、苦沒者，知汝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n09"/>於彼為信、為不信，為欲、不欲，為念、不念，為樂、不樂。汝今苦不？我若說未來苦集、苦沒者，知汝於彼為信、不信，為欲、不欲，為念、不念，為樂、不樂。汝今苦不？我今於此說現法苦集、苦沒。聚落主！若眾生所有苦生，彼一切皆以欲為本。欲生、欲集、欲起、欲因、欲緣而苦生。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主白佛言：<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>世尊！極略說法，不廣分別，我所不解。善哉！世尊！唯願廣說，令我等解！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我今問汝，隨汝意說。聚落主！於意云何？若眾生於此欝鞞羅聚落住者，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n10"/>是若縛、若打、若責、若殺，汝心當起憂、悲、惱苦不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主白佛言：<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>世尊！亦不一向。若諸眾生於此欝鞞羅聚落住者，於我有欲、有貪、有愛、有念、相習近者，彼遭若縛、若打、若責、若殺，我則生憂、悲、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n11"/>惱苦。若彼眾生所無欲、貪、愛、念、相習近者，彼遭縛、打、責、殺，我何為橫生憂、悲、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0229n11"/>惱苦？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>
              <pb ed="T" n="0230a"/>是故當知：眾生種種苦生，彼一切皆以欲為本。欲生、欲習、欲起、欲因、欲緣而生眾苦。聚落主！於意云何？汝依父母不相見者，則生欲、貪、愛、念不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主言：<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>不也，世尊！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>聚落主！於意云何？若見、若聞彼依父母，當起欲、愛、念不？</p>
        </q>
        <p>聚落主言：<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>如是，世尊！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>復問：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>聚落主！於意云何？彼依父母若無常變異者，當起憂、悲、惱苦不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主言：<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>如是，世尊！若依父母無常變異者，我或<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n01"/>隣死，豈唯憂、悲、惱苦！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>是故當知：若諸眾生所有苦生，一切皆以愛欲為本。欲生、欲集、欲起、欲因、欲緣而生苦。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主言：<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>奇哉！世尊！善說如此依父母譬。我有依父母，居在異處。我日日遣信問其安否。使未時還，我以憂苦，況復無常，而無憂苦？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>是故我說：其諸眾生所有憂苦，一切皆以欲為根本。欲生、欲集、欲起、欲因、欲緣而生憂苦。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>若有四愛念無常變異者，則四憂苦生。若三、二，若一愛念無常變異者，則一憂苦生。聚落主！若都無愛念者，則無憂苦塵勞。</p>
          </q>即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="7" xml:id="cgtn0099-0913a">
            <l>若無世間愛念者<caesura/>則無憂苦塵勞患</l>
            <l>一切憂苦消滅盡<caesura/>猶如蓮<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n02"/>花不著水</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>當其世尊說是法時，揭曇聚落主遠塵離垢，得法眼淨，見法得法，深入於法，度諸狐疑不由於他、不由他度，於正法、律得無所畏。從坐起，整衣服，合掌白佛：<q who="gandhagata">
            <p>已度，世尊！我以超越。我從今日歸佛、歸法、歸比丘僧，盡其壽命為優婆塞，唯憶持我！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此<pb ed="T" n="0230b"/>經已，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n03"/>揭曇聚落主聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
