<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0914">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0230b03"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在摩竭提國人間遊行，與千二百五十比丘、千優婆塞、五百乞殘食人，從城至城，從聚落至聚落，人間遊行，至<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n05"/>那羅聚落好衣菴羅園中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n06"/>刀師氏聚落主是尼揵弟子，詣<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n07"/>
            尼揵所，禮尼揵足，退坐一面。
                             爾時尼揵語刀師氏聚落主：
          <q who="niganthanataputta">
            <p>汝能共沙門瞿曇作蒺<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n08"/>藜論，令沙門瞿曇不得語、不得不語耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主言：<q who="asibandhakaputta">
            <p>阿梨！我立何等論為蒺<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n08"/>蔾論，令沙門瞿曇不得語、不得不語？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>尼揵語聚落主言：<q who="niganthanataputta">
            <p>汝往詣沙門瞿曇所，作是問：<q who="asibandhakaputta">瞿曇！常願欲令諸家福利具足增長，作如是願、如是說不？</q>若答汝言『不』者，汝當問言：<q who="asibandhakaputta">沙門瞿曇！與凡愚夫有何等異？</q>若言『有願有說』者，當復問言：<q who="asibandhakaputta">沙門瞿曇！若有如是願、如是說者，今云何於飢饉世，遊行人間，將諸大眾千二百五十比丘、千優婆塞、五百乞殘食人，從城至城，從村至村，<choice>
                  <sic>捐</sic>
                  <corr resp="CBETA">損</corr>
                </choice>費世間，如大雨雹，雨已，乃是減損，非增益也。瞿曇所說，殊不相應，不類不似，前後相違。</q>如是，聚落主！是名蒺蔾論，令彼沙門瞿曇不得語、不得不語。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時刀師氏聚落主受尼揵勸教已，詣佛所恭敬問訊，恭敬問訊已，退坐一面，白佛：<q who="asibandhakaputta">
            <p>瞿曇！常欲願令諸家福利增長不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>如來長夜欲令諸家福利增長，亦常作是說。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主言：<q who="asibandhakaputta">
            <p>若如是者，云何，瞿曇！於飢饉世人間乞食，將諸大眾……乃至不似不類，前後相<pb ed="T" n="0230c"/>違？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我憶九十一劫以來，不見一人施一比丘，有盡有減。聚落主！汝觀今日有人家大富，多錢財、多眷屬、多僕從，當知其家長夜好施，真實寂止，故致斯福利。聚落主！有八因緣，令人損減福利不增。何等為八？王所逼、賊所劫、火所焚、水所漂、藏自消減、抵債不還、怨憎殘破、惡子費用。有是八種為錢財難聚。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n09"/>聚落主！我說無常為第九句。如是，聚落主！汝捨九因九緣，而言『沙門瞿曇破壞他家』，不捨惡言、不捨惡見，如鐵槍投水，身壞命終，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0230n10"/>生地獄中。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時刀師氏聚落主心生恐怖，身毛皆豎，白佛言：<q who="asibandhakaputta">
            <p>世尊！我今悔過！如愚如癡，不善不辯，於瞿曇所不實斯誑，虛說妄語。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，從座起去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
