<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0916">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0231c03"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住那羅聚落好衣菴羅園中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有刀師氏聚落主——尼揵弟子，來詣佛所，稽首禮足，退坐一面。
                    爾時世尊告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>欲何所論？<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0231n05"/>尼揵若提子為何所說？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主言：<q who="asibandhakaputta">
            <p>彼尼揵若提子說：<q who="niganthanataputta">殺生者，一切皆墮<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0231n06"/>泥<choice>
                  <sic>梨</sic>
                  <corr resp="CBETA">犁</corr>
                </choice>中，以多行故，則將至彼；如是盜、邪婬、妄語皆墮泥犁中，以多行故，則將至彼。</q>
            </p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>若如尼揵若提子說『殺生者墮泥犁中，以多行故，而往生彼』者，則無有眾生墮泥犁中。聚落主！於意云何？何等眾生於一切時有心殺生？復於何時有心不殺生？乃至何時有心妄語？何時有心不妄語？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主白佛言：<q who="asibandhakaputta">
            <p>世尊！人於晝夜，少時有心殺生，……乃至少時有心妄語，而多時不有心殺生，……乃至妄語。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>若如是者，豈非無有人墮於泥犁中耶？如尼揵所說：<q who="niganthanataputta">有人殺生者，一切墮泥犁中，多習行者將往生彼，……乃至妄語亦復如是。</q>聚落主！彼大師出興於出，覺想籌量，入覺想地住。於凡夫地自辯所說，隨意籌量，為諸弟子作如是說法，言『殺生者，一切皆墮泥犁中，多習<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0231n07"/>行將往生彼，乃至妄語亦復如是。』彼諸弟子若信其說，言：『我大師知其所知，見其所見，能為弟子作如是說：若殺生者，一切皆墮泥梨中，多習行故，將往生彼。我本有心殺生、偷盜、邪婬、妄語，當墮泥犁中。』得如是見，乃至不捨此見，不厭彼業，不覺彼悔，於未來世，不捨殺生，乃至不捨妄語，彼意解脫不滿足，慧解脫亦不滿足。意解脫不滿足、慧解脫不滿足故，則為謗聖邪見；邪見因緣故，身壞命終，生惡趣泥犁中。如是，聚落主！有因、有緣眾生煩惱，有因、有緣眾生業煩惱。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>聚落主！如來、應、等正覺、明行足、善逝、世間解、無上士、調御丈夫、天人師、佛、世尊出興於世，常為眾生呵責殺生，讚歎不殺；呵責偷盜、邪婬、妄語，讚歎不盜、不婬、不妄語。常以此法，化諸聲聞，令念樂信重，言：『我大師知其所知，見其所見，呵責殺生，讚歎不殺，……乃至呵責妄語，讚歎不妄語。我從昔來，以愚癡無慧，有心殺生。我緣是故，今自悔責。』雖不能令彼業不為，且因此悔責故，於未來世，得離殺生，……乃至得離盜、婬、妄語，亦得滿足正意解脫，滿足慧解脫。意解脫、慧解脫滿足已，得不謗賢聖，正見成就；正見因緣故，得生善趣天上。如是，聚落主！有因、有緣眾生業煩惱清淨。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>聚落主！彼多聞聖弟子作如是學：隨時晝夜觀察所起少有心殺生、多有心不殺生。若於有心殺生，當自悔責，不是不類。若不有心殺生，無怨無憎，心生隨喜；隨喜已，歡喜生；歡喜已，心<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0232n01"/>猗息；心<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0232n01"/>猗息已，心受樂；受樂已，則心定；心<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0232n02"/>定已，聖弟子心與慈俱，無怨無嫉，無有瞋恚，廣大無量，滿於一方，正受住。二方、三方，乃至四方、四維、上下、一切世間，心與慈俱，無怨無嫉，無有瞋恚，廣大無量，善修習，充滿諸方，具足正受住。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊以爪<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0232n03"/>甲抄少土，語刀師氏聚落主言：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>云何，聚落主！我爪<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0232n03"/>甲土多？大地為多？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>聚落主白佛言：<q who="asibandhakaputta">
            <p>世尊！爪<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0232n03"/>甲土少少耳，大地土無量無數。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告聚落主：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>如甲上之土甚少，大地之土其數無量。如是心與慈俱，修習多修習，諸有量業者，如<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0232n03"/>甲上土，不能將去，不能令住。如是偷盜對以悲心，邪婬對以喜心，妄語對以捨心，不得為比。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>說是語時刀師氏聚落主遠塵離垢，得法眼淨。聚落主見法、得法、覺法、知法、深入於法，離諸狐疑不由於他、不隨於他，於正法、律得無所畏。從座起，整衣服，右膝著地，合掌白佛：<q who="asibandhakaputta">
            <p>我已度，世尊！已越，世尊！我今歸佛、歸法、歸比丘僧，盡其壽命，為優婆塞。世尊！譬如士夫欲求燈明，取其馬尾，以為燈炷，欲吹令<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0232n04"/>然，終不得明，徒自疲勞，燈竟不然。我亦如是，欲求明智，於諸愚癡尼揵子所，愚癡習近，愚癡和合，愚癡奉事，徒自勞苦，不得明智，是故我今重歸依佛、歸法、歸僧。從今以去，於彼尼揵愚癡不善不辯者所，少信、少敬、少愛、少念，於今遠離。是故，我今第三歸佛、歸法、歸僧，乃至盡壽，為優婆塞，自淨其心。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>時刀師氏聚落主聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
