<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0922">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0234a16"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城迦蘭陀竹園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊告諸比丘：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>世有四種良馬，有良馬駕以平乘，顧其鞭影馳<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0234n04"/>駃，善能觀察御者形勢，遲速左右，隨御者心，是名，比丘！世間良馬第一之德。復次，比丘！世間良馬不能顧影而自驚察，然以鞭<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0234n05"/>杖觸其毛尾則能驚速察御者心，遲速左右，是名世間第二良馬。復次，比丘！若世間良馬不能顧影，及觸皮毛能隨人心，而以鞭杖小侵皮肉則能驚察，隨御者心，遲速左右，是名，比丘！第三良馬。復次，比丘！世間良馬不能顧其鞭影，及觸皮毛，小侵膚肉，乃以鐵錐刺身，徹膚傷骨，然後方驚，牽車著路，隨御者心，遲速左右，是名世間第四良馬。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <q who="gotamo">
            <p>如是於正<pb ed="T" n="0234b"/>法、律有四種善男子。何等為四？謂善男子聞他聚落有男子、女人疾病困苦，乃至死，聞已，能生恐怖，依正思惟，如彼良馬顧影則調，是名第一善男子於正法、律能自調伏。復次，善男子不能聞他聚落若男、若女老、病、死苦，能生怖畏，依正思惟；見他聚落若男、若女老、病、死苦，則生怖畏，依正思惟，如彼良馬觸共毛尾，能速調伏，隨御者心，是名第二善男子於正法、律能自調伏。復次，善男子不能聞、見他聚落中男子、女人老、病、死苦，生怖畏心，依正思惟；然見聚落、城邑有善知識及所親近老、病、死苦，則生怖畏，依正思惟，如彼良馬，觸其膚肉，然後調伏，隨御者心，是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0234n06"/>名第三善男子於聖法、律而自調伏。復次，善男子不能聞、見他聚落中男子、女人及所親近老、病、死苦，生怖畏心，依正思惟；然於自身老、病、死苦能生厭怖，依正思惟，如彼良馬侵肌徹骨，然後乃調，隨御者心，是名第四善男子於聖法、律能自調伏。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行！</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
