<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 149. It is found in the 佛說馬有八態譬人經 Sutra at T.02.0115.0507.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T02.0115.0507a10">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t02.0115.0507a10"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>聞如是。一時佛在舍衛國行在祇樹給孤獨園。多比丘僧俱。</p>
        <p>佛告諸比丘。</p>
        <p>馬有弊惡態八。何等八。一態者解<g>[襾/(革*奇)]</g>韁時便掣車欲走。二態者駕車跳<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n03"/>
          <g>[跳-兆+梁]</g>欲嚙人。三態者便舉前兩<g>[腳-谷+去]</g>掣車走。四態者便<g>[跳-兆+翕]</g>車軨。五態者便人立持軛摩<g>[打-丁+沙]</g>車<g>[去*ㄗ]</g>行。六態者便傍行邪走。七態者便掣車馳走。得濁泥抵止住不復行。八態者懸<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n04"/>
          <g>[笐-〦+(兜-儿)]</g>餒之熟視不肯食。其主牽去欲駕之。遽<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n05"/>唅<g>[口*翕]</g>噬欲食不能得食。</p>
        <p>佛言。</p>
        <p>人亦有弊惡態八。何等為八。一態者聞說經便走不欲聽。如馬解<g>[襾/(革*奇)]</g>韁掣車走時。二態者聞說經意不解不知語所趣向。便瞋跳<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n03"/>
          <g>[跳-兆+梁]</g>不欲聞。如馬駕車時跳<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n03"/>
          <g>[跳-兆+梁]</g>欲嚙人時。三態者聞說經便逆不受。如馬舉前兩<g>[腳-谷+去]</g>掣車走時四態者聞說經便罵。如馬<g>[跳-兆+翕]</g>車軨時五態者聞說經。便起去如馬人。立持軛摩<g>[打-丁+沙]</g>車<g>[去*ㄗ]</g>行時。六態者聞說經不肯聽<g>[卑*頁]</g>頭邪視耳語。如馬傍行邪走時。七態者聞說經便欲窮難。問之不能相應答。便死抵妄語。如馬得濁泥便止不復行時。八態者聞說經不肯聽。反念<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n06"/>婬泆多求不欲聽受。<pb ed="T" n="0507b"/>死<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n07"/>入惡道時。乃遽欲學問行道。亦不能復得行道。如馬懸<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0507n04"/>
          <g>[笐-〦+(兜-儿)]</g>餧之熟視不肯食。其主牽去欲駕之。乃遽唅<g>[口*翕]</g>噬亦不得食。</p>
        <p>佛言。我說馬八態。惡人亦有八惡態如是。</p>
        <p>諸比丘聞經歡喜。作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
