<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0924">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0235a06"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城迦蘭陀竹園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊告諸比丘：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>世間馬有八態。何等為八？謂惡馬臨駕車時後腳蹹人，前腳跪地，奮頭齧人，是名世間馬第一態。復次，惡馬就駕車時低頭振軛，是名世間惡馬第二之態。復次，世間惡馬就駕車時下道而去，或復偏厲車，令其翻覆，是名第三之態。復次，世間惡馬就駕車時仰頭卻行，是名世間惡馬第四之態。復次，世間惡馬就駕車時小得鞭杖，或斷繮折勒，縱橫馳走，是名第五之態。復次，世間惡馬就駕車時舉前兩足，而作人立，是名第六之態。復次，世間惡馬就駕之時加之鞭杖，安住不動，是名第七之態。復次，世間惡馬就駕之時叢聚四腳，伏地不起，是名第八之態。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>如是，世間惡丈夫於正法、律有八種過。何等為八？若比丘！諸梵行者以見聞疑罪而發舉時彼則瞋恚，反呵責彼言：<q>汝愚癡，不辯不善，他立舉汝，汝云何舉我？</q>如彼惡馬後腳雙蹹，前腳跪地，斷鞅折軛，是名丈夫於正法、律第一之過。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>復次，比丘！諸梵行者以見聞疑舉，反出他罪，猶如惡馬怒項折軛，是名丈夫於正法、律第二之過。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>復次，比丘！諸梵行者以見聞疑舉，不以正答，橫說餘事，瞋恚<pb ed="T" n="0235b"/>憍慢，隱覆嫌恨，不忍，無所由作，如彼惡馬不由正路，令車翻覆，是名丈夫於正法、律第三之過。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>復次，比丘！諸梵行者以見聞疑舉，令其憶念，而作是言：『我不憶念！』觝突不伏，如彼惡馬卻縮轉退，是名丈夫於正法、律第四之過。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>復次，比丘！諸梵行者以見聞疑舉時，輕蔑不數其人，亦不數僧，攝持衣缽，隨意而去，如彼惡馬加以鞭杖，縱橫馳走，是名丈夫於正法、律第五之過。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>復次，比丘！諸梵行者以見聞疑舉時，自處高床、與諸上座共諍曲直，如彼惡馬雙腳人立，是名丈夫於正法、律第六之過。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>復次，比丘！諸梵行者以見聞疑舉時，默然不應，以惱大眾，如彼惡馬加其鞭杖，兀然不動，是名丈夫於正法、律第七之過。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>復次，比丘！諸梵行者以見聞疑舉時，則便捨戒，自生退沒，到於寺門，而作是言：『汝默然快喜安住，我自捨戒退沒。』如彼惡馬叢聚四足，伏地不動，是名丈夫於正法、律第八之過。是名比丘於正法、律有八種丈夫過惡。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行！</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
