<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0925">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0235b22"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城迦蘭陀竹園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊告諸比丘：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>世間良馬有八種德成就者，隨人所欲，取道多少。何等為八？生於良馬鄉，是名良馬第一之德。復次，體性溫良，不驚恐人，是名良馬第二之德。復次，良馬不擇飲食，是名良馬第三之德。復次，良馬厭惡不淨，擇地而臥，是名良馬第四之德。復次，良馬諸情態速為調馬者現，馬師<pb ed="T" n="0235c"/>調習，速捨其態，是名良馬第五之德。復次，良馬安於駕乘，不顧餘馬，隨其輕重，能盡其力，是名良馬第六之德。復次，良馬常隨正路，不隨非道，是名良馬第七之德。復次，良馬若病、若老，勉力駕乘，不厭不倦，是名良馬第八之德。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>如是，丈夫於正法、律八德成就，當知是賢士夫。何等為八？謂賢士夫住於正戒波羅提木叉律儀，威儀行處具足，見微細罪，能生怖畏，受持學戒，是名丈夫於正法、律第一之德。復次，丈夫性自賢善，善調善住，不惱、不怖諸梵行者，是名丈夫第二之德。復次，丈夫次行乞食，隨其所得，若粗、若細，其心平等，不嫌、不著，是名丈夫第三之德。復次，丈夫心生厭離於身惡業，口、意惡業，惡不善法及諸煩惱，重受諸有熾然苦報，於未來世生、老、病、死、憂、悲、惱苦，增其厭離，是名丈夫第四之德。復次，丈夫若有沙門過，諂曲不實，速告大師及善知識，大師說法則時除斷，是名丈夫第五之德。復次，丈夫學心具足，作如是念：『設使餘人學以不學，我悉當學。』是名丈夫第六之德。復次，丈夫行八正道，不行非道，是名丈夫第七之德。復次，丈夫乃至盡壽，精勤方便，不厭不倦，是名丈夫第八之德。如是丈夫八德成就，隨其行地，能速昇進。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行！</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
