<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0935">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0239b12"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住迦毘羅衛國尼拘律園中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時釋氏名曰<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0239n03"/>沙陀，語釋氏摩訶男：<q who="godha">
            <p>世尊說須陀洹成就幾種法？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>摩訶男答言：<q who="mahanama">
            <p>世尊說須陀洹成就四法。何等為四？謂於佛不壞淨，法、僧不壞淨，聖戒成就，是名四法成就須陀洹。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>釋氏沙陀語釋氏摩訶男：<q who="godha">
            <p>莫作是說！莫作是言世尊說四法成就須陀洹。然<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0239n04"/>彼三法三法成就須陀洹。何等為三？謂於佛不壞淨、於法不壞淨、於僧不壞淨，如是三法成就須陀洹。</p>
          </q>如是第三說。釋氏摩訶男不能令沙陀受四法，釋氏沙陀不能令摩訶男受三法，共詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面。
            釋氏摩訶男白佛言：<q who="mahanama">
            <p>世尊！釋氏沙陀來詣我所，問我言：<q who="godha">世尊說幾法成就須陀洹？</q>我即答言：<q who="mahanama">世尊說四法成就須陀洹。何等為四？謂於佛不壞淨，於法、僧不壞淨，聖戒成就，如是四法成就須陀洹。</q>釋氏沙陀作是言：<q who="godha">釋氏摩訶男！莫作是<pb ed="T" n="0239c"/>語！世尊說四法成就須陀洹，但三法成就須陀洹。何等為三？謂於佛不壞淨、於法不壞淨、於僧不壞淨，世尊說如是三法成就須陀洹。</q>如是再三說，我亦不能令彼釋氏沙陀受四法，釋氏沙陀亦不能令我受三法，是故俱來詣世尊所。今問世尊，須陀洹成就幾法？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時沙陀釋氏從坐起，為佛作禮，合掌白佛：<q who="godha">
            <p>世尊！若有如是像類法起，一者世尊，一者比丘僧，我寧隨世尊，不隨比丘僧。或有如是像類法起，一者世尊，一者比丘尼僧、優婆塞、優婆夷、若天、若魔、若梵、若沙門、婆羅門、諸天、世人，我寧隨世尊，不隨餘眾。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊告釋氏摩訶男：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>如摩訶男！釋氏沙陀作如是論，汝<choice>
                <sic>等</sic>
                <corr resp="CBETA">當</corr>
              </choice>云何？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>摩訶男白佛：<q who="mahanama">
            <p>世尊！彼沙陀釋氏作如是論，我知復<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0239n05"/>可說，我唯言善，唯言真實。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告摩訶男：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>是故當知四法成就須陀洹，於佛不壞淨，於法、僧不壞淨，聖戒成就，如是受持。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>時釋氏摩訶男聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，從坐起，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
