<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0592">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0157b18"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0157n06"/>寒林<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0157n07"/>中丘塚間。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時給孤獨長者有小因緣至王舍城，止宿長者舍。夜見長者告其妻子、僕使、作人言：<q who="護彌長者">
            <p>汝等皆起，破樵<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0030n01"/>然火，炊飯<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0157n08"/>
              <g ref="g000">[麩-夫+并]</g>調和眾<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0157n09"/>味，莊嚴堂舍。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>給孤獨長者見已，作是念：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>今此長者何所為作？為嫁女娶婦耶？為請賓客、國王、大臣耶？</p>
          </q>念已，即問長者：<q who="anathapindik">
            <p>汝何所作？為嫁女娶婦？為請賓客、國王、大臣耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時彼長者答給孤獨長者言：<q who="護彌長者">
            <p>我不嫁女娶婦，亦不請呼國王、大臣，唯欲請佛及比丘僧，設供養耳。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時給孤獨長者聞未曾聞佛名字已，心大歡喜，身諸毛孔皆悉怡<pb ed="T" n="0157c"/>悅，問彼長者言：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>何名為佛？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>長者答言：<q who="護彌長者">
            <p>有沙門瞿曇，是釋種子，於釋種中剃除鬚髮，著袈裟衣，正信、非家、出家學道，得阿耨多羅三藐三菩提，是名為佛。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>給孤獨長者言：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>云何名僧？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>彼長者言：<q who="護彌長者">
            <p>若婆羅門種剃除鬚髮，著袈裟衣，信家、非家，而隨佛出家；或剎利種、毘舍種、首陀羅種善男子等剃除鬚髮，著袈裟衣，正信、非家，彼佛出家而隨出家，是名為僧。今日請佛及現前僧，設諸供養。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>給孤獨長者問彼長者言：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>我今可得往見世尊不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>彼長者答言：<q who="護彌長者">
            <p>汝且住此，我請世尊來至我舍，於此得見。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時給孤獨長者即於其夜至心念佛，因得睡眠。天猶未明，忽見明相，謂天已曉，欲出其舍，行向城門，至城門下，夜始二更，城門未開――王家常法，待遠使命來往，至初夜盡，城門乃閉，中夜已盡，輒復開門，欲令行人早得往來。
                 爾時給孤獨長者見城門開，而作是念：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>定是夜過天曉門開。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>乘明相出於城門，出城門已，明相即滅，輒還闇冥。給孤獨長者心即恐怖，身毛為豎：得無為人及非人，或姦<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0157n10"/>
            姣人恐怖我耶？即便欲還。
                             爾時城門側有天神住。時彼天神即放身光，從其城門至寒林丘塚間光明普照，告給孤獨長者言：
          </p>
        <p>
          <q who="sivaka">
            <p>汝且前進，可得勝利，慎勿退還！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時彼天神即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="sivaka">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0592a">
            <l>善良馬百匹<caesura/>黃金滿百斤</l>
            <l>騾車及馬車<caesura/>各各有百乘</l>
            <l>種種諸珍奇<caesura/>重寶載其上</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0158a"/>宿命種善根<caesura/>得如此福報</l>
            <l>若人宗重心<caesura/>向佛行一步</l>
            <l>十六分之一<caesura/>過前福之上</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>
          <q who="sivaka">
            <p>是故，長者！汝當前進，慎勿退還！</p>
          </q>即復說偈：</p>
        <q who="sivaka">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0592b">
            <l>雪山大龍象<caesura/>純金為莊飾</l>
            <l>巨身長大牙<caesura/>以此象施人</l>
            <l>不及向佛福<caesura/>十六分之一</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>
          <q who="sivaka">
            <p>是故，長者！當速前進，得其大利，非退還也。</p>
          </q>復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="sivaka">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0592c">
            <l>金菩闍國女<caesura/>其數有百人</l>
            <l>種種眾妙寶<caesura/>瓔珞具莊嚴</l>
            <l>以<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0158n01"/>是持施與<caesura/>不及行向佛</l>
            <l>一步之功德<caesura/>十六分之一</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>
          <q who="sivaka">
            <p>是故，長者！當速前進，得其勝利，非退還也。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時給孤獨長者問天神言：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>賢者！汝是何人？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>天神答言：<q who="sivaka">
            <p>我是摩頭息揵大摩那婆先，是長者善知識，於尊者舍利弗、大目揵連所起信敬心，緣斯功德，今得生天，典此城門，是故告長者：<q who="sivaka">但當進前，慎<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0158n02"/>莫退還！前進得利，非退還也！</q>
            </p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時給孤獨長者作是念：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>佛興於世，非為小事；得聞正法，亦非小事，是故天神勸我令進，往見世尊。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時給孤獨長者尋其光明，逕至寒林丘塚間。爾時世尊出房<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0158n03"/>露地經行，給孤獨長者遙見佛已，即至其前，以俗人禮法恭敬問訊：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>云何，世尊！安隱臥不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊說偈答<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0158n04"/>言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0592d">
            <l>婆羅門涅槃<caesura/>是則常安樂</l>
            <l>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0158n05"/>愛欲所不染<caesura/>解脫永無餘</l>
            <l>斷一切希望<caesura/>調伏心熾然</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0158b"/>心得寂止息<caesura/>止息安隱眠</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊將給孤獨長者往入房中，就座而坐，端身繫念。爾時世尊為其說法，示教照喜已，世尊說：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>諸法無常，宜布施福事、持戒福事、生天福事，欲味、欲患、欲出，遠離之福。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>給孤獨長者聞法、見法、得法、入法、解法，度諸疑惑，不由他信，不由他度，入正法、律，心得無畏，即從座起，正衣服，為佛作禮，右膝著地，合掌白佛言：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>已度，世尊！已度，善逝！我從今日盡其壽命，歸佛、歸法、歸比丘僧，為優婆塞，證知我！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊問給孤獨長者：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝名何等？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>長者白佛：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>名<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0158n06"/>須達多，以常給孤貧辛苦故，時人名我為給孤獨。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>世尊復問：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝居何處？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>長者白佛言：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>世尊！在拘薩羅人間，城名舍衛，唯願世尊來舍衛國，我當盡壽供養衣被、飲食、房舍、床臥、隨病湯藥。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛問長者：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>舍衛國有精舍不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>長者白佛：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>無也，世尊！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告長者：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝可於彼建立精舍，令諸比丘往來宿止。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>長者白佛：<q who="anathapindika">
            <p>但使世尊來舍衛國，我當造作精舍僧房，令諸比丘往來止住。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊默然受請。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>時長者知佛世尊默然受請已，從座起，稽首佛足而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
