<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0962">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0245b26"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時<name type="person">婆蹉種出家</name>來詣佛所，與世尊<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0245n07"/>
          <choice>
            <sic>而</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">面</corr>
          </choice>相問訊，問訊已，退坐一面，白佛言：</p>
        <p>
          <q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>瞿曇！云何瞿曇作如是見、如是說：<q who="gotamo">世間常，此是真<pb ed="T" n="0245c"/>實，餘則虛妄。</q>耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆蹉種出家：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我不作如是見、如是說：<q who="gotamo">世間常，是則真實，餘則虛妄。</q>
            </p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>云何瞿曇作如是見、如是說：<q who="gotamo">世間無常、常無常、非常非無常，有邊、無邊、邊無邊、非邊非無邊，命即是身、命異身異，如來有後死、無後死、有無後死、非有非無後死。</q>？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆蹉種出家：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我不作如是見、如是說，……乃至非有非無後死。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時婆蹉種出家白佛言：<q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>瞿曇！於此見，見何等過患，而於此諸見，一切不說？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆蹉種出家：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>若作是見――世間常，此則真實，餘則虛妄者，此是倒見、此是觀察見、此是動搖見、此是垢污見、此是結見，是苦、是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0245n08"/>閡、是惱、是熱，見結所繫，愚癡無聞凡夫於未來世，生、老、病、死、憂、悲、惱苦生。婆蹉種出家！若作是見——世<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0245n09"/>間無常、常無常、非常非無常，有邊、無邊、邊無邊、非有邊非無邊，是命是身、命異身異，如來有後死、無後死、有無後死、非有非無後死。此是倒見……乃至憂、悲、惱苦生。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆蹉種出家白佛：<q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>瞿曇！何所見？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆蹉種出家：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>如來所見已畢。婆蹉種出家！然如來見，謂見此苦聖諦、此苦集聖諦、此苦滅聖諦、此苦滅道跡聖諦；作如是知、如是見已，於一切見、一切受、一切生，一切我、我所見、我慢繫著使，斷滅、寂靜、清涼、真實，如是等解脫。比丘！生者不然，不生亦不然。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆蹉白佛：<q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>瞿曇！何故說言『生者不然』？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆蹉：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我今問汝，隨意答我。婆蹉！猶如有人於汝前然火，汝見火<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0226n13"/>然</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆蹉白佛：<q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>如是，瞿曇！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆蹉：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>若有<pb ed="T" n="0246a"/>人問汝：『向者火然，今在何處？為東方去耶？西方、南方、北方去耶？』如是問者，汝云何<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0246n01"/>說？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆蹉白佛：<q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>瞿曇！若有來作如是問者，我當作如是答：<q who="vacchagotta">若有於我前然火，薪草因緣故然；若不增薪，火則永滅，不復更起。東方、南方、西方、北方去者，是則不然。</q>
            </p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆蹉：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我亦如是說，色已斷已知，受、想、行、識已斷已知，斷其根本，如截多羅樹頭，無復生分，於未來世永不復起。若至東方，南、西、北方，是則不然，甚深廣大，無量無數永滅。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆蹉白佛：<q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>我當說譬。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆蹉：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>為知是時。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆蹉白佛：<q who="vacchagotta">
            <p>瞿曇！譬如近城邑聚落，有好淨地，生堅固林，有一大堅固樹，其生<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0246n02"/>已來經數千歲，日夜既久，枝葉零落，皮膚枯朽，唯幹獨立。如是，瞿曇！如來法、律離諸枝條<choice>
                <sic>
                  <g ref="g000">[柯-口+日]</g>
                </sic>
                <corr resp="CBETA">柯</corr>
              </choice>
            </p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>爾時婆蹉出家聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，<choice>
            <sic>彼</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">從</corr>
          </choice>坐起去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
