<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>Hosoda 1989a: 192-193</head>
        <p>From Noriaki Hosoda 細田典明: Bonbun Zōagongyō Busshosetsuhon Gedōsōō (1) [Sanskrit fragments from the Parivrājakasaṃyukta of the Saṃyuktāgama (1) 梵文《雑阿含経》仏所說品外道相応(Ⅰ)] In《藤田宏達博士還曆記念論集：インド哲学と仏教》[Indian Philosophy and Buddhism: Essays in honour of Professor Kotatsu Fujita on his sixtieth birthday] 185-206. Kyoto. This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 200.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:lang="sa">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="hos1989a.192"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <note type="reference">「富隣尼経」B1. 157 V1-V5: Pūrṇika(?) （AN V, pp. 154-155 (Puṇṇiya) が一般に対照されるものの、內容的には対応しない。）; 『雑含』第九六六経、『別訳』第二〇〇経「分匿（経においては「富那」。）」</note>
        <p>§ 4<note type="footnote">§4~§5：vgl. NidSa 22. 11-13.</note>
          <note type="reference">(B1. 157)</note>(athāyuṣmān pūrṇiko 'ciraprakrāntān saṃbahulān anyatīrthikaparivrājakān vi)[di]tvā yena<note type="footnote">yena......ārocayati.: vgl. NidSa 22. 18.</note>bhagavāṃs tenopa(jagāma. upetya bhaga)[va] tpā<note type="reference">(V2)</note>(dau śirasā vanditvā, ekānte nyaśīdat. ekāntaniṣaṇṇa āyuṣmān pūrṇiko yāvad e)vāsyābh[ūt]﹙.﹚ s(aṃba)[h](u)lair anyatīrthikapari(vrājakaiḥ sārdham antarāka)thā<note type="reference">(V3)</note>(samudāhāras tat sarvaṃ bhagavato vistareṇārocayati.) evaṃ cāha﹙.﹚</p>
        <p>§ 5  kaccid ahaṃ bhadanta (evaṃ vyā)kuruvāṇo no ca [bh](agavantam abhyācakṣe. nātisarāmy uktavādī cāhaṃ bhagavato dharmavā)[d](ī) ca dharma[s]ya cānudharmaṃ vyākaromi﹙.﹚ na ca me kaści(d āga)c(ch)e(tparataḥ saha dharmeṇa vādānuvādaṃ garhasthānīyo dharmaḥ.)</p>
        <p>§ 6  (tatthyaṃ tvaṃ pūrṇika vyākuruvāṇ)[o] no ca mām abhyācakṣase﹙.﹚ nātisarasy uktavādī ca (tvaṃ mama dharmavādī ca dharmasya cānudharmaṃ vyākaroṣi. na ca te kaścid āgacchet parataḥ saha dharmeṇa) [v]ādānuvādaṃ garhasthānīyo dharmaḥ |</p>
        <p>§ 7  tat kasmād dhetoḥ﹙.﹚ pū[r](vaṃ pūrṇika)......(ana)[bhi]sa(ma)yāt*﹙.﹚ śvāṃtrakulajātā<note type="footnote">Pischel: ge sa . yā taṃ śvātra(?); SHT V: ti saḥ yātaṃś=c=āṃtra. 問題点は二点あり、第一点については両者ともに yā taṃ と読むが、写真を見ると(SHT V, Tafel 71)、yā と taṃ の文字の間は線で結ばれてあり、ta の上にある点はアヌスヴァラーラではなくヴィラーマに解されろ（本稿「ヴィラーマの用法」参照）。漢訳の対応箇所は「不無間等」で、これに対応する梵語は na+abhisam√i- あるいは anabhisamaya- と考えられる。Vgl. NidSa 16. 4: yatrājñānam adarśanam anabhisamayaḥ.「於彼彼不知不見無無間等」（『大正蔵』二巻八五頁上二四）。yāt を語尾とすることから、anabhisamayāt を想定したが、動詞の変化形（z. B.: nābhisamiyāt）である可能性もあり、なお検討の余地がある。Vgl. SWTF 1. Lfg. S. 46; 2. Lfg. S. 127-128. 第二点は「亂如狗腸」以下の比喩に関わる表現で、パーリ・ニカーヤ (s. SHT V S. 169 Anm. 10), Mvy Nrn, 5390-3 (vgl. Lalitavistara. p. 205. 11-14) に類句が知られる。「亂如狗腸」にあたる箇所は、"tantākulakajātā" (DN Ⅱ, p. 55. 15; SN Ⅱ, p. 92. 16), "tantā kulakajātā" (SN Ⅳ, p. 158. 15), "tantākulajāto" (AN Ⅱ, p. 211. 33), "tantrajālajātāḥ" (Mvy 5390), "tantrākulajātasya" (LV p. 205. 11; s. BHSD s. v.)とあり、tantr˘ā- の部分が微妙に対照しない。しかし、「狗腸」にあたる梵語として *śvāntra- (śvan-+antra-) という語が想定される。この語は辞書には見られないが、前掲の AN や SN Ⅳ に対応する雑阿含の箇所には「為狗腸」（第九八四経『大正蔵』二巻二五六頁上二一）、「如狗肚臟」（第二一六経『大正蔵』二巻五四頁中二七）とあり、一方、DN に対応する中阿含第九七『大因経』では「如織機相鎖」（『大正蔵』一巻五七八頁中一七）、単行『人本欲生経』では「如織機」（『大正蔵』一巻二四二頁上六）とあることから、この比喩に関する定形句として tantra- 系と śvāntra- 系の二類が知られ、雑阿含は後者に拠るものであると言えよう。ちなみに、雑阿含第九八四経全体に相当する蔵文が Upāyikā に収録されているが（次注榎本論文九二頁注三参照）、当該箇所につぃては "dru bu 'dzings pa lta bu, rtswa mun dza dang bal (ba) dza lta bu dan." (P. ed. Tu 109 b5) とあり、"guḍaguṃjijātā muṃjabalbajajātā" に対応し「亂如狗腸」にあたる蔵語はない。</note>guḍaguṃji[j](ā)tā (muṃjabalbajajātā ājavaṃjavasamāpannā asmāl lokāt paraṃ lokaṃ<note type="footnote">lokaṃ......na vyativarttaṃte.: vgl. SHT V Kat.-Nr. 1375 a V4; b V1; Kat.-Nr. 1031 a R3. この箇所は両断簡とも前出の雑阿含第九八四経の一部であり、Kat.-Nr. 1031 と『雑阿含経』との比定は榎本文雄氏によってなされた。「『雑阿含経』関係の梵文写本断片ーー『Turfan出土梵文写本目録』第5卷をめぐってーー」、（『仏教研究』第十五号、八一ー九三頁、昭和六十年）参照。</note>parāl lokād imaṃ lo)kaṃ sa[n](dh)āvaṃ[t]i saṃsaraṃti sa[ṃ]sā(rān na v)yativarttaṃte﹙.﹚</p>
        <p>§ 8  mi[th](yāmāneṣu pūrṇika)......(apariśeṣam<note type="footnote">apariśeṣam......gacchet.: vgl. SHT V Kat.-Nr. 1156 b V1.</note>adhyastaṃ parikṣayaṃ paryādā)[na]ṃ ga[c]chet sarvasyāḫ prajāyā dī(rgharātram arthāya hitāya) su<note type="reference">(R5)</note>(khāya ||)<note type="footnote">経末の形式について断簡から得る情報として、B1. 170 V3 では "sūtraṃ || "とあり、さらに五字分程のスペースをとって菱形文様（❖）を配している。</note>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
