<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0966">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0248a15"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城迦蘭陀竹園。時有尊者富隣尼住王舍城耆闍崛山中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有眾多外道出家詣尊者富隣尼，共相問訊慰勞已，退坐一面，問尊者富隣尼：<q who="titthiya">
            <p>我聞沙門瞿曇作『斷滅破壞有』教授耶？今問尊者富隣尼，竟為爾不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>富隣尼語諸外道出家：<q who="punniya">
            <p>我不如是知世尊教語，『眾生斷滅壞有，令無所有』者，無有是處！我作如是解：世尊所說有諸眾生，計言有我、我慢、邪慢，世尊為說，令其斷滅。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時諸外道出家聞富隣尼所說，心不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0248n02"/>喜悅，呵責而去！</p>
        <p>爾時尊者富隣尼，諸外道去已，往詣佛所，稽首禮足，退坐一面。以向諸外道出家所說具白世尊：<q who="punniya">
            <p>世尊！我向答諸外道說，得無謗毀世尊耶？為是法說，如佛所說，如法<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0248n03"/>說，隨順法說，得<pb ed="T" n="0248b"/>不為諸論<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0248n04"/>議者所見嫌<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0248n05"/>責耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告富隣尼：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>如汝所說，不謗如來，不失次第。如我記說，如法法說，隨順法說，不為諸論者之所嫌責。所以者何？富隣尼！先諸眾生我慢、邪慢，邪慢所迫、邪慢集、邪慢不無間等，亂如狗腸，如鐵鉤鏁，亦如亂草，往反驅馳，此世他世、他世此世，驅馳往反，不能遠離。富隣尼！一切眾生於諸邪慢無餘永滅者，彼一切眾生長夜安隱快樂。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，富隣尼比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行！</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
