<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>Hosoda 1989a: 194-196</head>
        <p>From Noriaki Hosoda 細田典明: Bonbun Zōagongyō Busshosetsuhon Gedōsōō (1) [Sanskrit fragments from the Parivrājakasaṃyukta of the Saṃyuktāgama (1) 梵文《雑阿含経》仏所說品外道相応(Ⅰ)] In《藤田宏達博士還曆記念論集：インド哲学と仏教》[Indian Philosophy and Buddhism: Essays in honour of Professor Kotatsu Fujita on his sixtieth birthday] 185-206. Kyoto. This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 201.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:lang="sa">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="hos1989a.194"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <note type="reference">「倶迦那経」B1. 157 R 5-159 V 2: Kokanada（AN V, pp. 196-198 (Kokanudo) .）; 『雑含』第九六七経、『別訳』第二〇一経「倶迦那（経においては「倶迦那提」。）」</note>
        <p>§1  ( || bhagavān rājagṛhe viharati veṇuvane kalandakani)vāpe﹙.﹚ athāyuṣmān ānanda(ḥ sa rātryā paścime yāme)<note type="footnote">Vgl. SHT V Kat.-Nr. 1129 B6: sa rātryā paścime yāme. この箇中は中阿含第三三『侍者経』「彼後夜時」（『大正蔵』一巻四七四頁上二）に対応し、同句の表現は Mahāvastu. Ⅱ, p. 133. 7 に知られる。Pischel は yena の前の欠損した文字を (ya?) と読んでおり、入手したコピーからこの文字は半分が欠損しており ṇ. とも読め、確定できない。「後夜」について Mvy では ”paścime yāme” (Nr. 8233) であり、当該箇所について “paścime yāme vyutthāya” と想定することも可能であり、なお検討の余地がある。</note>yena<note type="reference">B1. 158</note>nadī tapodā tenopajagā(ma. upetya nadyās tapodāyās tīre<note type="footnote">tīre......pariṣicya: vgl. SHT Ⅰ Kat.-Nr. 618 b R5 (=MPS 29. 4).</note>cīvarakāny upanikṣipya nadīṃ tapodām abhyavagāhya<note type="footnote">abhyavagāhya......pratyutthāya: vgl. MPS 29. 4.</note>gātrāṇi pariṣicya nadīṃ tapodāṃ pratyutthāya, e)<note type="reference">V 2</note>kacīvaraka asthād gātrāṇy ā[p](avayamānaḥ.)<note type="footnote">SHT V Kat.-Nr. 1332+1476 a R 3 に "(eka)cīvaraka asthād gātrāṇy āp(ū)payamānaḥ"（対応する漢訳は「拭體著衣」。中阿含第二〇四経『羅摩経』、『大正蔵』一巻、七七五頁下一三）とあり、āpūpayamānaḥ という推定が可能であるが、°pū° については、Pischel も (vā?) と読んでいる如く断簡の欠損部分はこの文字の上半部であり、ū を示す形跡がみられない。また、Kat.-Nr. 1332+1476 についても āp(ū)payamānaḥ と読み、ū については不確定である。</note>
        </p>
        <p>§2 (tena khalu samayena kokanadaḥ parivrājako yena nadī tapodā tenopajagāma. aśrauṣīd āyuṣmān ānandaḥ) <note type="reference">V 3</note>kokanadasya parivrājakasya [p](ariṣiñcanaśabdam. śrutvā ca punar āyuṣmatānandenotkāśanaśabdaḥ<note type="footnote">utkāśanaśabdaḥ......āha.: vgl. Divyāvadāna. p. 517. 25-26; SWTF 5. Lfg. s. v. utkāśanaśabda.</note>kṛtaḥ. aśrauṣīt kokanadaḥ parivrājako tasyotkāśa)<note type="reference">V 4</note>naśabdaṃ﹙.﹚ śrutvā ca punar evam āha﹙.﹚</p>
        <p>§3 [k]<note type="footnote">Pāli, l. c., p. 196. 11-12: 'kvattha āvuso' ti? 'Amhāvuso bhikkhū' ti. 'Katamesaṃ āvuso bhikkhūnan' ti? 'Samaṇānaṃ āvuso Sakyaputtiyānan' ti.</note>(o 'sy āyuṣman. ahaṃ śramaṇo 'smi. katameṣāṃ śramaṇānām. śākyaputrīyānām. pṛccheyam aham āyuṣmāṃ kañcid eva pradeśa)<note type="reference">V 5</note>mi saced avakāśaṃ kuryāḫ praśnasya (vyākaraṇāya. pṛcchāyuṣman. śrutvā te vedayiṣyāmi.)</p>
        <p>§4 (kin nv āyuṣman bhavati<note type="footnote">Vgl. Abhidh-k-bh(P) p. 294. 1-4; Abhidh-k-vy p. 467. 4-7.</note>tathāgataḥ paraṃ maraṇāt. avyākṛtaṃ bhagava)<note type="reference">R 1</note>tā bhavati tathāgataḥ paraṃ maraṇā(t. kin nv āyuṣman na bhavati bhavati ca na bhavati naiva bhavati naiva na bhavati tathāgataḥ paraṃ maraṇāt. avyākṛ)<note type="reference">R 2</note>taṃ bhagavatā na bhavati bhavati c(a na bhavati naiva bhavati naiva na bhavati tathāgataḥ paraṃ maraṇāt.)</p>
        <p>§5 (kin nv āyuṣman bhavati tathāgataḥ paraṃ maraṇā)<note type="reference">R 3</note>d iti pṛṣṭa avyākṛtam iti vadasi﹙.﹚ (na bhavati bhavati ca na bhavati naiva bhavati naiva na bhavati tathāgataḥ paraṃ maraṇād iti pṛṣṭa avyākṛtam iti va)<note type="reference">R 4</note>dasi﹙.﹚ kin nv āyuṣman na jānā(s)[i] (na paśyasi. nāham<note type="footnote">Pāli, l. c., p. 197. 6-7: 'Na kho ahaṃ āvuso na jānāmi na passāmi, jānām' ahaṃ āvuso passāmī' ti.</note>āyuṣman na jānāmi na paśyāmi. jānāmy ahaṃ paśyāmi. kin nv āyuṣman jānāsi paśyasi.)</p>
        <p>§6 ......<note type="reference">R 5</note>d[ṛ]ṣ[ṭ]ir d[ṛ]ṣṭisthānaṃ dṛṣṭisthā(na)......(tam ahaṃ jānāmi tam ahaṃ paśyāmi. evaṃ cāham āyuṣman jānāmy evaṃ paśyāmi. kin nv ahaṃ na jānāmi na pa)<note type="reference">B1. 159</note>śyāmi﹙.﹚</p>
        <p>§7 ko<note type="footnote">Vgl. SHT Ⅱ Kat.-Nr. 163 b R 1. 中阿含第一〇経『七車経』（『大正蔵』一巻四三一頁中二四以下）参照。</note>nāmāyuṣmaṃ﹙.﹚ āna(nda iti. āścaryaṃ yāvan mahācāryasya śrāvakena sārdham antarākathāsamudāhāraḥ. saced<note type="footnote">Pāli, l. c., p. 198. 10-13: Sace hi mayaṃ sañjāneyyāma: āyusmā Ānando ti, ettakam pi no na ppaṭibhāseyya.</note>ahaṃ sañjānīyām āyuṣmān ānanda iti)<note type="reference">V 2</note>etāvat pratibhāsya na<note type="footnote">pratibhāsya は正しくは pratibhāṣya であるが、梵文の意味が不明確なため、今はピシェルの読みに従う。前掲の小断片では “(pra)tibhāsyataḥ sādhu” (SHT Ⅱ a. a. O. R 6) とあり、対応する漢訳の前後は、「若我知尊者舍梨子者。不能答一句。況復爾所深論。善哉善哉」（同、中二九ー下二）。</note>haṃta [bh]......(evam uktvā prakrāntaḥ. || )</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
