<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 203. It is found in the 阿毘達磨大毘婆沙論 Abhidharma at T.27.1545.0509.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T27.1545.0509b17">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t27.1545.0509b17"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>謂契經說。長爪梵志。來詣佛所而白佛言。喬答摩。當知我一切不忍。乃至廣說。<seg type="not-parallel">契經雖作是說。而不說此於五見何見攝。見何諦斷此見。經是此論所依根本。彼未說者今應說之。故作斯論。
                    問何故名為長爪梵志。答由彼梵志身爪俱長。而且說為長爪梵志。問彼復何緣留此長爪。答彼貪習業無容<anchor type="variant" n="fnT27p0509n03"/>剪故。有作是說。彼恒山居爪髮雖長無人<anchor type="variant" n="fnT27p0509n03"/>剪剃。復有說者。彼在家時樂習絃管。後雖出家猶愛長爪故不剪之。有餘師說。彼在外道法中出家。外道法中有留爪者。故說彼為長爪梵志。此中以二事推求見趣。一以自性。二以對治。如文<pb ed="T" n="0509c"/>應知。問此惡見趣等起云何。答尊者舍利子。及大目乾連。投佛出家是此等起。謂長爪梵志。是舍利子舅。曾教尊者外道書論。聞舍利子與大目連歸佛出家。深心憂悔作如是念。智境無窮設解深遠終有迴義。彼喬答摩多聞智慧雖定應勝舍利子等。而必應有勝。喬答摩定復有餘能勝彼者。如是展轉智境無窮。故我不應不設方便。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>作是念已來詣佛所而白佛言。喬答摩。當知我一切不忍。世尊告曰。汝為忍此所起見不。時彼梵志作是思惟。若答言。忍便違所立。若言不忍便無所宗。若無所宗則非論道。思已愧恥默然而住。復次長爪梵志是斷見者。彼觀一切後當必斷。故佛告言。汝所起見亦當斷不。復次長爪梵志是猶豫者。彼觀一切皆可猶豫。故佛告言。汝於自見亦猶豫不。然彼梵志有占相智。自知所立必當墮負故。彼梵志默然而住。世尊告曰。無量有情同汝所見汝亦同彼。謂諸世間依三種見。一有一類。起如是見。立如是論。我一切忍。二有一類。起如是見。立如是論。我一切不忍。三有一類。起如是見。立如是論。我一分忍一分不忍。此中若言一切我皆忍者。彼依此見生愛貪著。若言一切我皆不忍者。彼依此見不生愛貪著。若言我一分忍一分不忍者。彼依此見一分生愛貪著。一分不生愛貪著。<seg type="not-parallel">問一切見趣無不皆能生愛貪著。世尊何故說依彼見有不生者。答應知彼經有別意趣。謂常見者執有<pb ed="T" n="0510a"/>後世。於能引發後有業思生愛貪著。若斷見者執無後世。於能引發後有業思不愛貪著。是彼契經所說意趣。然諸見趣無不皆能生愛貪著。謂斷見者信有現在入胎為初命終為後。撥無他世。於此見中生愛貪著。與常見者保執無異。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>如契經說。佛告梵志。若有沙門婆羅門等。捨惡見趣而不取者。當知此類少中復少。<seg type="not-parallel">問此類云何少中復少。答世間有情性愚鈍者如大地<anchor type="variant" n="fnT27p0510n01"/>土。性聰慧者如爪上土。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT27p0510n02"/>性聰慧中。邪見者多正見者少。喻如前說。是故名為少中復少。問如見蘊說斷常見者展轉相違。云何此中說有一類起如是見。我一分忍一分不忍而不相違。答此中說。一補特伽羅。若執色蘊為常。彼執四蘊為斷。若執四蘊為常。彼執色蘊為斷。故此二見非互相違。見蘊說二補特伽羅。一執色常。一執色斷乃至執識亦有二種。故彼二見展轉相違。彼經復說。</seg>世尊說此見趣法時。長爪梵志遠塵離垢。於諸法中生淨法眼。時舍利子受<pb ed="T" n="0510b"/>具足戒已經半月。隨觀此法得阿羅漢。<seg type="not-parallel">問時舍利子隨觀何法。尊者世友作如是說。尊者舍利子。即隨觀世尊為彼梵志說見趣法。成阿羅漢。復有說者。尊者舍利子。即隨觀梵志得預流果道所觀法。成阿羅漢。有作是說。尊者舍利子。即隨觀梵志得預流果能證學法。成阿羅漢。大德說曰。彼舍利子。隨觀緣起有十二支差別性法。成阿羅漢。是名舍利子所隨觀法。</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
