<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 203. It is found in the 大智度論 Abhidharma at T.25.1509.0061.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T25.1509.0061b18">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t25.1509.0061b18"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">復次欲令長<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n45"/>爪梵志等大論議師。於佛法中生信故。說是摩訶般若波羅蜜經。</seg>有梵志<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n46"/>號名長<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n45"/>爪。<seg type="not-parallel">更有名先尼婆蹉衢多羅。更有名薩遮<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n47"/>迦摩揵提等。是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n48"/>等閻浮提大論議師輩</seg>言。一切論可破。一切語可壞。一切執可轉。故無有實法可信可恭敬者。<seg type="not-parallel">如舍利弗本末經中說。舍利弗舅摩訶俱絺羅。與姊舍利論議不如。俱絺羅思惟念言。非姊力也。必懷智人寄言母口。未生乃爾。及生長大當如之何。思<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n49"/>惟已生憍慢心。為廣論議故出家作梵志。入南天竺國始讀經書。諸人問言。汝志何求。學習何<pb ed="T" n="0060c"/>經。長<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n45"/>爪答<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n50"/>言。十八種大經盡欲讀之。諸人語言。盡汝壽命猶不能知一。何況能盡。長爪自念。昔作憍慢為姊所勝。今此諸人復見輕辱。為<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n51"/>是二事故。自作誓言我不剪爪。要讀十八種經<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n52"/>書盡。人見爪長因號<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n53"/>為長爪梵志。是人以種種經書智慧力。種種譏刺是法是非法是應是不應是實是不實是有是無。破他論議。譬如大力狂象<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n54"/>搪<g>[打-丁+突]</g>蹴踏無能制者。如是長爪梵志以論議力。摧伏諸論師已。還至摩伽陀國王舍城那羅聚落。至本生處問人言。我姊生子今在何處。有人語言。汝姊子者適生八歲。讀一切經書盡。至年十六論議勝一切人。有釋種道人姓<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n55"/>瞿曇。與作弟子。長爪聞之即起憍慢。生不信心而作是言。如我姊子聰明如是。彼以何術誘誑剃頭作弟子。</seg>說是語已直向佛所。爾時舍利弗初受戒半月。佛邊侍立以扇扇佛。長爪梵志見佛問訊訖。<seg type="not-parallel">一面坐作是念。一切論可破一切語可壞。一切執可轉。是中何者是諸法實相。何者是第一義。何者性。何者相。不顛倒。如是思惟。譬如大海水<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n56"/>中欲盡其<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n57"/>涯底。求之<pb ed="T" n="0061a"/>既久不得一法實可以入心者。彼以何論議道。而得我姊子。作是思惟已<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n01"/>
          </seg>而語佛言。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n55"/>瞿曇。我一切法不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n02"/>受。佛問長爪。汝一切法不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n02"/>受。是見<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n02"/>受不。佛<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n03"/>所質義。汝已飲邪見毒。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n04"/>今出是毒氣。言一切法不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n02"/>受。是<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n05"/>見汝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n02"/>受不。爾時長爪梵志如好馬見鞭影<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n06"/>即覺便著正道。長爪梵志亦如是。得佛語鞭影入心。即棄捐貢高慚愧低頭。如是思惟。佛置我著<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n07"/>二處負門中。若我說是見我<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n02"/>受。是負處門<g>[色-巴+鹿]</g>。故<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n08"/>多人知。云何自言一切法不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n02"/>受。今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n09"/>受是見。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n10"/>此是現前妄語。是<g>[色-巴+鹿]</g>負處門<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n08"/>多人所知。第二負處門細。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n11"/>我<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n12"/>欲受之。以<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n13"/>不多人知故。作是念已。答佛言。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0061n55"/>瞿曇。一切法不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n14"/>受。是見亦不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n14"/>受。佛語梵志。汝不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n14"/>受一切法。是見亦不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n14"/>受。則無所<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n15"/>受。與眾人無異。何用<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n16"/>自高而生憍慢如是。長爪梵志不能得答。自知墮負處。即於佛一切智中起恭敬生信心。自思惟。我墮負處。<seg type="not-parallel">世尊不<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n17"/>彰我負。不言是非。不以為意。佛心柔<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n18"/>濡。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n19"/>第一清<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n20"/>淨。一切語論<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n21"/>處滅。得<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n22"/>大甚深法。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n23"/>是可恭敬處。心淨第<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n24"/>一。佛說法斷其邪見故。</seg>即於坐處得遠塵離垢。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n25"/>諸法中得法眼淨。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n26"/>時舍利弗<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n27"/>聞是語得阿羅漢。是長爪梵<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n28"/>志出家作沙門。得大力阿羅漢。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n29"/>
          <seg type="not-parallel">若長爪梵志。不聞般若波羅蜜氣分離四句第一義相應法。小信尚不得。何況得出家道果。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n30"/>佛欲導<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n31"/>引如是等大論議師利根人故。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT25p0062n32"/>說是般若波羅蜜經。</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
