<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0973">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0251b20"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住拘睒彌國瞿師羅園，尊者阿難亦住於彼。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有外道出家名曰<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0251n07"/>栴陀，詣尊者阿難所，與尊者阿難共相問訊慰勞已，退坐一面，問尊者阿難言：<q who="channa">
            <p>何故於沙門瞿曇所出家修梵行？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>阿難答言：<q who="anado">
            <p>為斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡故，於彼出家修梵行。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0251n07"/>栴陀復問：<q who="channa">
            <p>彼能說斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>阿難答言：<q who="anado">
            <p>我亦能說斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0251n07"/>栴陀復問：<q who="channa">
            <p>汝見貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡有何過患，說斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>阿難答言：<q who="anado">
            <p>染著貪<pb ed="T" n="0251c"/>欲映障心故，或自害，或復害他，或復俱害，現法得罪、後世得罪、現法後世二俱得罪，彼心常懷憂、苦受覺。若瞋恚映障、愚癡映障，自害、害他、自他俱害，乃至常懷憂、苦受覺。又復，貪欲為盲、為無目、為無智、為慧力羸、為障<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0250n06"/>閡，非明、非等覺，不轉向涅槃。瞋恚、愚癡亦復如是。我見貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡有如是過患，故說斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0251n07"/>栴陀復問：<q who="channa">
            <p>汝見斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡有何福利，而說斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>阿難答言：<q who="anado">
            <p>斷貪欲已，不自害，又不害他，亦不俱害；又復不現法得罪、後世得罪、現法後世得罪，心法常懷喜樂、受覺。瞋恚、愚癡亦復如是。於現法中常離熾然，不待時節，有得餘現法緣自覺知見。有如是功德利益故，說斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0251n08"/>癡。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>栴陀復問：<q who="channa">
            <p>尊者阿難！有道有跡，修習多修習，能斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>阿難答言：<q who="anado">
            <p>有，謂八正道——正見……乃至正定。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0251n07"/>栴陀外道白尊者阿難：<q who="channa">
            <p>此是賢哉之道、賢哉之跡，修習多修習，能斷貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>時<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0251n07"/>栴陀外道聞尊者阿難所說，歡喜隨喜，從坐起而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
