<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0977">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0252c12"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住王舍城迦蘭陀竹園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時尸婆外道出家來詣佛所，與世尊面相問訊慰勞已，退坐一面，白佛言：
                 <q who="moliyasivaka">
            <p>瞿曇！有一沙門婆羅門作如是見、如是說：『若人有所知覺，彼一切本所作因，修諸苦行，令過去業盡，更不造新業，斷於因緣，於未來世無復諸漏。諸漏盡故業盡，業盡故苦盡，苦盡者究竟苦邊。』今瞿曇所說云何？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告尸婆：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0252n19"/>彼沙門婆羅門實爾<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0252n20"/>洛漠說耳，不審不數，愚癡不善不辯。所以者何？或從風起苦，眾生覺知，或從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0252n21"/>痰起，或從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0252n22"/>唌唾起，或等分起，或自害，或他害，或因節氣。彼自害者，或拔髮、或拔鬚，或常立舉手，或蹲地，或臥灰土中，或臥<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0252n23"/>棘刺上，或臥杵上、或板上，或牛屎塗地而臥其<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0252n24"/>上，或臥水中，或日三洗浴，或一足而立，身隨日轉，如是眾苦精勤有行，尸婆！是名自害。他害者，或為他手石、刀、杖等，種種害身，是名他害。尸婆！若<pb ed="T" n="0253a"/>復時節所害，冬則大寒，春則大熱，夏寒暑俱，是名節氣所害。世間真實，非為虛妄。尸婆！世間有此真實，為風所害，乃至節氣所害，彼眾生如實覺知。汝亦自有此患，風<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0252n21"/>痰<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0252n22"/>唌唾，……乃至節氣所害覺，如是如實覺知。尸婆！若彼沙門婆羅門言一切人所知覺者皆是本所造因，捨世間真實事而隨自見，作虛妄說。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <q who="gotamo">
            <p>尸婆！有五因五緣生心法憂苦。何等為五？謂因貪欲纏，緣貪欲纏，生心法憂苦；因瞋恚、睡眠、掉悔、疑<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n01"/>纏，緣瞋恚、睡眠、掉悔、疑纏，生彼心法憂苦，尸婆！是名五因<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n02"/>五緣生心法憂苦。尸婆！有五因五緣不生心法憂苦。何等為五？謂因貪欲纏，緣貪欲纏，生彼心<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n03"/>法憂苦者，離彼貪欲纏，不起心法憂<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n04"/>苦；是名五因五緣不起心法憂苦，現法得離熾然，不待時節，通達現見，緣自覺知。尸婆！復有現法離熾然，不待時節，通達現見，緣自覺知，謂八正道——正見……乃至正定。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>說是法時尸婆外道出家<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n05"/>遠塵離垢，得法眼淨。時尸婆外道出家見法、得法、知法、入法，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n06"/>離諸狐疑，不由於他，入正法、律，得無所畏，即從坐起，整衣服，合掌白佛：<q who="moliyasivaka">
            <p>世尊！我今<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n07"/>可得於正法、律出家、受具足，得比丘分耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告尸婆：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝今得出家。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>如上說，……乃至心善解脫，得阿羅漢。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
