<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0978">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0253a26"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住那羅聚落好衣庵羅園中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時那羅聚落有商主外道出家，百二十歲，年耆根熟，為那羅聚落諸沙門、婆羅門、長者、居士尊重供養，如阿羅漢。</p>
        <p>彼商主<pb ed="T" n="0253b"/>外道出家先有宗親一人，命終生天，於彼天上見商主外道出家已，作是念：</p>
        <q who="商主外道出家宗親">
          <p>我欲往教彼商主外道出家詣世尊所，修行梵行，恐其不隨我<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n09"/>語，我今當往彼，以意論令問。</p>
        </q>
        <p>即下那羅聚落，詣彼商主外道出家所，說偈而問：</p>
        <q who="商主外道出家宗親">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0978a">
            <l>云何惡知識<caesura/>現善知識相</l>
            <l>云何善知識<caesura/>如己同一體</l>
            <l>何故求於斷<caesura/>云何離熾然</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>
          <q who="商主外道出家宗親">
            <p>若汝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n10"/>仙人持此意論而問於彼，有能分<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n11"/>明解說其義而答汝<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n12"/>者，便可從彼出家，修行梵行。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時商主外道出家受天所<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n13"/>問，持詣富蘭那迦葉所，以此意論偈問富蘭那迦葉。彼富蘭那迦葉尚自不解，況復能答？彼時商主外道出家復至末迦梨瞿舍利子所、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n14"/>刪闍耶毘羅坻子所、阿<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n15"/>耆多枳舍欽婆羅所、迦羅拘陀迦<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0251n07"/>栴延所、尼乾陀若提子所，皆以此意論偈而問，悉不能答。</p>
        <p>時商主外道出家作是念：<q who="商主外道出家">
            <p>我以此意論問諸出家師，悉不能答，我今復欲求出家；為我今自有財寶，不如還家，服習五欲。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>復作是念：<q who="商主外道出家">
            <p>我今可往詣沙門瞿曇，然彼耆舊、諸師、沙門、婆羅門、富蘭那迦葉等，悉不能答，而沙門瞿曇年少出家，詎復能了？然我聞先宿所說「莫輕新學年少出家」，或有沙門年少出家，有大德力，今且當詣沙門瞿曇。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>詣已，以彼意論心念而問，如偈所說。</p>
        <p>爾時世尊知彼商主心之所念，即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0978b">
            <l>云何惡知識<caesura/>現善友相者</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0253c"/>內心實恥厭<caesura/>口說我同心</l>
            <l>造事不樂同<caesura/>故知非善友</l>
            <l>口說恩愛語<caesura/>心不實相應</l>
            <l>所作而不同<caesura/>慧者應覺知</l>
            <l>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n16"/>是名惡知識<caesura/>現善知識相</l>
            <l>與己同一體<caesura/>云何善知識</l>
            <l>與己同體者<caesura/>非彼善知識</l>
            <l>放逸而不制<caesura/>沮壞懷疑惑</l>
            <l>伺求其端緒<caesura/>安於善知識</l>
            <l>如子臥父懷<caesura/>不為傍人<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n17"/>聞</l>
            <l>當知善知識<caesura/>何故求於斷</l>
            <l>生歡喜之處<caesura/>清涼稱讚歎</l>
            <l>修習福利果<caesura/>清涼永息滅</l>
            <l>是故求於斷<caesura/>云何離熾然</l>
            <l>寂靜止息味<caesura/>知彼遠離味</l>
            <l>遠離熾然惡<caesura/>飲以法喜味</l>
            <l>寂滅離欲火<caesura/>是名離熾然</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時商主外道出家作是念：<q who="商主外道出家">
            <p>沙門瞿曇知我心念。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>而白佛言：<q who="商主外道出家">
            <p>我今得入沙門瞿曇正法、律中修行梵行，出家、受具足，成比丘分不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告商主外道出家：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝今可得於<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n18"/>正法、律修行梵行，出家、受具足，成比丘分。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>如是出家已，思惟……乃至心善解脫，得阿羅漢。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
