<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0979">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0253c24"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：
                 一時佛住<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n20"/>俱夷那竭國力士生處堅固雙<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0253n21"/>樹林中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊涅槃時至，告尊者阿難：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝為世尊於雙樹間敷繩床，北首，如來今日中夜於無餘涅槃而般涅槃。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時尊者阿難奉教，於雙樹間敷繩床，北首，訖，來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退住一面，白<pb ed="T" n="0254a"/>佛言：<q who="anado">
            <p>世尊！<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n01"/>已於雙樹間敷繩床，北首。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊詣雙樹間，於繩床上北首右脅而臥，足足相累，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n02"/>繫念明想，正念正智。</p>
        <p>時俱夷那竭國有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n03"/>須跋陀羅外道出家，百二十歲，年耆根熟，為俱夷那竭國人恭敬供養，如阿羅漢。彼須跋陀羅出家聞世尊今日中夜當於無餘涅槃而般涅槃：<q who="須跋陀羅外道出家">
            <p>然我有所疑，希望而住，沙門瞿曇有力，能<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n04"/>開覺我，我今當詣沙門瞿曇，問其所疑。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>即出俱夷那竭，詣世尊所。</p>
        <p>爾時尊者阿難於園門外經行，時須跋陀羅語阿難言：<q who="須跋陀羅外道出家">
            <p>我聞沙門瞿曇今日中夜於無餘涅槃而般涅槃，我有所疑，希望而住，沙門瞿曇有力，能開覺我。若阿難不憚勞者，為我往白瞿曇，少有閑暇，答我所問？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>阿難答言：<q who="anado">
            <p>莫逼世尊！世尊疲極。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          如是須跋陀羅再三請尊者阿難，尊者阿難亦再三不許。
                           須跋陀羅言：
        </p>
        <q who="須跋陀羅外道出家">
          <p>我聞古昔出家耆年大師所說，久久乃有如來、應、等正覺出於世間，如<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n05"/>優曇缽花。而今如來中夜當於無餘涅槃界而般涅槃，我今於法疑，信心而<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n06"/>住，沙門瞿曇有力，能開覺我，若阿難不憚勞者，為我白沙門瞿曇。</p>
        </q>
        <p>阿難復答言：<q who="anado">
            <p>須跋陀羅！莫逼世尊！世尊今日疲極。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊以天耳聞阿難與須跋陀羅共語來往，而告尊者阿難：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>莫遮外道出家須跋陀羅！令入問其所疑。所以者何？此是最後與外道出家論<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n07"/>議，此是最後得證聲聞。善來比丘，所謂須跋陀羅。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時須跋陀<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n08"/>羅世尊為開善根，歡喜增上，詣世尊所，與世尊面相問訊慰勞已，退坐一面，白佛言：<q who="須跋陀羅外道出家">
            <p>瞿曇！凡世間入處，謂富蘭那迦葉等六師，各作如是宗：『此是沙門，此是沙門！』云何，瞿曇！為實各各有是宗不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊即為說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0979a">
            <l>始年二十九<caesura/>出家修善道</l>
            <l>
              <choice>
                <sic>成</sic>
                <corr resp="CBETA">成</corr>
                <corr resp="T100">至</corr>
              </choice>道至於今<caesura/>經五十餘年</l>
            <l>三昧明行具<caesura/>常修於淨戒</l>
            <l>離斯少道分<caesura/>此外無沙門</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>佛告須跋陀羅：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>於正法、律不得八正道者，亦不得初沙門，亦不得第二、第三、第四沙門。須跋陀羅！於此法、律得八正道者，得初沙門，得第二、第三、第四沙門。除此已，於外道無沙門，斯則異道之師，空沙門、婆羅門耳。是故，我今於眾中作師子吼。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>說是法時須跋陀羅外道出家遠塵離垢，得法眼淨。爾時須跋陀羅見法、得法、知法、入法，度諸狐疑，不由他信，不由他度，於正法、律得無所畏，從座起，整衣服，右膝著地，白尊者阿難：<q who="須跋陀羅外道出家">
            <p>汝得善利，汝得大師，為大師弟子，為大<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0254n09"/>師雨，雨灌其頂。我今若得於正法、律出家、受具足，得比丘分者，亦當得斯善利！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時尊者阿難白佛言：<q who="anado">
            <p>世尊！是須跋陀羅外道出家今求於正法、律出家、受具足，得比丘分。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊告須跋陀羅：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>此比丘來修行梵行。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>彼尊者須跋陀羅即於爾時出家，即是受具足，成比丘分。如是思惟……乃至心善解脫，得阿羅漢。</p>
        <p>時尊者須跋陀羅得阿羅漢，解脫樂覺知己，作是念：<q who="須跋陀羅外道出家">
            <p>我不忍見佛般涅槃，我當先般涅槃。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時尊者須跋陀羅先般涅槃已，然後世尊般涅槃。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
