<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 228. It is found in the 中阿含經．大品．請請經 Sutra at T.01.0063.0861.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0026.0610a10">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0026.0610a10"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>我聞如是。一時。佛遊王舍城。在竹林加蘭哆園。與大比丘眾五百人俱。共受夏坐。</p>
        <p>爾時。世尊月十五日。說從解脫相請請時。在比丘眾前敷座而坐。告諸比丘我是梵志。而得滅訖。無上醫王。我今受身。最是後邊。我是梵志。得滅訖後。無上醫王。我今受身。最是後邊。謂汝等輩是我真子。從口而生。法法所化。謂汝等輩是我真子。從口而生。法法所化。汝當教化。轉相教訶。</p>
        <p>爾時。尊者舍梨子亦在眾中。於是。尊者舍梨子即從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n07"/>坐起。偏袒著衣。叉手向佛。白曰。世尊。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n08"/>嚮之所說。我是梵志。而得滅訖。無上醫王。我今受身。最是後邊。我是梵志。得滅訖後。無上醫王。我今受身。最是後邊。謂汝等輩是我真子。從口而生。法法所化。謂汝等輩是我真子。從口而生。法法所化。汝當教化。轉相教訶。世尊諸不調者令得調御。諸不息者令得止息。諸不度者而令得度。諸不解脫者令得解脫。諸不滅訖者令得滅訖。未得道者令其得道。不施設梵<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n09"/>行令施設梵行。知道．覺道．識道．<pb ed="T" n="0610b"/>說道。世尊弟子於後得法。受教．受訶．受教．訶已。隨世尊語。即便趣行。得如其意。善知正法。唯然。世尊不嫌我身．口．意行耶。</p>
        <p>彼時。世尊告曰。舍梨子。我不嫌汝身．口．意行。所以者何。舍梨子。汝有聰慧．大慧．速慧．捷慧．利慧．廣慧．深慧．出要慧．明達慧。舍梨子。汝成就實慧。<seg>舍梨子。猶轉輪王而有太子。不越教已。則便受拜父王所傳。而能復傳。如是。舍梨子。我所轉法輪。汝復能轉。</seg>舍梨子。是故我不嫌汝身．口．意行。</p>
        <p>尊者舍梨子復再叉手向佛。白曰。唯然。世尊不嫌我身．口．意行。世尊不嫌此五百比丘身．口．意行耶。</p>
        <p>世尊告曰。舍梨子。我亦不嫌此五百比丘身．口．意行。所以者何。舍梨子。此五百比丘盡得無著。諸漏已盡。梵行已立。所作已辦。重擔已捨。有結已盡。而得善義正智正解脫。<seg>唯除一比丘。我亦本已記於現法中得究竟智。生已盡。梵行已立。所作已辦。不更受有。知如真。</seg>舍梨子。是故我不嫌此五百比丘身．口．意行。</p>
        <p>尊者舍梨子復三叉手向佛。白曰。唯然。世尊不嫌我身．口．意行。亦不嫌此五百比丘身．口．意行。世尊。此五百比丘幾比丘得三明達。幾比丘得俱解脫。幾比丘得慧解脫耶。</p>
        <p>世尊告曰。舍梨子。此五百比丘。九十比丘得三明達。<seg>九十</seg>比丘得俱解脫。餘比丘得慧解脫。舍梨子。此眾無枝無葉。亦無節<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n10"/>戾。清淨真實。得正住立。</p>
        <p>爾時。尊者<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n11"/>傍耆舍亦在眾中。於是。尊者傍耆舍即從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n07"/>坐起。偏袒著衣。叉手向佛。白曰。唯然。世<pb ed="T" n="0610c"/>尊加我威力。唯願善逝加我威力。令我在佛及比丘眾前。以如義相應而作讚頌。</p>
        <p>世尊告曰。傍耆舍。隨汝所欲。</p>
        <p>於是。尊者傍耆舍在佛及比丘眾前。以如義相應而讚頌曰。</p>
        <lg met="7">
          <l>今十五請日<caesura/>集坐五百眾</l>
          <l>斷除諸結縛<caesura/>無礙有盡仙</l>
          <l>清淨光明照<caesura/>解脫一切有</l>
          <l>生老病死盡<caesura/>漏滅所作辦</l>
          <l>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n12"/>調悔及疑結<caesura/>慢<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n13"/>有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0610n14"/>漏已盡</l>
          <l>拔斷愛結刺<caesura/>上醫無復有</l>
          <l>勇猛如師子<caesura/>一切恐畏除</l>
          <l>已度於生死<caesura/>諸漏已滅訖</l>
          <l>猶如轉輪王<caesura/>群臣所圍繞</l>
          <l>悉領一切地<caesura/>乃至於大海</l>
          <l>如是勇猛伏<caesura/>無上商人主</l>
          <l>弟子樂恭敬<caesura/>三達離死怖</l>
          <l>一切是佛子<caesura/>永除枝葉節</l>
          <l>轉無上法輪<caesura/>稽首第一尊</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">佛說如是。彼諸比丘聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</seg>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
