<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 228. It is found in the 佛說受新歲經 Sutra at T.01.0061.0858.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0061.0858a14">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0061.0858a14"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>聞如是。一時佛在<seg type="not-parallel">舍衛國東苑鹿母園中。</seg>與大比丘眾五百人俱。是時世尊。七月十五日。於露地敷坐。比丘僧前後圍遶。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>佛告阿難曰。汝今於露地速擊揵槌。所以然者。今七月十五日是受新歲之日。是時尊者阿難。右膝著地長跪叉手。便說此偈。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>智慧無染著<caesura/>何等名受歲</l>
        </lg>
        <p>爾時世尊復說此偈報阿難曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>受歲三業淨<caesura/>身口意所作</l>
          <l>兩兩比丘對<caesura/>自陳所作短</l>
          <l>還自稱名字<caesura/>今日眾受歲</l>
          <l>我亦淨意受<caesura/>唯願原其過</l>
        </lg>
        <p>爾時阿難復以此偈問其儀曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>過去恒沙佛<caesura/>辟支及聲聞</l>
          <l>盡是諸佛法<caesura/>獨是釋迦文</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          <pb ed="T" n="0858b"/>爾時世尊復更以偈報阿難曰。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>恒沙過去佛<caesura/>弟子清淨心</l>
          <l>皆是諸佛法<caesura/>非今釋迦文</l>
          <l>辟支無此法<caesura/>無歲無弟子</l>
          <l>獨逝無伴侶<caesura/>不與他說法</l>
          <l>當來佛世尊<caesura/>恒沙不可計</l>
          <l>彼亦受此歲<caesura/>如今瞿曇法</l>
        </lg>
        <p>是時尊者阿難聞此語已。歡喜踊躍不能自勝。即昇講堂手執揵槌。並作是說。我今擊此如來信<g>[壴*皮]</g>。諸有如來弟子眾者盡當普集。爾時阿難復說此偈。</p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>降伏魔力怨<caesura/>除結無有餘</l>
          <l>露地擊揵槌<caesura/>比丘聞當集</l>
          <l>諸欲聞法人<caesura/>度流生死海</l>
          <l>聞此妙響音<caesura/>盡當速集此</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">爾時尊者阿難已擊揵槌。至世尊所頭面禮足。在一面住白世尊言。今正是時。唯願世尊。何所[束*力]使。是時世尊告阿難曰。汝隨次第坐。如來自當知時。是時世尊坐于草坐。告諸比丘。汝等盡當坐于草坐。諸比丘對曰。如是世尊。時諸比丘各坐草坐。</seg>是時世尊默然觀諸比丘已。便<g>[束*力]</g>諸比丘。我今欲受新歲。我無過咎於眾人乎。又不犯身口意耶。如來說此語已。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">諸比丘默然不對。如來是時復三告諸比丘。我今欲受新歲。然我無過於眾人乎。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>是時尊者舍利弗。即從坐起長跪叉手。白世尊言。諸比丘眾觀察如來無身口意過。所以然者。世尊今日不度者度。不脫者脫。不涅槃者令得涅槃。無救護者為作救護。為盲者作眼目。<pb ed="T" n="0858c"/>為病者作醫王。三界獨尊無能及者。最尊最上。未起道意者令發道意。眾人未悟。尊令悟之。未聞法者使令聞之。為迷者作徑路導以正法。以此事緣如來無咎於眾人也。亦無身口意過。是時舍利弗白世尊言。我今亦向如來自陳。然無過咎於如來及比丘僧乎。世尊告曰。汝今舍利弗。都無身口意所作非行。所以然者。汝今智慧無能及者。種種智慧。無量智慧。無邊之智。無與等智。疾智捷智。甚深之智。平等之智。少欲知足樂 之處。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">多諸方便。念不錯亂摠持三昧。根原具足戒。成就三昧。成就智慧。成就解脫。成就解脫知見。成就勇悍。能忍所說。知惡之為非法。心性庠序。不行卒暴。猶如轉輪聖王最大太子。當紹王位。轉於寶輪。舍利弗亦復如是。轉於無上清淨法輪。諸天世人及龍鬼神魔若魔天。本所不轉。汝今所說常如法議。未曾違理。</seg>
        </p>
        <p>是時舍利弗白佛言。此五百比丘盡當受歲。此五百人盡無過咎於如來乎。世尊告曰。我亦不責此五百比丘身口意行。所以然者。此舍利弗大眾之中。極為清淨無諸瑕穢。</p>
        <p>
          <seg type="not-parallel">今此眾中最小下座。得須陀洹道。必當上及不退轉法。</seg>
            以是之故我不怨責此眾。
                                爾時朋耆奢在此眾中。即從坐起前至世尊所。頭面禮足白世尊言。我今堪任欲有所論。世尊告曰。欲有所說今正是時。朋耆奢即於佛前。歎佛及比丘僧。而說此偈。
          </p>
        <lg met="5">
          <l>十五清淨日<caesura/>五百比丘集</l>
          <l>諸縛結悉解<caesura/>無愛更不生</l>
          <l>
            <pb ed="T" n="0859a"/>轉輪大聖王<caesura/>群臣所圍繞</l>
          <l>普遍諸世界<caesura/>天上及世間</l>
          <l>大將人眾導<caesura/>為人作導師</l>
          <l>弟子樂侍從<caesura/>三達六通徹</l>
          <l>皆是真佛子<caesura/>無有塵垢者</l>
          <l>能斷欲愛刺<caesura/>今日自歸命</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
      <div type="not-parallel">
        <p>爾時世尊可朋耆奢所說。是時朋耆奢作是念。如來今日可我所說。歡喜踊躍不能自勝。即從坐起禮佛<g>[去*ㄗ]</g>退還就本位。爾時世尊告諸比丘。我聲聞中第一造偈弟子。所謂朋耆奢比丘是。所說無疑難。亦是朋耆奢比丘是也。爾時諸比丘聞佛所說。歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
