<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <p>This is part of the text-cluster of BZA (T.100) sutra 228. It is found in the 佛說解夏經 Sutra at T.01.0063.0861.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="T01.0063.0861b14">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="t01.0063.0861b14"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>如是我聞。一時佛在王舍城迦蘭陀竹林精舍。與五百苾芻眾俱。皆是阿羅漢。諸漏已盡所作已辦。除諸重擔逮得己利。盡諸有結心善解脫。唯一苾芻現居學位。世尊已為授記。見法得法當證滿果。</p>
        <p>爾時世尊安居既滿。當解夏時。於十五日與苾芻眾敷座而坐。會眾坐已。是時佛告苾芻眾言。我今已得梵行寂靜。是最後身。以無上樂斷除諸病。我之弟子了知諸法皆已通達。是故我今說解夏法。諸苾芻眾。我於夏中所有身口意業。汝等可忍。</p>
        <p>是時尊者舍利弗聞佛語已。從座而起偏袒右肩。右膝著地合掌向佛。而白佛言。世尊。如佛所說。我今已得梵行寂靜。乃至身口意業可忍者。我等知。佛身口意業無諸過失。我等苾芻今無可忍。於意云何。我佛世尊難調者<pb ed="T" n="0861c"/>能調。無止息者善為止息。無安隱者而善安慰。未寂靜者令得寂靜。如來善了正道。善說正道。開示正道。乃至我等樂聲聞菩提者。佛為善說。令聲聞等如理修行而證聖果。是故我等於佛世尊身口意法而無可忍。</p>
        <p>爾時尊者舍利弗白佛言。世尊。我今對佛身口意業所有不善求佛可忍。佛告舍利弗。汝今所有身口意業我當忍可。於意云何。汝舍利弗。具戒多聞少欲知足。斷諸煩惱。發大精進。安住正念。具等引<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。聞<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。捷<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。利<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。出離<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。了達<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。廣大清淨<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。甚深<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。無等<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧。具大<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧寶。未見者令見。未調伏者。令得調伏。未聞法者而為說法。具瞋恚者而令歡喜能為四眾說法無倦。譬如金輪王子。而受灌頂繼紹王位依法而治。汝舍利弗。亦復如是。為我之子。受灌頂法紹法王位。如我所轉無上法輪。如我漏盡證得解脫。是故汝舍利弗。所有三業我今忍可。時舍利弗聞佛忍可。投誠禮謝。復白佛言。世尊。如佛為我忍可三業。於此會中五百苾芻。身口意業所有不善。唯願世尊。亦如是忍。佛告舍利弗。五百苾芻所有三業我亦可忍。於意云何。此五百苾芻皆是阿羅漢。諸漏已盡所作已辦。除諸重擔逮得己利。盡諸有結心善解脫。唯一苾芻現居學位。而此苾芻我已授記。見法得法當證滿果。舍利弗。是故我於五百苾芻所有三業皆悉可忍。</p>
        <p>爾時舍利弗重白佛言。世尊。我與五百苾芻眾等。所有三業佛已可忍。我今有疑。當復啟<pb ed="T" n="0862a"/>請。願佛世尊。為我分別世尊。此五百苾芻中幾苾芻得三明法。復幾苾芻得俱解脫。復幾苾芻得<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧解脫。</p>
        <p>佛告舍利弗。此五百苾芻中。九十苾芻得三明法。九十苾芻得俱解脫。餘者苾芻得<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0861n08"/>慧解脫。舍利弗。如是苾芻盡諸煩惱皆住真實。爾時會中有一尊者。名<g>[口*縛]</g>儗舍。作如是念。我今對佛苾芻眾前。以解夏伽陀伸於讚歎。是時尊者<g>[口*縛]</g>儗舍。作是念已。從座而起。偏袒右肩右膝著地。合掌恭肅。說伽陀曰。</p>
        <lg met="7">
          <l>解夏十五日<caesura/>清淨行律儀</l>
          <l>五百苾芻眾<caesura/>悉斷煩惱縛</l>
          <l>皆盡諸漏法<caesura/>而證聖果位</l>
          <l>內寂外善調<caesura/>解脫而離有</l>
          <l>盡生死邊際<caesura/>所作皆已辦</l>
          <l>無明我慢結<caesura/>斷盡無有餘</l>
          <l>我佛最上尊<caesura/>斷諸邪念法</l>
          <l>及斷有漏法<caesura/>善除愛病苦</l>
          <l>愛滅不復生<caesura/>離取大師子</l>
          <l>盡諸有怖畏<caesura/>唯我佛世尊</l>
          <l>譬如金輪王<caesura/>千子常圍繞</l>
          <l>善治四天下<caesura/>調伏四海邊</l>
          <l>又如戰得勝<caesura/>為最上調御</l>
          <l>聲聞得三明<caesura/>離死法亦然</l>
          <l>佛子皆如是<caesura/>證滅不復生</l>
          <l>我今禮法<anchor type="variant" n="fnT01p0862n01"/>王<caesura/>無上大日尊</l>
        </lg>
        <p>是時<g>[口*縛]</g>
            儗舍苾芻。說此伽陀已復還本座。
                                爾時尊者舍利弗與諸苾芻。聞佛宣說解夏之法。心生快利踊躍
          <choice>
            <sic>歎</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">歡</corr>
          </choice>喜。信受奉行。
                </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
