<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0993">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0259a05"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有諸上座比丘隨佛左右依止而住。所謂：尊者阿若憍陳如、尊者摩訶迦葉、尊者舍利弗、尊者摩訶目揵連、尊者阿那律陀、尊者二十億耳、尊者陀羅驃摩羅子、尊者婆那迦婆娑、尊者耶舍舍羅迦毘訶利、尊者富<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0259n02"/>
            留那、尊者分陀檀尼迦，如此及餘上座比丘隨佛左右依止而住。
                             時尊者婆耆舍住舍衛國東園鹿子母講堂。時尊者婆耆舍作是念：
          </p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <p>今日世尊在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。諸上座比丘隨佛左右依止而住。我今當往至世尊所，各各說偈，歎諸上座比丘。</p>
        </q>
        <p>作是念已，往詣佛所，稽首佛足，退住一面，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0259n03"/>而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0993a">
            <l>上上座比丘<caesura/>已斷諸貪欲</l>
            <l>超過諸世間<caesura/>一切之積聚</l>
            <l>深智少言說<caesura/>勇猛勤方便</l>
            <l>道德淨明顯<caesura/>我今稽首禮</l>
            <l>已伏諸<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0259n04"/>魔怨<caesura/>遠離於群聚</l>
            <l>不為五欲縛<caesura/>常習於空閑</l>
            <l>清虛而寡欲<caesura/>我今稽首禮</l>
            <l>遮羅延勝族<caesura/>禪思不放逸</l>
            <l>內心樂正受<caesura/>清淨離塵穢</l>
            <l>辯慧顯深義<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
            <l>所得神通慧<caesura/>超諸神通力</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0259b"/>六神通眾中<caesura/>自在無所畏</l>
            <l>神通最勝故<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
            <l>於大千世界<caesura/>五道諸趣生</l>
            <l>乃至於梵世<caesura/>人天優劣想</l>
            <l>淨天眼悉見<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
            <l>精勤方便力<caesura/>斷除諸愛集</l>
            <l>壞裂生死網<caesura/>心常樂正法</l>
            <l>離諸悕望想<caesura/>超度於彼岸</l>
            <l>清淨無塵穢<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
            <l>永離諸恐畏<caesura/>無依離財物</l>
            <l>知足度疑惑<caesura/>伏諸魔怨敵</l>
            <l>身念觀清淨<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
            <l>無有諸世間<caesura/>煩惱棘刺林</l>
            <l>結縛使永除<caesura/>三有因緣斷</l>
            <l>精練滅諸垢<caesura/>究竟明顯現</l>
            <l>於林離林去<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
            <l>無舍宅所依<caesura/>幻偽癡恚滅</l>
            <l>調伏諸愛喜<caesura/>出一切見處</l>
            <l>清淨無瑕穢<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
            <l>其心自在轉<caesura/>堅固不傾動</l>
            <l>智慧大德力<caesura/>難伏魔能伏</l>
            <l>斷除無明結<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
            <l>大人離闇冥<caesura/>寂滅牟尼尊</l>
            <l>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0259n05"/>正法離垢過<caesura/>光明自顯照</l>
            <l>照一切世界<caesura/>是故名為佛</l>
            <l>地神虛空天<caesura/>三十三天子</l>
            <l>光明悉映障<caesura/>是故名為佛</l>
            <l>度生死有邊<caesura/>超踰越群眾</l>
            <l>柔弱善調伏<caesura/>正覺第一覺</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0259c"/>斷一切結縛<caesura/>伏一切異道</l>
            <l>降一切魔怨<caesura/>得無上正覺</l>
            <l>離塵滅諸垢<caesura/>是故稽首禮</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>尊者婆耆舍偈讚歎時，諸比丘聞其所說，皆大歡喜。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
