<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0994">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0259c06"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時尊者婆耆舍住舍衛國東園鹿子母講堂，疾病困篤。尊者富隣尼為看病人，供給供養。時尊者婆耆舍語尊者富隣尼言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <p>汝往詣世尊所，持我語白世尊言：<q who="punniya">尊者婆耆舍稽首世尊足，問訊世尊：<q who="vangisa">少病少惱，起居輕利，得自安樂住不？</q>
            </q>復作是言：<q who="punniya">尊者婆耆舍住東園鹿子母講堂，疾病困篤，欲求見世尊，無力方便堪詣世尊。善哉！世尊！願往至東園鹿子母講堂尊者婆耆舍所，哀愍故！</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>時尊者富隣尼即受其語，往詣世尊，稽首佛足，退坐一面，作是言：</p>
        <q who="punniya">
          <p>尊者婆耆舍住東園鹿子母講堂，疾病困篤，願見世尊，無力方便堪能奉見。善哉！世尊！願往東園鹿子母講堂尊者婆耆舍所，為哀愍故！</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊默然而許。時尊者富隣尼知佛許已，即從坐起，禮佛足而去。世尊晡時從禪起，往詣尊者婆耆舍。尊者婆耆舍遙見世尊，憑床欲起。爾時世尊見尊者婆耆舍憑床欲起，語言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>婆耆舍！莫自輕動！</p>
        </q>
        <p>世尊即坐，問尊者婆耆舍：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝所患苦，為平和可堪忍不？身諸苦痛為增？為損？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>（如前焰摩迦修多羅廣說……乃至）<q who="vangisa">
            <p>我所苦患，轉覺其增，不覺其損。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆耆舍：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我今問汝，隨意答<pb ed="T" n="0260a"/>我。汝得心不染、不著、不污、解脫、離諸顛倒不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆耆舍白佛言：<q who="vangisa">
            <p>我心不染、不著、不污、解脫、離諸顛倒。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆耆舍：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝云何得心不染、不著、不污、解脫、離諸顛倒？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆耆舍白<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n01"/>佛：<q who="vangisa">
            <p>我過去眼識於色，心不顧念，於未來色不欣想，於現在色不著。我過去、未來、現在眼識於色，貪欲、愛樂、念──於彼得盡，無欲，滅，沒，息，離，解脫。心解脫已，是故不染、不著、不污，離諸顛倒，正受而住。
                 如是耳、鼻、舌、身、意識，過去於法，心不顧念，未來不欣，現在不著。過去、未來、現在法中、念欲<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n02"/>愛盡，無欲，滅，沒，息，離，解脫。心解脫已，是故不染、不著、不污、解脫，離諸顛倒，正受而住。唯願世尊今日最後饒益於我，聽我說偈！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆耆舍：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>宜知是時。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>尊者婆耆舍起，正身端坐，繫念在前，而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0994a">
            <l>我今住佛前<caesura/>稽首恭敬禮</l>
            <l>於一切諸法<caesura/>悉皆得解脫</l>
            <l>善解諸法相<caesura/>深信樂正法</l>
            <l>世尊等正覺<caesura/>世尊為大師</l>
            <l>世尊降魔怨<caesura/>世尊大牟尼</l>
            <l>滅除一切使<caesura/>自度群生類</l>
            <l>世尊於世間<caesura/>諸法悉覺知</l>
            <l>世間悉無有<caesura/>知法過佛者</l>
            <l>於諸天人中<caesura/>亦無與佛等</l>
            <l>是故我今日<caesura/>稽首大精進</l>
            <l>稽首士之上<caesura/>拔諸愛欲刺</l>
            <l>我今是最後<caesura/>得見於世尊</l>
            <l>稽首日種尊<caesura/>暮當般涅槃</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0260b"/>正<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n03"/>智繫正念<caesura/>於此朽壞身</l>
            <l>餘勢之所起<caesura/>從今夜永滅</l>
            <l>三界不復染<caesura/>入無餘涅槃</l>
            <l>苦受及樂受<caesura/>亦不苦不樂</l>
            <l>從觸因緣生<caesura/>於今悉永斷</l>
            <l>苦受及樂受<caesura/>亦不苦不樂</l>
            <l>從觸因緣生<caesura/>於今悉已知</l>
            <l>若內及與外<caesura/>苦樂等諸受</l>
            <l>於受無所著<caesura/>正智正繫心</l>
            <l>於初中最後<caesura/>諸聚無障<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n04"/>礙</l>
            <l>諸聚既已斷<caesura/>了知<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n05"/>受無餘</l>
            <l>明見真實者<caesura/>說九十一劫</l>
            <l>三劫中不空<caesura/>有大仙人尊</l>
            <l>餘空無洲依<caesura/>唯畏恐怖劫</l>
            <l>當知大仙人<caesura/>乃復出於世</l>
            <l>安慰諸天人<caesura/>開眼離塵冥</l>
            <l>示悟諸眾生<caesura/>令覺一切苦</l>
            <l>苦苦及苦集<caesura/>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n06"/>超苦之寂滅</l>
            <l>賢聖八正道<caesura/>安隱趣涅槃</l>
            <l>世間難得者<caesura/>現前悉皆得</l>
            <l>生世得人身<caesura/>演說於正法</l>
            <l>隨己之所欲<caesura/>離垢求清淨</l>
            <l>專修其己利<caesura/>勿令空無果</l>
            <l>空<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n07"/>過則生憂<caesura/>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n08"/>隣於地獄苦</l>
            <l>於所說正法<caesura/>不樂不欲受</l>
            <l>當久處生死<caesura/>輪迴息無期</l>
            <l>長夜懷憂<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n09"/>惱<caesura/>如商人失財</l>
            <l>我今眾慶集<caesura/>無復生老死</l>
            <l>輪迴悉已斷<caesura/>不復重受生</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0260c"/>愛識河水流<caesura/>於今悉枯竭</l>
            <l>已拔陰根本<caesura/>連鎖不相續</l>
            <l>供養大師畢<caesura/>所作者已作</l>
            <l>重擔悉已捨<caesura/>有流悉已斷</l>
            <l>不復樂受生<caesura/>亦無死可惡</l>
            <l>正智正繫念<caesura/>唯待終時至</l>
            <l>念空野龍象<caesura/>六十雄猛<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0260n10"/>獸</l>
            <l>一旦免枷鎖<caesura/>逸樂山林中</l>
            <l>婆耆舍亦然<caesura/>大師口生子</l>
            <l>厭捨於徒眾<caesura/>正念待時至</l>
            <l>今告於汝等<caesura/>諸來集會者</l>
            <l>聽我最後偈<caesura/>其義所饒益</l>
            <l>生者悉歸滅<caesura/>諸行無有常</l>
            <l>速生速死法<caesura/>何可久依怙</l>
            <l>是故強其志<caesura/>精勤方便求</l>
            <l>觀察有恐怖<caesura/>隨順牟尼道</l>
            <l>速盡此苦陰<caesura/>勿復增輪轉</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0994b">
          <l>佛口所生子<caesura/>歎說此偈已</l>
          <l>長辭於大眾<caesura/>婆耆舍涅槃</l>
          <l>彼以慈悲故<caesura/>說此無上偈</l>
        </lg>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0994c">
            <l>尊者婆耆舍<caesura/>如來法生子</l>
            <l>垂心哀愍故<caesura/>說此無上偈</l>
            <l>然後般涅槃<caesura/>一切當敬禮</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
