<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0994">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0023c18"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">拘薩羅</name>人間遊行，至<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <pb ed="T" n="0024a"/>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時舍衛國有<name type="place">憍慢婆羅門</name>止住，父母種姓俱淨，無<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0023n15"/>瑕點能說者，世世相承悉皆清淨；為婆羅門師，言論通達，諸論記典悉了萬名，解法優劣，分<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0023n16"/>明<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0023n17"/>諸字，悉知萬事久遠本末因緣，句句記說；容貌端正。或生志高、族姓志高、容色志高、聰明志高、財富志高，不敬父母、諸尊、師長。聞沙門瞿曇在拘薩羅國人間遊行，至舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。聞已，作是念：<q who="憍慢婆羅門">
            <p>我當往彼沙門瞿曇所，若有所說，我當共論；無所說者，默然而還。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時憍慢婆羅門乘白馬車，諸年少婆羅門前後導從，持金柄傘蓋，手執金瓶，往見世尊。至於園門，下車步進。爾時世尊與諸大眾圍繞說法，不時顧念憍慢婆羅門。時憍慢婆羅門作是念：</p>
        <q who="憍慢婆羅門">
          <p>沙門瞿曇不顧念我，且當還去。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊知憍慢婆羅門心念而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0092a">
            <l>憍慢既來此<caesura/>不善更增慢</l>
            <l>向以義故來<caesura/>應轉增其義</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>時憍慢婆羅門作是念：<q who="憍慢婆羅門">
            <p>沙門瞿曇已知我心。欲修敬禮。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊告憍慢婆羅門：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>止！止！不須作禮，心淨已足。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時諸大眾咸各高聲唱言：<q who="大眾">
            <p>奇哉！世尊！大德大力。今此憍慢婆羅門恃生憍慢、族姓憍慢、容色憍慢、聰明憍慢、財富憍慢，不敬父母、諸尊、師長，今於沙門瞿曇所謙卑下下，欲接足禮。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時憍慢婆羅門於大眾前唱令靜默，而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="憍慢婆羅門">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0092b">
            <l>云何不起慢<caesura/>云何起恭敬</l>
            <l>云何善慰<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0024n01"/>諭<caesura/>云何善供養</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊說偈答言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0092c">
            <l>父母及長兄<caesura/>和<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0024n02"/>尚諸師長</l>
            <l>及諸尊重者<caesura/>所不應生慢</l>
            <l>應當善恭敬<caesura/>謙下而問訊</l>
            <l>盡心而奉事<caesura/>兼設諸供養</l>
            <l>離貪恚癡心<caesura/>漏盡阿羅漢</l>
            <l>正智善解脫<caesura/>伏諸憍慢心</l>
            <l>於此賢聖等<caesura/>合掌稽首禮</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊為憍慢婆羅門種種說法，示教照喜。如佛世尊次第說法，說布施、持戒、生天功德，愛、欲、味、患，煩惱清淨，出要、遠離諸清淨分。如是廣說，如白淨衣無諸黑惡，速受染色。憍慢婆羅門即於座上解四聖諦苦<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0023n12"/>習滅道，得無間等。</p>
        <p>時憍慢婆羅門見法、得法、知法、入法，度諸疑惑，不由他度，於正法中得無所畏，即從座起，整衣服，為佛作禮，合掌白佛：</p>
        <q who="憍慢婆羅門">
          <p>我今可得於正法中出家、受具足不？</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告憍慢婆羅門：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝今可得於正法中出家、受具足。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>彼即出家，獨<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0024n03"/>正思惟：所以善男子剃除鬚髮，著袈娑衣，正信、非家、出家學道，得阿羅漢，心善解脫。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
