<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0093">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0024b13"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">拘薩羅</name>人間遊行，至<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <pb ed="T" n="0024c"/>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0024n05"/>
          <name type="person">長身婆羅門</name>，作如是邪盛大會：以七百特牛行列繫柱，特、牸、水牛及諸羊犢、種種小蟲悉皆繫縛，辦諸飲食、廣行布施，種種外道從諸國國皆悉來集邪盛會所。</p>
        <p>時長身婆羅門聞沙門瞿曇從拘薩羅人間遊行，至舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園，作是念：</p>
        <q who="uggatasarira">
          <p>我今辦邪盛大會，所以七百特牛行列繫柱，……乃至小小諸蟲皆悉繫縛。為邪盛大會故，種種異道從諸國國來至會所。我今當往沙門瞿曇所問邪盛法，莫令我作邪盛大會。分數中有所短少。</p>
        </q>
        <p>作是念已，乘白馬車，諸年少婆羅門前後導從，持金柄傘蓋，執金澡瓶，出舍衛城，詣世尊所，恭敬承事。至精舍門，下車步進，至於佛前，面相問訊慰勞已，退坐一面，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="uggatasarira">
          <p>瞿曇！我今欲作邪盛大會，以七百特牛行列繫柱，……乃至小小諸蟲皆悉繫縛。為邪盛大會故，種種異道從諸國國皆悉來至邪盛會所。又聞瞿曇從拘薩羅人間遊行，至舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園，我今故來請問瞿曇邪盛大會法諸物分數，莫令我所作邪盛大會諸分數之中有所短少。</p>
        </q>
        <p>佛告婆羅門：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>或有一邪盛大會主行施作福而生於罪，為三刀劍之所刻削，得不善果報。何等三？謂身刀劍、口刀劍、意刀劍。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>何等為意刀劍生諸苦報？如一會主造作大會，作是思惟：我作邪盛大會，當殺爾所少壯特牛，爾所水特、水牸，爾所羊犢及種種諸蟲。是名意刀劍生諸苦報。如是施主雖念作種種布施、種種供養，實生於罪！</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>云何為口刀劍生諸苦報？有一會主造作大會，作如是教：我今作邪盛大會，汝等當殺爾所少壯特牛，……乃至殺害爾所微細蟲。是名口刀劍生諸苦報。大會主雖作是布施、供養，實生於罪！</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>云何為身刀劍生諸苦報？謂有一大會主造作大會，自手傷殺爾所特牛，……乃至殺害種種細蟲，是名身刀劍生諸苦報。彼大會主雖作是念種種布施、種種供養，實生於罪！</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>然婆羅門當勤供養三火，隨時恭敬，禮拜奉事，施其安樂。何等為三？一者根本，二者居家，三者福田。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>何者為根本<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0024n06"/>火，隨時恭敬，奉事供養，施其安樂？謂善男子方便得財，手足勤苦，如法所得，供養父母，令得安樂，是名根本火。何故名為根本？若善男子從彼而生，所謂父母，故名根本。善男子以崇本故，隨時恭敬，奉事供養，施以安樂。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>何等為居家火，善男子隨時育<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n01"/>養，施以安樂？謂善男子方便得財，手足勤苦，如法所得，供給妻子、宗親、眷屬、僕使、傭客，隨時給與，恭敬施安，是名家火。何故名<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n02"/>家？其善男子處於居家，樂則同樂，苦則同苦，在所為作皆相順從，故名為<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n03"/>家。是故善男子隨時供給，施與安樂。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>何等名福田火，善男子隨時恭敬，尊重供養，施其安樂？謂善男子方便得財，手足勤勞，如法所得，奉事供養諸沙門、婆羅門——善能調伏貪、恚、癡者，如是等沙門、婆羅門，建立福田，崇向增進，樂分樂報，未來生天，是名福田火。何故名田？為世福田，謂為應供，是故名田。是善男子隨時恭敬，奉事供養，施其安樂。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時世尊復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0093a">
            <l>根本及居家<caesura/>應供福田火</l>
            <l>是火增供養<caesura/>充足安隱樂</l>
            <l>無罪樂世間<caesura/>慧者往生彼</l>
            <l>如法財復會<caesura/>供養所應養</l>
            <l>供養應養故<caesura/>生天得名稱</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>然，婆羅門！今善男子<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n04"/>先所供養三火應斷令滅。何等為三？謂貪欲火、瞋恚火、愚癡火。所以者何？若貪火不斷不滅者，自害害他，自他俱害，現法得罪，後世得罪，現法後世得罪，緣彼而生心法憂苦；恚火、癡火亦復如是。婆羅門！若善男子事積薪火，隨時辛苦，隨時然，隨時滅火因緣受苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p>爾時長身婆羅門默然而住。時有婆羅門子名<name type="person">鬱多羅</name>，於會中坐。長身婆羅門須臾默然，思惟已，告鬱多羅：</p>
        <q who="uggatasarira">
          <p>汝能往至邪盛會所，放彼繫柱特牛及諸眾生受繫縛者，悉<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n05"/>皆放不？而告之言：<q who="欝多羅">長身婆羅門語汝：<q who="uggatasarira">隨意自在，山澤曠野，食不斷草，飲淨流水，四方風中受諸快樂。</q>
            </q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p>鬱多羅白言：<q who="欝多羅">
            <p>隨大師教！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>既往彼邪盛會所放諸眾生，而告之言：<q who="欝多羅">
            <p>長身婆羅門語汝：<q who="uggatasarira">隨其所樂，山澤曠野，飲水食草，四風自適。</q>
            </p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊知鬱多羅。知已，為長身婆羅門種種說法，示教照喜。如律，世尊說法先後，說戒、說施及生天功德，愛、欲、味、患，出要清淨，煩惱清淨，開示顯<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n06"/>現，譬如鮮淨白</p>
        <p>時長身婆羅門見法、得法、知法、入法，度諸疑惑，不由他度，於正法中得無所畏。既從座起，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n07"/>整衣服，偏袒右肩，合掌白佛：<q who="uggatasarira">
            <p>已度，世尊！我從今日盡其壽命。歸佛、歸法、歸比丘僧，為優婆塞，證知我！<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n08"/>唯願世尊與諸大眾受我飯食！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊默然而許。時長身婆羅門知佛受請已，為佛作禮，右繞三匝而去。長身婆羅門還邪盛處，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0025n09"/>所諸供辦淨美好者，布置床座，遣使請佛，白言：<q who="uggatasarira">
            <p>時到，惟聖知時！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          爾時世尊著衣持缽，大眾圍繞，往到長身婆羅門會所，大眾前坐。
                           時長身婆羅門知世尊坐定已，手自供養種種飲食。食已，澡漱洗缽畢，別敷卑床，於大眾前端坐聽法。
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>爾時世尊為長身婆羅門說種種法，示教照喜已，從座起而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
