<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-0101">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0028a20"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">拘薩羅</name>人間遊行，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n03"/>
          <name type="place">有從迦帝聚落</name>、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n04"/>
          <name type="place">墮鳩羅聚落</name>二村中間，一樹下坐，入<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n05"/>盡正受。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n06"/>
          <name type="person">豆磨種姓婆羅門</name>隨彼道行，尋佛後來，見佛腳跡千輻輪相，印文顯現，齊輻圓輞，眾好滿足。見已，作是念：<q who="dona">
            <p>我未曾見人間有如是足跡，今當隨跡以求其人。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>即尋腳跡至於佛所，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n07"/>來見世尊坐一樹下，入<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n05"/>盡正受，嚴容絕世，諸根澄靜，其心寂定，第一調伏，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n08"/>正觀成就，光相巍巍，猶若金山。見已，白言：<q who="dona">
            <p>為是<pb ed="T" n="0028b"/>天耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆羅門：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我非天也。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <q who="dona">
            <p>為龍、夜叉、乾闥婆、阿修羅、迦樓羅、緊那羅、摩睺羅伽、人、非人等？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告婆羅門：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我非龍……乃至人、非人也。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>婆羅門白佛：<q who="dona">
            <p>若言非天、非龍……乃至非人、非非人，為是何等？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊說偈答言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-0101a">
            <l>天龍乾闥婆<caesura/>緊那羅夜叉</l>
            <l>無善阿修羅<caesura/>諸摩睺羅伽</l>
            <l>人與非人等<caesura/>悉由煩惱生</l>
            <l>如是煩惱漏<caesura/>一切我已捨</l>
            <l>已破已磨滅<caesura/>如<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n09"/>芬陀利生</l>
            <l>雖生於水中<caesura/>而未曾著水</l>
            <l>我雖生世間<caesura/>不為世間著</l>
            <l>歷劫常選擇<caesura/>純苦無暫樂</l>
            <l>一切有為行<caesura/>悉皆生滅故</l>
            <l>離垢不傾動<caesura/>已拔諸劍刺</l>
            <l>究竟生死<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0028n10"/>除<caesura/>故名為佛陀</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，豆摩種婆羅門聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，從路而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
