<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1278">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0351b12"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有<name type="person">
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n08"/>瞿迦梨</name>比丘，是<name type="person">提婆達多</name>伴黨，來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面。爾時世尊告瞿迦梨比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p>瞿迦<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n09"/>梨！汝何故於<name type="person">舍利弗</name>、<name type="person">目揵連</name>清淨梵行所，起不清淨心？長夜當得不饒益苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p>瞿迦梨比丘白佛言：<q who="kokaliya">
            <p>世尊！我今信世尊語，所說無異，但舍利弗、大目揵連心有惡欲。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p> 如是第二、第三說，瞿迦梨比丘――提婆達多伴黨――於世尊所再三說中，違反不受，從座起去。<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n10"/>去已，其身周遍生諸<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n11"/>
            疱瘡，皆如栗，漸漸增長，皆如桃李。
                             時瞿迦梨比丘患苦痛，口說是言：
          </p>
        <q who="kokaliya">
          <p>極燒！極燒！</p>
        </q>
        <p>膿血流出，身壞命終，生大<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n12"/>鉢曇摩地獄。</p>
        <p>時有三天子，容色絕妙，於後夜時來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面。時一天子白佛言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p>瞿迦梨比丘――提婆達多伴黨――今已命終。</p>
        </q>
        <p>
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n13"/>時，第二天子作是言：<q who="devata">
            <p>諸尊當知：瞿迦梨比丘命終墮地獄中。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>第三天子即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1277a">
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" n="0351c"/>士夫生世間<caesura/>斧在口中生</l>
            <l>還自斬其身<caesura/>斯由其惡言</l>
            <l>應毀便稱譽<caesura/>應譽而便毀</l>
            <l>其罪生於口<caesura/>死墮惡道中</l>
            <l>博弈亡失財<caesura/>是非為大咎</l>
            <l>毀佛及聲聞<caesura/>是則為大過</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p>彼三天了說是偈已，即沒不現。</p>
        <p>爾時世尊夜過晨朝，來入僧中，於大眾前敷座而坐，告諸比丘：
                 <q who="gotamo">
            <p>昨後夜時有三天子來詣我所，稽首我足，退坐一面。第一天子語我言：『世尊！瞿迦梨比丘――提婆達多伴黨――今已命終。』第二天子語餘天<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n14"/>子言：『瞿迦梨比丘命終墮地獄中。』第三天子即說偈言：<q who="devata">
                <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1277b">
                  <l>士夫生世間<caesura/>斧在口中生</l>
                  <l>還自斬其身<caesura/>斯由其惡言</l>
                  <l>應毀便稱譽<caesura/>應譽而便毀</l>
                  <l>其罪口中生<caesura/>死則墮惡道</l>
                </lg>
              </q>
                     說是偈已，即沒不現。諸比丘！汝等欲聞生<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n15"/>阿浮陀地獄眾生其壽齊限不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>諸比丘白佛：<q who="bhikkhavo">
            <p>今正是時唯願世尊為諸大眾說阿浮陀地獄眾生壽命齊限。諸比丘聞已。當受奉行。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告比丘：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>諦聽！善思！善為汝說。譬如<name type="place">拘薩羅國</name>，四<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n16"/>斗為一阿羅，四阿羅為一獨籠那，十六獨籠那為一闍摩那，十六闍摩那為一摩尼，二十摩尼為一佉梨，二十佉梨為一倉，滿中芥子。若使有人百年<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n17"/>百年取一芥子，如是乃至滿倉芥子都盡，阿浮陀地獄眾生壽命猶故不盡。如是二十阿浮陀地獄眾生壽等一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0351n18"/>尼羅浮陀地獄眾生壽，二十尼<pb ed="T" n="0352a"/>羅浮陀地獄眾生壽等一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0352n01"/>阿吒吒地獄眾生壽，二十阿吒吒地獄眾生壽等一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0352n02"/>阿波波地獄眾生壽，二十阿波波地獄眾生壽等一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0352n03"/>阿休休地獄眾生壽，二十阿休休地獄眾生壽等一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0352n04"/>
                優缽羅地獄眾生壽，二十優缽羅地獄眾生壽等一缽曇摩地獄眾生壽，二十缽曇摩地獄眾生壽等一摩訶缽曇摩地獄眾生壽。
                                 比丘！彼瞿迦梨比丘命終墮摩訶缽曇摩地獄中，以彼於尊者舍利弗、大目揵連比丘生惡心、誹謗故。是故，諸比丘！當作是學：於
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0352n05"/>彼燒燋<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0352n06"/>炷所，尚不欲毀壞，況毀壞有識眾生？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告諸比丘：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>當如是學！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行！</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
