<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head xml:lang="sa">a lpa de ba tā sū tra</head>
        <head xml:lang="bo">lha'i mdo nyung du</head>
        <p>
          From the Derge edition. Derge 330. This is part of the text-cluster of BZA
                              (T.100) sutra 297.
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:lang="bo">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="der.72.sa.258b7"/>
      <div type="parallel">
        <p>
          sangs rgyas dang/ byang chub sems dpa' thams cad la phyag 'tshal lo/ 'di skad
                                  bdag gis thos pa dus gcig na/ bcom ldan 'das mnyan yod na rgyal bu rgyal
                                  byed kyi tshal mgon med zas sbyin gyi kun dga' ra ba na bzhugs te/
        </p>
        <p>
          de nas lha zhig bcom ldan 'das ga la ba der song ste phyin nas bcom ldan 'das
                                  kyi zhabs la mgo bos phyag 'tshal te phyogs gcig tu bdug go/ phyogs gcig tu
                                  'dug nas lha des bcom ldan 'das la zhu ba zhus pa/
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>tshul khrims gang lags spyod pa gang/ yon tan gang lags las gang gis/</l>
          <l>gnas pa ji ltar shes rab gang/ skye po gang dag mtho ris mchi/</l>
          <l>lha la thugs brtse nyer bzung nas/ ston pas de la lung bstan pa/</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>skye bo mtho ris gang 'gro ba/ lha khyod nga la rab tu nyon/</l>
          <l>srog gcod pa las phyir ldog cing/ khrims bzung yang dag sdom la dga'/</l>
          <l>gang dag 'byung bo mi 'tshe ba/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>gang dag ma byin len spong zhing/ sbyin pa gtong la rtag dga' ste/</l>
          <l>rku ba spong zhing mi rku ba/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>gzhan gyi chung ma'i thad mi 'gro/ log par gyem pa rnam par spong/</l>
          <l>bdag gi chung mas chog sems pa/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>gzhan gyi don la rku byed dang/ bdag gi phyir dang 'jigs pa'i phyir/</l>
          <l>brdzun gyi tshig rnams mi smra ba/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>grogs po rtag par 'byed byed pa/ phra ma'i tshig rnams rab spong zhing/</l>
          <l>gang dga 'dun par rab dga' ba/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>rgyags la rten cing zhe gcod pa/ tshig rtsub dag ni rnam sbyong zhing/</l>
          <l>'jam po'i tshig tu gang smra ba/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>don med gnas dang ldan pa yi/ kyal pa'i tshig rnams rab spong zhing/</l>
          <l>gang yang dus su chos smra ba/ skyes bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>grong ngam 'on te dgon pa na/ gzhan gyis bdag gir byas pa la/</l>
          <l>de la chags sems gang med pa/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>byams pa'i sems kyis mi 'tshe zhing/ gnod par sems pa med pa yis/</l>
          <l>skys bo kun la mi gnod pa/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>las dang las kyi rnam smin dang/ gnyi ga la yang gang dad cid/</l>
          <l>yang dag lta pa yang dag 'dzin/ skye bo de dag mthi ris 'gro/</l>
          <l>dge ba'i chos rnams 'di dag ni/ dkar po'i chos kyi lam bcu ste/</l>
          <l>gang dag yang dag 'dzin 'gyur ba/ skye bo de dag mtho ris 'gro/</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>bram ze mya ngan 'das pa dang/ dgra dang 'jigs pa kun 'das shing/</l>
          <l>'jig rten chags med rgal ba ni/ mang po yod par ma mthong ngo/</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          bcom ldan 'das kyis de skad ces bka' stsal nas lha de yi rangs te/
                               bcom ldan 'das kyis gsungs pa la mngon par bstod do/
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
