<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1307">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0359a10"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main">
        <p>時有<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0359n02"/>
          <name type="person">赤馬天子</name>，容色絕妙，於後夜時來詣佛所，稽首佛足，退坐一面，其身光明遍照祇樹給孤獨園。</p>
        <p>時彼赤馬天子白佛言：<q who="rohitassadevaputta">
            <p>世尊！頗有能行過世界邊，至不生、不老、不死處不？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告赤馬：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>無有能過世界邊，至不生、不老、不死處者。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>赤馬天子白佛言：<q who="rohitassadevaputta">
            <p>奇哉！世尊！善說斯義。如世尊說言：<q who="gotamo">無過世界邊，至不生、不老、不死處<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0359n03"/>者。</q>所以者何？世尊！我自憶宿命，名曰赤馬，作外道仙人，得神通，離諸愛欲。我時作是念：<q who="rohitassadevaputta">我有如是<choice>
                  <sic>揵</sic>
                  <corr resp="CBETA">捷</corr>
                </choice>疾神足如健士夫，以利箭橫射過多羅樹影之頃，能登一須彌，至一須彌；足躡東海，<choice>
                  <sic>越</sic>
                  <corr resp="CBETA">超</corr>
                </choice>至西海。</q>我時作是念：<q who="rohitassadevaputta">我今成就如是<choice>
                  <sic>揵</sic>
                  <corr resp="CBETA">捷</corr>
                </choice>疾神力，今日寧可求世界邊。</q>作是念已，即便發行，唯除食息便利，減節睡眠，常行百歲，於彼命終，竟不能<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0359n04"/>得過世界邊，至不生、不老、不死之處。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛告赤馬：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>我今但以一尋之身，說於世界、世界集、世界滅、世界滅道跡。赤馬天子！何等為世間？謂五受陰。何等為<pb ed="T" n="0359b"/>五？色受陰、受受陰、想受陰、行受陰、識受陰，是名世間。何等為色集？謂當來有愛、貪、喜俱，彼彼染著，是名世間集。云何為世間滅？若彼當來有愛、貪、喜俱，彼彼染著，無餘斷、捨、離、盡、無欲、滅、息沒，是名世間滅。何等為世間滅道跡？謂八聖道——正見、正志、正語、正業、正命、正方便、正念、正定，是名世間滅道跡。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>
          <q who="gotamo">
            <p>赤馬！了知世<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0359n05"/>間苦，斷世<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0359n05"/>間苦；了知世間集，斷世間集；了知世間滅，證世間滅；了知世間滅道跡，修彼<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0359n06"/>滅道跡。赤馬！若比丘於世間苦若知、若斷，世間集若知、若斷，世間滅若知、若證，世間滅道跡若知、若修。赤馬！是名得世界邊，度世間愛。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊重說偈言：</p>
        <q who="rohitassadevaputta">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1307a">
            <l>未曾遠遊行<caesura/>而得世界邊</l>
            <l>無得世界邊<caesura/>終不盡苦邊</l>
            <l>以是故牟尼<caesura/>能知世界邊</l>
            <l>善解世界邊<caesura/>諸梵行已立</l>
            <l>於彼世界邊<caesura/>平等覺知者</l>
            <l>是名賢聖行<caesura/>
              <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0359n07"/>度世間彼岸</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>是時赤馬天子聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，稽首佛足，即沒不現。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
