<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="tn0099-1320">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="tp0362a29"/>
      <div type="opening">
        <p>如是我聞：一時佛住<name type="place">摩鳩羅山</name>，尊者<name type="person">那伽波羅</name>為親侍者。</p>
      </div>
      <pb ed="T" n="0362b"/>
      <pb ed="T" n="0362c"/>
      <div type="main">
        <p>爾時世尊於夜闇時天小微雨，電光睒現，出於房外，露地經行。</p>
        <p>是時<name type="person">天帝釋</name>作是念：<q who="天帝釋">
            <p>今日世尊住摩鳩羅山，尊者那伽波羅親侍供養，其夜闇冥，天時微雨，電光睒現，世尊出房，露地經行，我當化作<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n08"/>毘琉<choice>
                <sic>瑠</sic>
                <corr resp="CBETA">璃</corr>
              </choice>重閣，執持重閣，隨佛經行。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>作是念已，即便化作<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n09"/>鞞琉璃重閣，持詣佛所，稽首佛足，隨佛經行。爾時摩竭提國人若男若女，夜啼之時以摩鳩羅鬼恐之即止。親侍供養弟子之法，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n10"/>待師禪覺，然後乃眠。爾時世尊為天帝釋夜經行久。</p>
        <p>爾時尊者那伽波羅作是念：<q who="nagapala">
            <p>世尊今夜經行至久，我今當作摩鳩羅鬼形而恐怖之！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>時那伽波羅比丘即反被俱<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n11"/>執，長毛在外，往<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n12"/>在世尊經行道頭，白佛言：<q who="nagapala">
            <p>摩鳩羅鬼來！摩鳩羅鬼來！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊告那伽波羅比丘：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>汝那伽波羅愚癡人，以摩鳩羅鬼神像恐怖佛耶？不能動如來、應、等正覺一毛髮也，如來、應、等正覺久離恐怖！</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時天帝釋白佛言：<q who="天帝釋">
            <p>世尊！世尊正法、律中亦復有此人耶？</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>佛言：<q who="gotamo">
            <p>憍尸迦！瞿曇家中極大廣闊，斯等於未來世亦當使得清淨之法。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
        <p>爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg met="5" xml:id="cgtn0099-1320a">
            <l>若復婆羅門<caesura/>於自所得法</l>
            <l>得到於彼岸<caesura/>若一<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n13"/>毘舍遮</l>
            <l>及<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n14"/>與<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n15"/>摩鳩羅<caesura/>皆悉超過去</l>
            <l>若復婆羅門<caesura/>於自所行法</l>
            <l>一切諸受覺<caesura/>觀察皆已滅</l>
            <l>若復婆羅門<caesura/>自法度彼岸</l>
            <l>一切諸因緣<caesura/>皆悉已滅盡</l>
            <l>若復婆羅門<caesura/>自法度彼岸</l>
            <l>一切諸人<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0362n16"/>我<caesura/>皆悉已滅盡</l>
            <l>若復婆羅門<caesura/>自法度彼岸</l>
            <l>於生老病死<caesura/>皆悉已超過</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing">
        <p>佛說此經已，釋提桓因聞佛所說，歡喜隨喜，稽首佛足，即沒不現。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
