<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza091">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0404c19"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza091">
        <p n="bza091.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza091">
        <p n="bza091.02">爾時有一摩納，名曰<name type="person">佛移</name>，往詣佛所，稽首問訊，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="ujjayo">
          <p n="bza091.03">世尊！為有幾法教，在家人處於家中得現報利，并得利樂？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza091.04">佛告摩納：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza091.05">有四法，使在家人得現世報，獲利益樂。何謂為四？一、能精勤，二、能守護諸根，三、得善知識，四、正理養命。云何『精勤』？隨所作業，家計資生，或為王臣，或為農夫，或復治生，或復牧人，隨其所作，不憚<app n="fnT02p0404n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">劬</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">勤</rdg>
            </app>劬勞，寒暑風雨，飢渴飽滿，蚊虻蠅蜂。雖有勤苦，不捨作業。為成業故，終不休廢，是名『精勤』。云何名<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0405a" n="0405a"/>為『守護諸根』？若族姓子如法聚財，設有方計，不為王、賊、水、火之所劫奪，怨憎之處悉不得侵，不生惡子，是名『守護』。云何名為『近於善友』？若族姓子近於善友──而此善友資性賢良，終不姦盜，亦不放逸，飲酒醉亂。吐出實言，不為欺誑──，與如此人共為親友，未生憂惱能令不生，已生憂惱能使<app n="fnT02p0405n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">滅除</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">除滅</rdg>
            </app>滅除，未生喜樂能使得生，已<app n="fnT02p0405n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">生</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">得</rdg>
            </app>生喜樂能使不失，是名『善友』。云何名為『正理養命』？若族姓子知其財物，量其多少，節其<app n="fnT02p0405n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">財</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">時</rdg>
            </app>財用，入多於出，莫苟輕用──譬如有人，食<app n="fnT02p0404n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">優</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">憂</rdg>
            </app>優曇果。初食之時樹上甚多，既食之已，醉眠七日。既醒悟已，方覺失<choice>
              <sic>＊果</sic>
              <corr resp="CBETA">果</corr>
            </choice>──，宜處以理，奢儉得中。若有錢財，不能衣食，不能惠施，極自儉用，眾人咸言：『如<app n="fnT02p0405n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">此</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">是</rdg>
            </app>此之人，死如狗死！』宜自籌量，不奢不儉，是名『正理養命』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza091.06">摩納復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="ujjayo">
          <p n="bza091.07">修何等法，令在家人現受其利，後世得福？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza091.08">佛告摩納：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza091.09">有四種法，能獲福報。何謂為四？所謂信、戒及施、聞慧。云何名『戒』？能行不殺，……（乃至）不飲酒。云何名『施』？施沙門、婆羅門、師長、父母、貧窮之者，乞與衣、食、床敷、臥具、病瘦醫藥，種種所須盡能惠與，<app n="fnT02p0405n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">名之</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">是名</rdg>
            </app>名之為『施』。云何『聞慧』？如實知苦，知苦諦；如實知<app n="fnT02p0405n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">習</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">集</rdg>
            </app>習，知<app n="fnT02p0405n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">習</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">集</rdg>
            </app>習諦；如實知道，知道諦；如實知滅，知滅諦，是名『聞慧具足』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza091.10">佛告摩納：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza091.11" met="5" xml:id="cg091a">
            <l>精心修事業<caesura/>勤守護不失</l>
            <l>親近於善友<caesura/>能正理養命</l>
            <l>信戒施聞慧<caesura/>除斷於慳貪</l>
            <l>若能如是者<caesura/>速獲清淨道</l>
            <l>如是八種法<caesura/>能得現利喜</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0405b" n="0405b"/>於未來之世<caesura/>亦得天上樂</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza091">
        <p n="bza091.12">佛說是已，佛移摩納聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
