<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>The conversion of Aṅgulimāla</head>
        <p>Translation of BZA 016. First version published in <emph>Buddhist Studies Review</emph>vol. 23-1 (2006).</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="bza016en" xml:lang="en">
      <div>
        <p>Thus have I heard, once, the Buddha traveled in Magadha in the Tao-he forest.</p>
        <p>[On his way] he met a herdsman  who said: ‘In this forest lives the bandit Aṅgulimāla, who might kill you’. The Buddha told the herdsman: ‘I don’t think I will be harmed by this bandit’, and went along. He met another herdsman who told him the same and the Buddha answered as before. This happened three times, and the Buddha said: ‘This evil person will never harm me’. When he had entered the depth of the forest, Aṅgulimāla saw him coming from afar and, scabbard in the left hand, sword in the right, charged forward. But though he was running quickly and the Buddha calmly walked along, he could not reach him. When Aṅgulimāla became exhausted, he called to the Buddha: ‘Stop! Renunciant, stop!’. The Buddha replied: ‘I have already stopped, it is you who haven’t stopped’.</p>
        <p>There Aṅgulimāla spoke a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>This renunciant keeps on walking / but says: ‘I have already stopped’. //</l>
          <l>I now have stopped / and he says I have not. //</l>
          <l>Why does he say he has stopped / and I keep going? //</l>
        </lg>
        <p>There the Buddha spoke a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>For long have I abstained / from harming other beings by knife or cudgel. //</l>
          <l>You trouble them / persist in your evil ways. //</l>
          <l>So I say I have stopped / and you have not. //</l>
          <l>I have abandoned causing, out of spite and evil / harm to all endowed with form. //</l>
          <l>It is you who do not cease your evil ways / always doing unwholesome deeds. //</l>
          <l>So I say I have stopped / and you have not. //</l>
          <l>I have abandoned all forms of hatred / towards living beings. //</l>
          <l>You harm the living / have not abandoned the dark ways. //</l>
          <l>So I say I have stopped / and you have not. //</l>
          <l>I enjoy my state  / the mind concentrated tirelessly. //</l>
          <l>You don’t see the four truths  / and cannot find a place to stop. //</l>
          <l>So I say that it is me who has stopped / and you have not. //</l>
        </lg>
        <p>There Aṅgulimāla spoke a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>Long have I dwelt in this wilderness / never have I seen such a man; //</l>
          <l>the Bhagavant has come here / to teach me the good Dhamma. //</l>
          <l>Long have I followed evil ways / today I will abandon them. //</l>
          <l>Now that I have heard you speak / I follow the Dhamma and cut off all evil.  //</l>
        </lg>
        <lg>
          <l>[Having spoken thus he] sheathed the sword / and cast it into a deep pit //</l>
          <l>and bowed his head to pay homage / and took refuge with the World-honored One //</l>
          <l>filled with deep faith / he set his mind on going forth. //</l>
          <l>There the Buddha let compassion arise / for the benefit of all worlds //</l>
          <l>invited him: ‘Come’/ so he became a renunciant. //</l>
        </lg>
        <p>There Aṅgulimāla, son of a good family, cut off his hair, put on the robes and went forth. [From then on] he took his abode in silent emptiness, his mind striving tirelessly, focused on his practice, diligent in his efforts, by concentration he focused his mind in true insight. He practised supreme abstinence, reached the end of suffering and attained realization within this present world, within his own very body. He clearly understood his nature. He knew: birth had come to an end, the holy abode is established, done is what had to be done, there will be no further rebirth [for me]. When the venerable Ahiṃsaka  became an Arahat and attained the joy of liberation he spoke this verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>My name is Ahiṃsaka [one who does no harm]  / but later I committed great cruelties. //</l>
          <l>Now however my name has come true / truth is not to harm. //</l>
          <l>Now I abstain from doing harm with body / speech and mind. //</l>
          <l>Who never harms others / is truly called Ahiṃsaka. //</l>
          <l>I was steeped in blood / they called me Aṅgulimāla. //</l>
          <l>[like one] carried away by a strong current / only now that I have taken refuge in the Buddha //</l>
          <l>and received ordination / I grasped the three knowledges,  //</l>
          <l>fully understanding the teachings of the Buddha / I respect and practise it. //</l>
          <l>In this world, those who tame / or control use knife and staff and cudgel, //</l>
          <l>use iron hooks and whips and bridles / dealing cuffs and blows. //</l>
          <l>The World-honored One, the great tamer / has done away with evil methods, //</l>
          <l>has cast away knife, staff and cudgel / this is the true way of taming. //</l>
          <l>Crossing water, one needs a bridge or a boat / to straighten arrows, one needs a fire, //</l>
          <l>the carpenter needs an axe / knowledge is adjusted by wisdom. //</l>
          <l>A person who at first committed evil / then stops, not continuing doing so: //</l>
          <l>he shines upon the world / like the moon when the clouds have disappeared. //</l>
          <l>A person who was slothful at first / then stops being lazy: //</l>
          <l>whole-heartedly he abandons thorns and poison / focusing on crossing to the other shore. //</l>
          <l>Once the evil deeds are done / one is bound to be reborn in evil realms. //</l>
          <l>Meeting the Buddha purged my guilt / I could avoid [the fruit of] my evil actions. //</l>
          <l>All those who grasp what I say / liberate their minds from the bonds of hatred, //</l>
          <l>by patient suffering attain the pure vision / being victorious without fighting is the teaching of the Buddha. //</l>
        </lg>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
