<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza066">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0396b08"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza066">
        <p n="bza066.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza066">
        <p n="bza066.02">爾時<name type="person">波斯匿</name>王於閑靜處作是思惟：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza066.03">頗有一法，能得現利及後世利？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza066.04">作是念已，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，退坐一面，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza066.05">世尊！頗有一法，能得現利、後世利不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza066.06">佛告王曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza066.07">
                            我有一法，修行，增廣，現在、未來多所饒益，所謂修行不放逸法，現得利益，來世亦利。譬如大地，能生百穀、一切草木。一切善法亦因不放逸生，不放逸增長，不放逸廣大。<app n="fnT02p0396n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">大</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">天</rdg>
            </app>大王！猶如大地，一切種子因地而生，因地增廣。一切眾生因不放逸，亦復如是。一切根香中，黑堅實香最為第一。此事亦爾，一切善法因不放逸。堅實香中，赤栴檀為第一。此事亦爾，一切善法因不放逸為本。不放逸者，是實法因。不放逸者，善法生處。一切華鬘中，乾陀婆梨琴華鬘最為第一。一切善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切水生華中，青蓮華第一。一切善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切畜生跡中，象跡最大。一切善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）如與賊戰，能先諸鬪名為第一。一切善法，不<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0396c" n="0396c"/>放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切獸中，師子第一。善法之中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切樓觀，高波那<app n="fnT02p0396n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">寫</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】【聖】">羅</rdg>
            </app>寫最為第一。善法之中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切閻浮提樹，閻浮提界上樹最為第一。善法之中，不放逸為第一。……（餘如上說）一切<app n="fnT02p0396n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">詹</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">薝</rdg>
            </app>詹婆羅樹中，鳩羅<app n="fnT02p0396n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">苦</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">薝</rdg>
            </app>苦婆羅最為第一。諸善法中。不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切波吒羅樹中，錦文芭吒羅為第一。諸善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切樹中，波<app n="fnT02p0396n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">利</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">梨</rdg>
            </app>利質多羅為第一。諸善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切山中，須彌山第一。諸善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切金中，閻浮檀金第一。諸善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切妙衣，迦尸衣第一。諸善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切色中，白為第一。諸善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切鳥中，金翅為第一。諸善法中，不放逸第一。……（餘如上說）一切明中，日光為第一。不放逸法，亦復如是。……（餘如上說）<app n="fnT02p0396n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">如上說</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">上</rdg>
            </app>如上說諸修行善行，不放逸者，是其根本，是其生因。是故──大王！──汝今應修不放逸法，亦應依止不放逸法。王若如是，王之夫人及以妃后亦不放逸。王子、大臣及諸官屬亦復<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0397a" n="0397a"/>如是。若不放逸，即是守護中宮<app n="fnT02p0397n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">內外</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">外內</rdg>
            </app>內外。以不放逸故，倉庫盈滿。王不放逸，則為自護并護一切。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza066.08">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza066.09" met="5" xml:id="cg066a">
            <l>不放逸最勝<caesura/>放逸多譏嫌</l>
            <l>今世不放逸<caesura/>後世得大利</l>
            <l>現利他世利<caesura/>解知二俱利</l>
            <l>是名為健夫<caesura/>明哲之所行</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza066">
        <p n="bza066.10">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
