<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                      法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                            Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                            text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                            lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                            Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                            edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
            (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
            (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                            comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                            the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                            literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                        English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project is to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The texts are kept in single files in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any changes after 2008 see the revision
                          description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza041">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0387a02"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza041">
        <p n="bza041.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza041">
        <p n="bza041.02">爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza041.03">昔<name type="person">釋提桓因</name>欲詣遊戲園，勅御者<name type="person">摩得梨</name>：<q who="sakko">汝駕千馬車。</q>時摩得梨尋駕車已，詣<name type="person">帝釋</name>所，即白<app n="fnT02p0387n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">釋</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">帝釋</rdg>
            </app>釋言：<q who="matali">嚴駕已訖，宜知是時。</q>爾時帝釋出<name type="place">毘禪延堂</name>，合掌南向。時摩得梨見已，心亦驚怕，失鞭及轡。帝釋語言：<q who="sakko">汝見何事，驚怖乃爾？</q>摩得梨言：<q who="matali">
              <name type="person">摩佉</name>！<name type="person">釋脂之夫</name>！我今見汝合掌南向，心懷懼故，致失鞭、轡。一切有生，皆敬於汝。一切地主，盡屬於汝。四天王天及三十三天，皆禮敬汝。誰復有德，勝於汝者，叉手合掌南向而立？</q>帝釋答言：<q who="sakko">一切敬我，信如汝言。一切天、人所恭敬者，名之為法。我今恭敬禮具足戒法。</q>爾時帝釋即說偈言：<q who="sakko">
              <lg n="bza041.04" met="5" xml:id="cg041a">
                <l>有諸出家者<caesura/>以修不放逸</l>
                <l>長夜入寂定<caesura/>修最上梵行</l>
                <l>捨棄於三毒<caesura/>能得解脫法</l>
                <l>有如是等法<caesura/>我今恭敬禮</l>
                <l>諸大阿羅漢<caesura/>遠離於欲者</l>
                <l>能滅無明闇<caesura/>斷除諸結使</l>
                <l>并在家修善<caesura/>不作惡業者</l>
                <l>如是正法子<caesura/>今我皆敬禮</l>
              </lg>
            </q>                    　　　
                    摩得梨言：<q who="matali">汝禮最勝，我願隨禮！</q>爾時帝釋作是語已，合掌敬禮，乘輦而去。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza041.05">佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza041.06">帝釋處於人、天而得自在，尚能恭敬禮敬於法，況汝比丘剃除鬚髮，出家學道，而當不勤恭敬於法。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza041">
        <p n="bza041.07">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
