<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>The daughters of Māra</head>
        <p>Translation of BZA 031. First version published in <emph>
            Buddhist Studies
                                Review
          </emph>vol. 23-1 (2006).</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="bza031en" xml:lang="en">
      <div>
        <p>
          Thus have I heard, once, the Buddha was staying in the village uruvelā near the
                              river nerañjarā under the Bodhi tree. This was not long after he had attained
                              Buddhahood. At that time King Māra had this thought: ‘The Buddha is staying in
                              the village uruvelā near the river nerañjarā under the Bodhi tree. He has just
                              attained Buddhahood. I should go there and try to mislead him’.
        </p>
        <p>He went to the Buddha and spoke this verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>You live alone in the wilderness // taciturn, always silent.</l>
          <l>
            Of radiant countenance and with celestial body // all senses [perceiving]
                                    happiness,
          </l>
          <l>like someone who had lost his fortune // and later regained it.</l>
          <l>
            You are idling your time away in the silence of meditation // and the
                                    enjoyment that comes with it.
          </l>
          <l>
            Since you were able to discard public honours // and do not desire status and
                                    profit,
          </l>
          <l>why do you not with others // form close friendships?</l>
        </lg>
        <p>At that time the World-honoured One answered with a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            For a long time I have attained meditative concentration // where the mind is
                                    always still.
          </l>
          <l>I have defeated your armies of desire // [and] reached the highest fortune.</l>
          <l>
            My senses are always quiet and happy // In my mind I have attained silent
                                    extinction.
          </l>
          <l>Defeating your armies of desire // practising the way I feel joy,</l>
          <l>
            [I live] alone, apart from the hustle and bustle [of others] // What use is
                                    there for close friends?
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>At that time King Māra spoke this verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>Now, since you have attained the true way // you can rest in Nirvāṇa.</l>
          <l>
            Since you have reached the wonderful Dhamma // you should keep it forever in
                                    your bosom.
          </l>
          <l>Uprightly face and understand it alone; // why should you teach the many?</l>
        </lg>
        <p>At that time the World-honoured One answered with a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            Humankind does not belong to you // if someone asks me about the teaching
                                    that leads to the other shore,
          </l>
          <l>I will correctly explain // the truth to let them attain extinction.</l>
          <l>Stopping their mind without giving up; // Māra will not overpower them.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>at that time King Māra spoke this verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>It is as if there is a large white boulder // its colour like that of fat.</l>
          <l>
            A flock of crows cannot distinguish [the two] // they perch on it and peck
                                    away,
          </l>
          <l>
            but do not get the taste [they wanted] // and with bruised beaks take off
                                    again into the air.
          </l>
          <l>
            I myself am like this // having come in vain, there is nothing more to
                                do.
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          There King Māra, having spoken this verse, became depressed and dispirited and
                              felt deep regret. he went to an empty place where he crouched alone and with an
                              arrow drawing [figures] on the ground, trying to think of a way79 [to prevent
                              the Buddha from teaching]. Māra had three daughters; the first was called
                              Passionate, the second Pleasing, and the third Desirable. Māra’s daughters came
                              to his side and addressed their father with a verse:
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>Father is famous as a great Lord // why are you so depressed?</l>
          <l>
            We will with the snare of desire // bind him [the Buddha] like one catches a
                                    bird,
          </l>
          <l>and bring him to our father // to make you feel at ease.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>King Māra answered with a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>This man is good in cutting off desire // he is not moved by it.</l>
          <l>He has left the world of Māra already // this is why I am sad.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          There, Māra’s three daughters changed their appearance. Becoming extraordinary
                              beautiful, they went to the Buddha, paid homage to his feet and sat to one side.
                              The three daughters said together in one voice: ‘We have come to worship you and
                              be at your service’. But the World-honoured One [had already attained] the final
                              cutting-off of desires and did not even look at them. They addressed him like
                              this a second and a third time. The Buddha did not look at them. There, Māra’s
                              three daughters retreated and discussed the matter: ‘it is in the nature of men
                              that they like different types [of women]. some like [their women] young, some
                              like them middle-aged and some mature’. upon [saying] that, each daughter
                              changed into six hundred women, some of them small girls, some teenagers, some
                              of them already married women, and some not yet married, some of them had given
                              birth already and some had not yet given birth. having thus turned into a
                              multitude of women, they all went to the Buddha and said to him: ‘World-honoured
                              One! We have come to worship the World-honoured One and be at his service. We
                              will serve [the World-honoured One] in every way’.
        </p>
        <p>
          The Buddha did not look at them. They addressed him like this a second and a
                              third time. The Buddha did not look at them at all. There, Māra’s daughters
                              retreated and conferred again. ‘he must have attained the final cutting-off of
                              desire, utmost liberation. Otherwise he would have looked at us and become mad,
                              spitting blood. It might even have torn his heart apart. Let us go to him and
                              debate with him in verse’.
        </p>
        <p>Māra’s daughter Passionate asked in a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            The body upright, one hand cupped within another, you sit under the tree //
                                    alone in complete solitude, contemplating.
          </l>
          <l>Like someone who has lost a fortune // and desires to find a great treasure.</l>
          <l>In the cities and villages // your mind is without passion or attachment.</l>
          <l>Why is it that among all those people // you have made no close friends?</l>
        </lg>
        <p>At that time the World-honoured One answered in a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            I have already attained the great treasure // attained quiet extinction in
                                    the mind.
          </l>
          <l>
            I have destroyed the host of passion and desire // am not attached to
                                    wonderful forms.
          </l>
          <l>I dwell alone sitting in meditation // experiencing the ultimate joy.</l>
          <l>For this reason // I do not desire close friends.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Māra’s daughter Desirable spoke this verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            Dwelling in which state, oh monk // have you crossed the five currents [of
                                    sense-pleasures],
          </l>
          <l>as well as the sixth [i.e. mind] // in what meditation do you abide?</l>
          <l>
            That you attained the crossing from the great shore of desire // forever free
                                    from the bondage of becoming?
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>At that time the World-honoured One spoke a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            The body has obtained subtle, gentle joy // the mind attained good
                                    liberation.
          </l>
          <l>The mind abstains from action // consciousness will not regress again.</l>
          <l>
            Having attained the method of cutting off discursive thought // having
                                    attained avoidance of falling into hate and passion;
          </l>
          <l>if one can abide in this state // [one] can cross the five currents,</l>
          <l>and the sixth as well // if one can sit in meditation like this,</l>
          <l>
            one can cross from the [existance bound by the] great fetter of desire // and
                                    leave the relentless flow of becoming.
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>Māra’s daughter Pleasing said in a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            Having cut off the fetter of passion // having abandoned what most people are
                                    attached to,
          </l>
          <l>
            crossing over the currents of many desires // crossing from the many desires’
                                    shore of death;
          </l>
          <l>only the wise // can cross against these difficulties.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>At that time the World-honoured One spoke this verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            By great effort the Tathāgata extracts himself // [and] crosses with the help
                                    of the true Dhamma.
          </l>
          <l>Liberated by the Dhamma // the wise have no reason not to be happy.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          The three daughters, their wish unfulfilled, returned to their father. King Māra
                              scolded them and for that spoke a verse:
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            My three daughters thought they could destroy him // their appearance
                                    [blinding] like lightning.
          </l>
          <l>
            Advancing on the [one with] great effort // [they are scattered by him] like
                                    tufts of grass in the wind;
          </l>
          <l>
            [they act like they could] tear down a mountain with their fingernails //
                                    bite an iron pellet with their teeth;
          </l>
          <l>foolish children [trying] with lotus stalks // to suspend a great mountain.</l>
          <l>
            The Buddha has already crossed beyond all attachment // to desire to debate
                                    with him
          </l>
          <l>
            [is like wanting to] catch the wind with a net // like wanting to take down
                                    the moon from the sky,
          </l>
          <l>to scoop the ocean with one’s hands // hoping to dry it out.</l>
          <l>
            The Buddha has already left all attachment behind; // to desire to go and
                                    debate with him
          </l>
          <l>
            [is like] striding over Mount sumeru with one’s foot // looking for earth in
                                    the great ocean.
          </l>
          <l>
            The Buddha has already abandoned all attachment; // to go and debate with him
                                    […]
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>King Māra, sad and regretful, vanished and returned to his heavenly palace.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
