<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                              法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                    lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                    Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                    edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                    the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                                English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza002">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0374a19"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza002">
        <p n="bza002.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza002">
        <p n="bza002.02">爾時世尊與無<app n="fnT02p0374n09">
            <lem wit="【大】">央</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">殃</rdg>
          </app>央數大眾圍遶說法。當于爾時有一比丘，容色憔悴，無有威德，來詣佛所，頂禮佛足，叉手合掌向諸比丘，在一面坐。時諸比丘皆作是念：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza002.03">今此比丘何故如是顏容毀悴，無有威德？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza002.04">世尊爾時知諸比丘心之所念，即告之言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza002.05">汝──諸比丘！──見彼比丘禮我已不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza002.06">時諸比丘白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza002.07">世尊！唯然，已見。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza002.08">佛復告<app n="fnT02p0374n10">
            <lem wit="【大】">言</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">曰</rdg>
          </app>言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza002.09"> 汝等今者勿於彼所生下劣想。何以故？彼比丘者所作已辦，獲阿羅漢，捨於重擔，盡諸有結，得正解脫，而今汝等不應於彼<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0374b" n="0374b"/>生輕賤想。汝等若當知見如我，然後乃可籌量於彼。若妄稱量，則為自損。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza002.10">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza002.11" met="7" xml:id="cg002a">
            <l>孔雀雖以色嚴身<caesura/>不如鴻鵠能高飛</l>
            <l>外形雖有美<app n="fnT02p0374n11">
                <lem wit="【大】">儀容</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">容儀</rdg>
              </app>儀容<caesura/>未若斷漏功德尊</l>
            <l>今此比丘猶良馬<caesura/>能善調伏其心行</l>
            <l>斷欲滅結離生死<caesura/>受後邊身壞魔軍</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza002">
        <p n="bza002.12">佛說是已，諸比丘等聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
