<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza071">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0399a19"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza071">
        <p n="bza071.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza071">
        <p n="bza071.02">爾時<name type="person">波斯匿</name>王往詣佛所，稽首佛足，在一面坐。時<name type="place">祇洹</name>中有長髮梵志七人，復有裸形尼乾七人，復有一衣外道七人，身皆長大。波斯匿王見諸外道，在祇洹中經行彷徉。時波斯匿王從坐而起，合掌敬心，向諸外道，自說：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza071.03">我是波斯匿王。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza071.04">如是三說。佛告波斯匿王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza071.05">何故見此長髮裸形一衣之人，如此恭敬？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza071.06">王言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza071.07">世尊！我國有此三人，阿羅漢中，名為最勝。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza071.08">佛告王言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza071.09">汝不善知他心所趣，云何知是羅漢、非羅漢也？如共久處，用意觀察，爾乃<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0399b" n="0399b"/>可知持戒、破戒。雖復久處，聰智能知，愚者不知。若其父母，親里眷屬，有死亡者，可分別知。若無此事，難可了知。若遭厄難，為人<app n="fnT02p0399n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">強 逼</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">逼迫強</rdg>
            </app>強逼，令行殺害，或為女人，私處逼迫，而不犯戒，可知堅實。隨逐觀察，乃能可知淨行、不淨。欲試其智，聽其所說，唯有智者，善能分別。唯有智人，久處共住，爾乃可知。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza071.10">王即讚佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza071.11">善哉！世尊！如佛所說：久處共住，爾乃可知持戒、破戒。臨難別人，觀察其行，知淨、不淨。講說議論，乃別其智、凡。此上說有智能知，愚者不知。久處乃知，非可卒知。何以故？我所使人，亦使著如是形服，使遠至他國，察彼國中，或經八月，或至十月，作種種事已，還來歸國，五欲自恣。一切所作，如前無異。是以知佛所說，實是善說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza071.12">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza071.13" met="5" xml:id="cg071a">
            <l>不以見色貌<caesura/>而可觀察知</l>
            <l>若卒見人時<caesura/>不可即便信</l>
            <l>相貌似羅漢<caesura/>實不攝諸根</l>
            <l>形貌種種行<caesura/>都不可分別</l>
            <l>如似塗耳<app n="fnT02p0399n05">
                <lem wit="【大】">鐺</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">璫</rdg>
              </app>鐺<caesura/>亦復如塗錢</l>
            <l>愚者謂是金<caesura/>其內實是銅</l>
            <l>如是諸人等<caesura/>癡闇無所知</l>
            <l>外相似賢<app n="fnT02p0399n06">
                <lem wit="【大】">善</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">聖</rdg>
              </app>善<caesura/>內心實毒惡</l>
            <l>行時多將從<caesura/>表於賢勝者</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza071">
        <p n="bza071.14">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
