<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                      法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                            Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                            text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                            lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                            Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                            edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
            (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
            (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                            comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                            the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                            literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                        English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project is to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The texts are kept in single files in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any changes after 2008 see the revision
                          description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza035">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0384c11"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza035">
        <p n="bza035.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza035">
        <p n="bza035.02">爾時有一比丘，往到佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面立，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza035.03">世尊！云何名『<name type="person">帝釋</name>』？云何作『帝釋相』？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.04">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.05">帝釋本在人中，所有布施，生純信心。信心施於貧窮、沙門、婆羅門等。其所施時，施漿飲食，種種餚饍，種種華鬘，種種諸香，燒香、塗香、財帛、床榻。以是因緣，時諸天等名為『帝釋』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.06">比丘復白佛：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza035.07">何故名帝釋為『<name type="person">富蘭但那</name>』？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.08">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.09">帝釋昔在人中，施無厭足。數數施故，諸天號名為『富蘭但那』。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza035.10">以何因緣復名帝釋為『<name type="person">摩佉婆</name>』？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.11">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.12">帝釋本作婆羅門，名『摩佉婆』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.13">又問：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza035.14">復何因緣名『<name type="person">婆娑<app n="fnT02p0384n17">
                <lem wit="【大】">婆</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">妥</rdg>
              </app>婆</name>』？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.15">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.16">數數常以衣服施沙門、婆羅門。以是緣故，名『婆娑婆』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.17">又問：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza035.18">復何因緣名『<name type="person">憍尸迦</name>』？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.19">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.20">帝釋本為人時，姓憍尸迦，故名『憍尸迦』。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza035.21">復<app n="fnT02p0384n18">
              <lem wit="【大】">何因</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">以何</rdg>
            </app>何因緣名『<name type="person">舍脂夫</name>』？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.22">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.23">帝釋娶毘摩質多羅阿修羅王女，名<app n="fnT02p0384n19">
              <lem wit="【大】">舍脂</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">舍脂夫</rdg>
            </app>『舍脂夫』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.24">又問：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza035.25">復以何緣名<app n="fnT02p0384n20">
              <lem wit="【大】">為</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">一為</rdg>
            </app>為『<name type="person">千眼</name>』？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.26">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.27">帝釋本為人時，極大聰明。斷事之時，須臾之間能斷千事。以<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0385a" n="0385a"/>是因緣，故名『千眼』。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza035.28">復以何緣名『<name type="person">因陀羅</name>』？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.29">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.30">帝釋居天王位，斷理天事，故名『因陀羅』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza035.31">爾時世尊告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza035.32">能具上七事。以是緣故，諸天號曰『帝釋』。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza035">
        <p n="bza035.33">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
