<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>Sakka is patient in the face of insult</head>
        <p>Translation of BZA 039. First version published in <emph>
            Buddhist Studies
                                Review
          </emph>vol. 23-1 (2006).</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="bza039en" xml:lang="en">
      <div>
        <p>
          Thus have I heard, once, the Buddha was staying at Sāvatthī at the Jeta Grove in
                              the Anāthapiṇḍika Park.
        </p>
        <p>
          At that time the World-honored One told the monks: “Long time ago, Sakka Devānam
                              Indo was about to do battle with the asuras, when everything had been readied ,
                              he addressed the devas: ‘If we devas should attain victory, we will with five
                              bonds bind [the king of the] asuras, and bring him to our palace.’ The asura
                              [king] also ordered his host: ‘If we win, we also will with five bonds bind
                              Sakka Devānam Indo, and bring him to our palace.’
        </p>
        <p>
          At that time, the devas won, and they bound Vepacitti with five bonds and brought
                              him into their palace. When Vepacitti saw Sakka, he got angry and insulted him,
                              using extremely foul language. When Sakka heard these insults, he stayed silent,
                              did not react. His charioteer Mātali addressed him with a verse:
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>Sakka! Husband of Suja! Maghavā! // Are you afraid or weak?</l>
          <l>
            Vepacitti insults you to your face // how can you suffer this foul
                                language?
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>And Sakka answered with a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            It is not that I am afraid that I engender patience // neither is it that I
                                    am weak
          </l>
          <l>
            And therefore suffer Vepacitti’s insults // I have by victorious wisdom
                                    practiced patience
          </l>
          <l>
            The foolish of shallow knowledge, unwise // always argue and quarrel without
                                    end
          </l>
          <l>If I use force to chastise him // I am not different from this fool</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Again the charioteer said:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            If one loosens the bonds of the naïve and foolish // they will behave worse
                                    and worse 轉劇不休息
          </l>
          <l>
            [They are] like a cow that walks behind // [and suddenly] tries to charge
                                    over those in front of it
          </l>
          <l>A firm one will forcefully // restrain the foolish</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Again Sakka spoke a verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            I reckon in order to restrain the foolish // there is nothing better than
                                    patient silence
          </l>
          <l>
            At a time when someone is incensed by hatred and anger // he can only be
                                    restrained by patience
          </l>
          <l>What the foolish call strong // is not truly strong</l>
          <l>
            The foolish do not distinguish between good and bad // have no way to
                                    restrain [themselves]
          </l>
          <l>
            If I can find the courage in me // to patiently endure the foolish and
                                    inferior
          </l>
          <l>This is called foremost patience // and to be skillful in patience.</l>
          <l>The inferior person when facing someone strong // can not but practice it</l>
          <l>this is called timid patience // not true patience.</l>
          <l>Power gives the freedom // to counter those who insult [us]</l>
          <l>with silence, not reacting // this is the best [form of] patience.</l>
          <l>Weakness is afraid of power // it is silent [because] it cannot react</l>
          <l>this is called fear // not the practice of patience.</l>
          <l>The naïve and foolish without wisdom // afflict others by harming them,</l>
          <l>seeing the other’s silent patience // they believe they are victorious.</l>
          <l>A wise and saintly person // takes patience to be the best [way to behave].</l>
          <l>
            Thus among the saintly // the meritorious power of patience is always
                                    praised.
          </l>
          <l>
            It diminishes for oneself and also for others // eradicates many hindrances
                                    and fears.
          </l>
          <l>
            Seeing the other full of hatred and anger // but being able to practice
                                    silent patience,
          </l>
          <l>
            the other’s hatred will vanish naturally // no need for the strength of blade
                                    and cudgel.
          </l>
          <l>For the great benefit of both // benefiting oneself and benefiting others.</l>
          <l>
            What the foolish deem patience because of fear // is praised by the wise and
                                    saintly.
          </l>
          <l>
            We are patient with those superior to us // because we are afraid of being
                                    harmed.
          </l>
          <l>When struggling with equals // one too is patient, because one fear’s harm.</l>
          <l>
            To be able to be patient with people inferior to us // is the best form of
                                    patience.
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          The Buddha told the monks: “Sakka in the heaven of the thirty-three in freely
                              exercising his rulership, if he can practice and praise patience, how much more
                              should you, oh monks, who have abandoned form and entered the teaching, how much
                              more should you practice and praise patience. Practicing and praising patience
                              is the manner of [those having gone forth into] homelessness.
        </p>
        <p>
          When the Buddha had finished, the monks, having listened to what he had said,
                              were happy and practiced accordingly.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
