<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                      法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                            Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                            text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                            lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                            Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                            edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
            (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
            (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                            comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                            the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                            literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                        English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project is to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The texts are kept in single files in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any changes after 2008 see the revision
                          description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza036">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0385a06"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza036">
        <p n="bza036.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza036">
        <p n="bza036.02">爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza036.03">昔所有一夜叉，形狀甚小，顏色鄙惡，身形又黑，人不喜見，坐<name type="person">帝釋</name>座上。爾時<name type="person">三十三天</name>見是夜叉，坐於釋處，皆大瞋忿，種種毀罵。爾時夜叉惡相漸滅，善色轉生，漸漸長大。諸天罵詈，瞋恚轉多，夜叉遂復身形長大，顏色鮮盛。諸天相將至帝釋所，白帝釋言：<q who="devatavatimsa">有一夜叉，極為醜陋，身形甚小，坐帝釋<app n="fnT02p0385n02">
                <lem wit="【大】">處</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">座</rdg>
              </app>處。我等諸天盡共罵詈，而夜叉子顏色轉好，身形漸大！</q>
                    帝釋語言：
                    <q who="sakko">有是夜叉，得諸罵詈，形色轉好，名助人瞋。</q>爾時帝釋還向坐所，偏袒右肩，手擎香<app n="fnT02p0385n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">爐</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">罏</rdg>
            </app>爐，語夜<app n="fnT02p0385n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">又</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">叉</rdg>
            </app>又言：
                    <q who="sakko">大仙！我是帝釋。我是帝釋。</q>三自稱名，夜叉轉小，形色轉惡，於是消滅。帝釋還<app n="fnT02p0385n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">復</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">復坐</rdg>
            </app>復帝釋坐，告諸天言：
                    <q who="sakko">自今以往，莫生瞋恚。若有惡對，慎莫加瞋。</q>即說偈言：<q who="sakko">
              <lg n="bza036.04" met="5" xml:id="cg036a">
                <l>若他來侵欺<caesura/>莫還侵欺彼</l>
                <l>於來侵害者<caesura/>皆生於慈心</l>
                <l>無瞋無害者<caesura/>常應親近之</l>
                <l>彼即是賢聖<caesura/>亦賢聖弟子</l>
                <l>諸有瞋恚者<caesura/>為瞋山所障</l>
                <l>若有瞋恚時<caesura/>能少禁制者</l>
                <l>是名為善法<caesura/>如轡制惡馬</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza036.05">佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza036.06">帝釋居天王位，受諸欲樂，猶能制瞋，又常讚嘆，禁制瞋者，況汝比丘信家非<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0385b" n="0385b"/>家，出家入道，剃除鬚髮，被服法衣，而不制瞋，讚離瞋者。是故──比丘！──當<app n="fnT02p0385n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">如</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">作</rdg>
            </app>如是學。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza036">
        <p n="bza036.07">爾時比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
