<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza072">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0399b28"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza072">
        <p n="bza072.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza072">
        <p n="bza072.02">爾時有五國王，共集一處，各相謂言：</p>
        <q who="rajano">
          <p n="bza072.03">五<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0399c" n="0399c"/>欲之中，何者最妙？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.04">一王說曰：</p>
        <q who="ekacca">
          <p n="bza072.05">色為第一。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.06">次王說言：</p>
        <q who="ekacca">
          <p n="bza072.07">聲為第一。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.08">次王說言：</p>
        <q who="ekacca">
          <p n="bza072.09">味為第一。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.10">第四王言：</p>
        <q who="ekacca">
          <p n="bza072.11">香為第一。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.12">第五王言：</p>
        <q who="ekacca">
          <p n="bza072.13">細滑第一。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.14">諸王心意，人各不同，各見第一，乃相謂言：</p>
        <q who="rajano">
          <p n="bza072.15">我等心意，所美不同，各競其理。可詣佛所，稟受分別。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.16">
          <name type="person">波斯匿</name>王而為上首，共詣佛所。五王爾時禮佛足已，在一面立，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza072.17">世尊！我等五王私共議論：<q who="panca rajano">五欲之中，何者第一？</q>一王說言：<q who="ekacca">色為第一。</q>如此五王，所說不同，各稱第一。所<app n="fnT02p0399n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">說</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">謂</rdg>
            </app>說不同故，來詣佛所，<app n="fnT02p0399n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">諮</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【聖】"/>
            </app>諮問斯義，何者第一？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.18">佛說：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza072.19">若於色中取其像貌，心意封著，稱適其意。當於爾時設有妙色勝於此者，但以所著為勝，不顧色妙。聲、香、味、觸，亦復如是。……（乃至）於觸受其相貌，心意計著，以為最勝。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.20">爾時有一婆羅門，名曰<name type="person">卑嶷</name>，即從坐起，偏袒右肩，右膝著地，合掌向佛，白言：</p>
        <q who="akkosakabharadvajo">
          <p n="bza072.21">世尊！欲有所說，唯願聽許！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.22">佛告卑嶷：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza072.23">宜知是時。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.24">卑嶷即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="akkosakabharadvajo">
          <lg n="bza072.25" met="7" xml:id="cg072a">
            <l>央伽大王畜寶鎧<caesura/>摩竭提主得大利</l>
            <l>佛出其國最上寶<caesura/>名稱普聞如山王</l>
            <l>譬如蓮華新敷榮<caesura/>光映泉池香遍至</l>
            <l>佛亦如日處虛空<caesura/>光明周普照世界</l>
            <l>諦視如來智慧力<caesura/>猶如猛火炎熾盛</l>
            <l>開諸眼目作大明<caesura/>諸有疑惑來稟化</l>
            <l>一切悉得決所疑</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.26">五王皆讚美<app n="fnT02p0399n10">
            <lem wit="【大】">偈訖</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">說竭</rdg>
          </app>偈訖，各以上衣以用賞之。爾時五王聞佛所說，皆大歡喜，從坐而去。王去已後，卑嶷合掌向佛，即以五衣奉上於佛：</p>
        <q who="akkosakabharadvajo">
          <p n="bza072.27">唯願納受！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza072.28">佛即納受。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza072">
        <p n="bza072.29">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
