<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                      法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                            Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                            text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                            lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                            Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                            edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
            (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
            (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                            comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                            the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                            literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                        English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project is to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The texts are kept in single files in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any changes after 2008 see the revision
                          description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza044">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0388a29"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza044">
        <p n="bza044.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0388b" n="0388b"/>獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza044">
        <p n="bza044.02">爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza044.03">往昔之時遠於聚落、阿練若處多有諸仙，在中而住。離仙處不遠有天、阿脩羅而共戰鬪。爾時<name type="person">毘摩質多羅</name>阿脩羅王著五種容飾：首戴天冠，捉摩尼拂，上戴華蓋，帶於寶劍，眾寶革屣，到仙人住處，行不由門，從壁而入，亦復不與諸<app n="fnT02p0388n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">仙</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">仙人</rdg>
            </app>仙言語，共相問訊，還從壁出。爾時有一仙人，而作是語：<q who="isi">毘摩質多羅等無恭敬心，不與諸仙問訊共語，從壁而出。</q>復有一仙，而作是言：<q who="isi">阿脩羅等若當恭敬，問訊諸仙，應勝諸天。今必不如！</q>有一仙問言：<q who="isi">此為是誰？</q>有一仙言：<q who="isi">此是毘摩質多阿脩羅王。</q>仙人復言：<q who="isi">阿脩羅法知見微淺，無有法教，無尊敬心，猶如農夫。諸天必勝，阿脩羅負！</q>爾時<name type="person">帝釋</name>後到仙邊，即捨天王五種容飾，從門而入，慰勞諸仙，遍往觀察，語諸仙言：<q who="sakko">盡各安隱，無諸惱耶？</q>問訊已訖，從門而出。復有一仙問言：<q who="isi">此為是誰？安慰問訊，周遍察行，然後乃出。甚有法教，容儀端正。</q>一仙答言：<q who="isi">此是帝釋。</q>有一仙言：<q who="isi">諸天極能敬順，為行調<app n="fnT02p0388n04">
                <lem wit="【大】">適</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">伏</rdg>
              </app>適。諸天必勝，阿脩羅負！</q>毘摩質多羅聞諸仙讚嘆諸天，毀呰阿脩羅，甚大瞋恚。諸仙聞已，往詣阿脩羅所語言：<q who="isayo">我等聞爾，甚大瞋忿！</q>即說偈言：<q who="isayo">
              <lg n="bza044.04" met="5" xml:id="cg044a">
                <l>我等故自來<caesura/>欲乞索所願</l>
                <l>施我等無畏<caesura/>莫復生瞋忿</l>
                <l>我等若有過<caesura/>願教責數我</l>
              </lg>
            </q>                    　　　
                    毘摩質多以偈答言：<q who="vepacitti">
              <lg n="bza044.05" met="5" xml:id="cg044b">
                <l>不施汝無畏<caesura/>汝等侵毀我</l>
                <l>卑遜求帝釋<caesura/>於我生毀呰</l>
                <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0388c" n="0388c"/>
                <l>汝等求無畏<caesura/>我當與汝畏</l>
              </lg>
            </q>爾時諸仙以偈答言：<q who="isayo">
              <lg n="bza044.06" met="5" xml:id="cg044c">
                <l>如人自造作<caesura/>自獲於果報</l>
                <l>行善自獲善<caesura/>行惡惡自報</l>
                <l>譬如下種子<caesura/>隨種得果報</l>
                <l>汝今種苦子<caesura/>後必還自受</l>
                <l>我今乞無畏<caesura/>逆與我怖畏</l>
                <l>從今日已往<caesura/>使<app n="fnT02p0388n05">
                    <lem wit="【大】">汝</lem>
                    <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">我</rdg>
                  </app>汝畏無盡</l>
              </lg>
            </q> 諸仙面與阿脩羅<app n="fnT02p0388n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">語</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">論</rdg>
            </app>語已，即乘虛去。毘摩質多羅即於其夜夢與帝釋交兵共戰，生大驚怕。第二亦爾。第三夢時，帝釋軍眾果來求戰。時毘摩質多即共交兵。阿脩羅敗，帝釋逐<app n="fnT02p0388n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">進</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">退</rdg>
            </app>進，至阿脩羅宮。爾時帝釋種種戰諍，既得勝已，詣諸仙所。諸仙在東，帝釋在西，相對而坐。時有東風，仙人向帝釋即說偈言：
                    <q who="isi">
              <lg n="bza044.07" met="5" xml:id="cg044d">
                <l>我身久出家<caesura/>腋下有臭氣</l>
                <l>風吹向汝去<caesura/>移避就南坐</l>
                <l>如此諸臭氣<caesura/>諸天所不喜</l>
              </lg>
            </q>   
                    爾時帝釋以偈答言：<q who="sakko">
              <lg n="bza044.08" met="5" xml:id="cg044e">
                <l>集聚種種華<caesura/>以為首上鬘</l>
                <l>香氣若干種<caesura/>能不生厭離</l>
                <l>諸仙人出家<caesura/>氣如諸華鬘</l>
                <l>我今頂戴受<caesura/>不以為厭患</l>
              </lg>
            </q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza044.09">佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza044.10">帝釋居天王位，長夜恭敬諸出家者。汝諸比丘以信出家，亦應當作如是欽敬。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza044">
        <p n="bza044.11">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
