<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>Two monks argue. The Buddha reminds them of how Sakka deals with anger</head>
        <p>Translation of BZA 037. First version published in <emph>
            Buddhist Studies
                                Review
          </emph>vol. 23-1 (2006).</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="bza037en" xml:lang="en">
      <div>
        <p>
          Thus have I heard, once, the Buddha was staying at Sāvatthī at the Jeta Grove in
                              the Anāthapiṇḍika Park.
        </p>
        <p>
          At that time one early morning the World-honored One took his robes and the
                              begging bowl and entered the town to beg for food. Having eaten he washed his
                              feet, gathered his seat [for meditation] and went to the Andhavana forest [to
                              meditate]. Having looked around probing [for a good spot], he sat down
                              cross-legged beneath a tree in a secluded place, and abided in meditation.
        </p>
        <p>
          At that time in the Jeta Vihāra there were two monks who got into an argument
                              during a meeting. One endured in silence, the other was incensed with anger.
                              When the one who had become incensed, saw that he had transgressed, he went to
                              the monk who had stayed silent and wanted to confess. The monk who had endured
                              in silence [however] did not accept the confession. When this transpired there
                              ensued a noisy discussion among the monks. The Tathāgata was at that time
                              abiding in meditation, and heard [the clamor] clearly with his deva-like
                              hearing, which surpasses human hearing and can discern sounds from far away. He
                              rose from his seat, and went among the monk, took place on the seat prepared in
                              front of them. The Buddha said to the monks: “This morning I took my robes and
                              begging bowl and entered the town to beg for food. (…etc…) went into the forest,
                              and sitting silently, I heard the monks shouting and clamoring. What is the
                              matter?”
        </p>
        <p>
          There the monks told the Buddha: “World-honored One, in the Jeta Vihāra there are
                              two monks, who got into an argument during a meeting. One monk endured?? in
                              silence, the other monk was incensed and said a lot. The incensed monk knew that
                              he had transgressed and went [to offer a] honest confession. The monk that had
                              endured silently did not accept the others confession, so it became a public
                              issue and everybody started shouting.”
        </p>
        <p>
          The Buddha told the monks: “Why be so stupid and not accept someone’s confession?
                              Oh monks, know that [once] in ancient days Sakka the ruler of the gods was among
                              the gods in the Sudhammā Hall and spoke this verse:
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            If for instance one uses a cup of dried gourd // fills it with butter to have
                                    a lamp
          </l>
          <l>The fire burning, consuming // will burn the gourd as well</l>
          <l>The angry mind is like this // it turns on itself and burns one’s good roots</l>
          <l>I am never furious // if anger arises I quickly disperse it</l>
          <l>No more like drawn into a maelstrom // endlessly circling around</l>
          <l>
            Though there is anger I do not speak harshly // do not mention what others
                                    do not want to speak about
          </l>
          <l>
            deeply respect what others do not want to speak about // I am always without
                                    violence
          </l>
          <l>Taking control over my body // has been of great advantage to me</l>
          <l>Those without anger, without violence // those are nobles</l>
          <l>And the disciples of nobles // those one always should befriend</l>
          <l>Those with anger and hatred // face an obstacle heavy as a mountain</l>
          <l>If one at a time of anger and hate // can control oneself even a little</l>
          <l>This I call well-done // like the taming of a wicked horse</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          Buddha said to the monks: “Sakka the ruler of the gods, reigns over the gods. At
                              ease among them, still he can practice patience and praise those with patience.
                              How could you, oh monk, who went forth, disfigured [by cutting of your hair] ,
                              not be patient and praise patience.”
        </p>
        <p>
          When the Buddha had finished, the monks, having listened to what he had said,
                              were happy and practised accordingly.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
