<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                      法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                            Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                            text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                            lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                            Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                            edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
            (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
            (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                            comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                            the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                            literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                        English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project is to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The texts are kept in single files in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any changes after 2008 see the revision
                          description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza048">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0389b29"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza048">
        <p n="bza048.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0389c" n="0389c"/>獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza048">
        <p n="bza048.02">爾時<name type="person">帝釋</name>來詣佛所，將欲還時請受一戒。何謂一戒？若我還宮，見諸怨憎，設來害我，我於彼所終不加害。<name type="person">毘摩質多羅</name>既聞帝釋持如是戒，便捉利劍，於路而待。時<name type="person">釋提桓因</name>
            聞阿脩羅在於路側，捉劍而待，
                                遙語阿脩羅言：
          </p>
        <q who="sakko">
          <p n="bza048.03">止！止！汝今自縛！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.04">毘摩質多語帝釋言：</p>
        <q who="vepacitti">
          <p n="bza048.05">汝於佛所受一戒言：<q who="sakko">若我還宮，見諸怨憎，設彼害我，我於彼所終不加惡。</q>豈可不受如是戒耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.06">帝釋答言：</p>
        <q who="sakko">
          <p n="bza048.07">我雖受戒，語汝：<q who="sakko ">住！住！汝今自縛！</q>如是之言，於戒無犯。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.08">毘摩質多羅言：</p>
        <q who="vepacitti">
          <p n="bza048.09">
            <name type="person">憍尸迦</name>！放我！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.10">帝釋語言：</p>
        <q who="sakko">
          <p n="bza048.11">汝作呪誓──更於我所不為怨疾──，我當放汝。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.12">毘摩質多羅即說誓言：</p>
        <q who="vepacitti">
          <lg n="bza048.13" met="7" xml:id="cg048a">
            <l>貪瞋妄語謗賢聖<caesura/>如是惡報使我得</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.14">爾時帝釋聞斯誓已，即語毘摩質多羅言：</p>
        <q who="sakko">
          <p n="bza048.15">我今放汝。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.16">釋提桓因還至佛所，頂禮佛足，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="sakko">
          <p n="bza048.17"> 世尊！毘摩質多羅聞我受戒，即捉利劍，在於路側，伺圖於我。時我遙語阿脩羅言：<q who="sakko ">止！止！汝今自縛！</q>毘摩質多即語我言：<q who="vepacitti">汝於佛所受於一戒：<q who="sakko">若我還宮，見有怨憎，設來害我，我於彼所終不加惡。</q>豈可不受如是戒耶？</q>
                                我即答言：<q who="sakko">我雖受戒，但語汝：<q who="sakko">住！汝今自縛！</q>如是之言，於戒無犯。</q>
                    毘摩質多羅即語我言：<q who="vepacitti">憍尸迦！放我！</q>我即語言：<q who="sakko">汝可重誓──更於我所莫生憎<app n="fnT02p0389n09">
                <lem wit="【大】">疾</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嫉</rdg>
              </app>疾──，我當放汝。</q>時毘摩質多羅聞我語已，即說誓言：
                    <q who="vepacitti">
              <lg n="bza048.18" met="7" xml:id="cg048b">
                <l>貪瞋妄語謗賢聖<caesura/>如是惡報使我得</l>
              </lg>
            </q>我聞其誓，即放令去。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.19">帝釋復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="sakko">
          <p n="bza048.20">此阿脩羅作重誓已，從今已後更不作於怨憎惡耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza048.21">佛告帝釋：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza048.22">阿脩羅設不作誓，猶不為惡，況作<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0390a" n="0390a"/>誓已。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza048">
        <p n="bza048.23">爾時帝釋聞佛所說，踊躍歡喜，即於坐沒，尋還天宮</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
