<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>Māra plays the Vīṇā -- Godhika</head>
        <p>Translation of BZA 030. First version published in <emph>
            Buddhist Studies
                                Review
          </emph>vol. 23-1 (2006).</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="bza030en" xml:lang="en">
      <div>
        <p>
          Thus have I heard, once, the Buddha was staying near rājagaha on vebhāra Mountain
                              in the sattapaṇṇiguhā cave. at that time, there was a monk called godhika who
                              lived alone in a cave on isigili mountain at the Black rock. Living in the
                              wilderness, he made diligent efforts,and through his tenacity cut through the
                              view of self and attained temporary liberation, bearing witness [to the truth]
                              within his own body. Then he regressed and lost it. [This happened] a second
                              time, a third time … altogether six times. always he regressed. Then the monk
                              thought: ‘now, living alone and making diligent efforts, I have regressed six
                              times. if I regress again, I will kill myself with a blade’.
        </p>
        <p>
          King Māra the Bad knew that Buddha was staying near rājagaha on gijjhakūṭa
                              mountain in the sattapaṇṇiguhā cave. he also knew that a disciple of gotama
                              called godhika was also staying near rājagaha, on isigili mountain at the Black
                              rock. There, making diligent efforts with tenacious mind, godhika had reached
                              temporary liberation, had witnessed [the truth] with his own body, but after
                              each of the six attainments had regressed again. at that time King Māra had this
                              thought: ‘When the monk godhika attains [temporary liberation] a seventh time,
                              he will certainly kill himself, and leave the world of Māra’.
        </p>
        <p>
          Having thought thus, he took his lapis lazuli lute and went before the Buddha.
                              Plucking his lute he made this verse:
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            You endowed with great wisdom and great strength // with great magical
                                    powers,
          </l>
          <l>
            having attained freedom in the Dhamma // your majestic radiance shines
                                    brightly.
          </l>
          <l>Now your Sāvaka disciple // wishes to kill himself.</l>
          <l>You, best among men // should restrain him.</l>
          <l>
            how could he who rejoices in your teaching // die while still learning
                                it?
          </l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          When King Māra had spoken this verse, the Buddha said to him: ‘Bad One, you have
                              always been a great friend of the slothful. What you said now you spoke for your
                              own sake, not for the sake of that monk’.
        </p>
        <p>At that time the World-honoured One spoke this verse:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>If one is not easily frightened // [and] persistently practises diligently,</l>
          <l>one can always enjoy meditation // [and] day and night practise the good.</l>
          <l>
            [godhika] has ended the propensity towards of lust and desire // [and]
                                    defeated your armies.
          </l>
          <l>[he] has now cast off his final body // [and] entered Nirvāṇa forever.</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          There King Māra became sad and dispirited, dropped his lapis lazuli lute and
                              melancolicly and regretfully returned to his palaces.
        </p>
        <p>
          The Buddha ordered the monks to [follow him to] godhika’s place at isigili.
                              [There] they saw something like smoke gathering to the east of godhika’s corpse.
                              The Buddha said to the monks: ‘Do you see the smoke gathering?’. The monks said:
                              ‘Yes, World-honoured One, we see it’. [Then the smoke] gathered likewise towards
                              the south, the west and the north [of godhika’s body]. The Buddha said to the
                              monks: ‘This is the Bad One; his form is hidden and he is surrounding godhika
                              looking for his consciousness’. The Buddha said to the monks: ‘The monk
                              godhika has entered Nirvāṇa; there is no consciousness [to be found]; there is
                              no destination’. At that time, King Māra changed into a young man and spoke this
                              verse:
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>
            Above and below and in the four directions // I have searched for godhika’s
                                    consciousness.
          </l>
          <l>Does no one know his destination // where his consciousness abides?</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          At that time the Buddha said to the Bad One: ‘Thus the wise and steadfast one has
                              vanquished your armies and entered Nirvāṇa’.
        </p>
        <p>
          When the Buddha had finished, the monks, having listened to what he had said,
                              were happy and practised accordingly.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
