<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza059">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0393c12"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza059">
        <p n="bza059.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza059">
        <p n="bza059.02">爾時<name type="person">波斯匿</name>王往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza059.03">世尊！有一長者，名<name type="person">摩訶南</name>。其家巨富，多饒財寶。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza059.04">佛問王曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza059.05">云何大富？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza059.06">王<app n="fnT02p0393n12">
            <lem wit="【大】">白</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">曰</rdg>
          </app>白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza059.07">彼長者家，金、銀、珍寶，數千萬億，不可稱量，況復餘財。雖有財富，不能<app n="fnT02p0393n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">飲</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">餘</rdg>
            </app>飲食。所可食者，雜糠麁澁。若作羹時，渾煮<app n="fnT02p0393n14">
              <lem wit="【大】">薑</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">薑一</rdg>
            </app>薑罷。煮已，<app n="fnT02p0393n15">
              <lem wit="【大】">還</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">業</rdg>
            </app>還取賣為財用。所可衣者，唯著麁布，五總<app n="fnT02p0393n16">
              <lem wit="【大】">踈</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">䟽</rdg>
            </app>踈弊以為內衣。乘朽故車，連綴樹葉以為<app n="fnT02p0393n17">
              <lem wit="【大】">繖</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">傘</rdg>
            </app>繖蓋。未曾見其施沙門、婆羅門、貧窮、乞兒。若欲食時，要先閉門，恐諸沙門、婆羅門等來從其乞。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza059.08">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza059.09">大王！如此之人，非善丈夫。何以故？得斯財富，不能開意，正直受樂，又復不能孝養，供給妻子，亦不賜與奴婢、僕使，又不時時施諸沙門、婆羅門，亦復不求上業，生天之報。譬如鹵地，有少汪水，以鹹苦故，無能飲者，乃至竭盡。世間愚夫亦復如是，大得財業，不能施用，身自受樂，亦復<app n="fnT02p0393n18">
              <lem wit="【大】">末</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">未</rdg>
            </app>末能供<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0394a" n="0394a"/>養父母及與妻子并其眷屬──奴婢、僕使。親友、知識，悉不惠與。雖豐財寶，都無利益。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza059.10">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza059.11">大王！善丈夫者，得於財業，能自施用，正直受樂，亦能供養師長、父母及與妻子并其眷屬──奴婢、僕使。親友、知識，……（乃至）供養沙門、婆羅門、貧窮、乞匃，悉能惠施。如斯善人，所得財寶，名為上<app n="fnT02p0394n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">業</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">還</rdg>
            </app>業。作快樂因，生天之緣。此人聚財，成就大善。譬如近城、村邑、聚落，有清冷池，流出好水，四邊平正，多饒林樹，種種華果，有柔軟草，遍布其地。一切眾人，皆得洗浴并獲好飲。飛禽走獸，翱翔嬉樂。善健丈夫亦復如是，……（乃至）生天，成就大善。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza059.12">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza059.13" met="5" xml:id="cg059a">
            <l>譬如鹹鹵土<caesura/>中有冷汪水</l>
            <l>鹹苦不可飲<caesura/>後自煎涸盡</l>
            <l>儜夫亦復爾<caesura/>雖有多財寶</l>
            <l>不能自衣食<caesura/>亦不施他人</l>
            <l>是名為儜者<caesura/>有財能布施</l>
            <l>譬如平博地<caesura/>有好清流池</l>
            <l>林亦甚蔚茂<caesura/>人獸同快樂</l>
            <l>是名為智者<caesura/>如似大牛王</l>
            <l>生則受快樂<caesura/>死則生天上</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza059">
        <p n="bza059.14">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
