<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                          法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                            English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project was funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project was to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. In the original interface, the texts were kept in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasted from 2005-2009.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>Value added:</p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Markup of person and place names.</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA marked. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan &amp; others: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Markup of person and place names. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <div>
        <head>Sakka pays obeisance to the Buddha 2</head>
        <p>Translation of BZA 041. First version published in <emph>
            Buddhist Studies
                                Review
          </emph>vol. 23-1 (2006).</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body xml:id="bza041en" xml:lang="en">
      <div>
        <p>
          Thus have I heard, once, the Buddha was staying at Sāvatthī at the Jeta Grove in
                              the Anāthapiṇḍika Park.
        </p>
        <p>
          At that time the World-Honored One told the bhikkhus: “Long time ago Sakka
                              Devānam Indo wanted to go for a ride and enjoy his park land. He ordered his
                              charioteer Mātali: ‘Harness the thousand-horse chariot!’ Soon Mātali had
                              harnessed the chariot, went to Sakka, and said to him: ‘The chariot is ready, we
                              may leave whenever you please.’ Thereupon Sakka left the Vejayanta Palace and
                              with folded hands paid obeisance facing south. When Mātali saw this, his mind
                              was filled with surprise and fear, and he dropped whip and reigns.
        </p>
        <p>
          Sakka said: ‘What have you seen that you are so scared?’ Mātali said: ‘Maghavā!
                              Husband of Suja! When I saw you with folded hands paying obeisance facing south,
                              my mind became filled with fear and I dropped whip and reigns. All beings revere
                              you; all the kings are completely under your rule. The four [Guardian] kings and
                              the thirty-three gods, all respectfully revere you. Who then surpasses you in
                              power, that you stand and pay obeisance with folded hands facing south?’ Sakka
                              answered: ‘Everybody reveres me, that might indeed be as you say. [However,]
                              what all devas and human beings respectfully venerate is the Dhamma. I
                              respectfully pay obeisance to the perfect discipline and Dhamma.’ And Sakka
                              spoke a verse:
        </p>
        <lg>
          <l>Those who have left home // and practice relentlessly</l>
          <l>
            To enter silent meditation during the long night, // who lead the holy life
                                    perfectly
          </l>
          <l>They abandon the three poisons // can attain the Dhamma of liberation</l>
          <l>To this Dhamma // I pay obeisance</l>
          <l>To all great Arhants // who have abandoned desire</l>
          <l>Dispelled the darkness of ignorance // have cut off all fetters</l>
          <l>As well as to those lay-people who practice good // do not do evil actions</l>
          <l>To all followers of the correct Dhamma // I pay obeisance</l>
        </lg>
        <p>Mātali said:</p>
        <lg>
          <l>You are venerating the very best // I will follow you in worship</l>
        </lg>
        <p>
          When Sakka had spoken thus, he paid obeisance with folded hands, mounted the
                              chariot and went.
        </p>
        <p>
          The Buddha told the monks: “Sakka is powerful among men and devas, if even he
                              does pay obeisance to the Dhamma, how much more should you, oh monks, who have
                              cut off your hair, left home to study the way, how much more diligent should you
                              be in paying obeisance to the Dhamma.”
        </p>
        <p>
          When the Buddha had finished, the monks, having listened to what he had said,
                              were happy and practiced accordingly.
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
