<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza068">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0397b03"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza068">
        <p n="bza068.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza068">
        <p n="bza068.02">爾時<name type="person">波斯匿</name>王往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza068.03">世尊！布施之時，應與何處？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.04">佛答王曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza068.05">修布施者，隨意所樂，布施於彼。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.06">王復問佛：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza068.07">布施何處，得大果報？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.08">佛答王曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza068.09">
                            汝問異前。我今問汝，隨汝意答。如出軍陣，欲鬪戰時，如東方有剎利，盛壯有力，然其不能善解兵法，亦復不知善調其身及以射術，畏憚前敵，生于驚懼。每常先退，不能住其所止之處。射箭不遠，設復射箭，終無所中，不堪處彼大陣之中。大王！若鬪戰時，有如此人，王當安慰：<q who="pasenadi">汝親近我，當重賞賜！</q>王能爾不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.10">王言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza068.11">世尊！我實不用如是之人。何以故？鬪戰之時，所不須故。</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza068.12">南方有婆羅門，西方有毘舍，北方有首陀，亦復如是。如此人等，王當用不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.13">王言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza068.14">若鬪戰時，皆所不用。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.15">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza068.16"> 若鬪戰時，東方有剎利來，年在盛壯，身體<app n="fnT02p0397n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">丁</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">長</rdg>
            </app>丁大，驍勇有力，善解兵法，兼知射術，種種諸術，多諸手<app n="fnT02p0397n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">伎</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">技</rdg>
            </app>伎，善能調身，勇於向敵，大膽不懼，心無驚畏，見敵不退，住所<app n="fnT02p0397n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">住</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">往</rdg>
            </app>住處，彎弓遠射，能中於物，箭不虛發，勇<app n="fnT02p0397n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">捍</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">悍</rdg>
            </app>捍直進，能壞大陣。大王！若鬪戰時，當用何者？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.17">王答佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza068.18">用勇健者。何以故？鬪戰之法，須勇健故。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.19">南、西、北方，亦復如是。佛告大王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza068.20">如是，大王！若有沙門、婆羅門，五支不具，不任福田。復有五支滿足，堪任福田。施得大果，得大利益，極為熾盛，果報增廣。云何名為具於五支？斷除五蓋。云斷除五蓋何？斷除<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0397c" n="0397c"/>欲蓋，瞋恚、睡眠、<app n="fnT02p0397n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">調</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">掉</rdg>
            </app>調悔及疑。自知除五欲，名斷除五蓋。云何滿足五支？滿足無學：戒、定、慧、解脫、解脫知見。若能滿足如是五支，沙門、婆羅門施得大果，名大熾然，果報深廣。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza068.21">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza068.22" met="5" xml:id="cg068a">
            <l>譬如有一人<caesura/>驍勇有大力</l>
            <l>兼善解射術<caesura/>眾<app n="fnT02p0397n11">
                <lem wit="【大】">技</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【聖】">伎</rdg>
              </app>技悉備知</l>
            <l>鬪戰須此人<caesura/>當厚賜財寶</l>
            <l>并與其爵賞<caesura/>不擇其種姓</l>
            <l>但錄其功勳<caesura/>大王應如是</l>
            <l>若能行善者<caesura/>柔和修忍辱</l>
            <l>能見四真諦<caesura/>得入於聖位</l>
            <l>供養黠慧者<caesura/>不應擇種姓</l>
            <l>住處悉應有<caesura/>飲食并臥具</l>
            <l>如此之供養<caesura/>應有具戒者</l>
            <l>於大洪流中<caesura/>應作浮囊栰</l>
            <l>并造作橋船<caesura/>自渡亦濟他</l>
            <l>安<app n="fnT02p0397n12">
                <lem wit="【大】">直</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">置</rdg>
              </app>直多聞者<caesura/>譬如有密雲</l>
            <l>遍覆於世界<caesura/>電光甚赫曜</l>
            <l>雷音聲遠震<caesura/>降注于大雨</l>
            <l>土地普沾洽<caesura/>眾卉木叢林</l>
            <l>無不蒙潤者<caesura/>禾稼既滋茂</l>
            <l>農夫生悅慶<caesura/>如是信施主</l>
            <l>多聞能惠施<caesura/>無有慳嫉者</l>
            <l>潤澤喻飲食<caesura/>勸讓益進與</l>
            <l>如雷音遠震<caesura/>譬如降注雨</l>
            <l>大獲於子實<caesura/>能修布施者</l>
            <l>大獲於功德<caesura/>後得涅槃樂</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza068">
        <p n="bza068.23">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
