<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza053">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0391c02"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza053">
        <p n="bza053.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">俱薩羅國</name>漸次遊行，至<name type="place">舍衛城</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza053">
        <p n="bza053.02">時<name type="person">波斯匿</name>王聞佛來至舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園，往詣佛所，稽首問訊，在一面坐，而白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza053.03">世尊！我昔聞爾出家求道，要成無上至真等正覺。汝為實有如是語耶，將非他人謬傳者乎？為是譏嫌，致於毀呰，作此語也？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza053.04">佛告波斯匿言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza053.05">如此語者，是真實語，非為毀呰，亦非增減。實是我語，實如法說，非非法說。一切外人，亦無有能譏嫌我者。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza053.06">波斯匿王復作是言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza053.07">我雖聞爾有如此語，猶未能信。何故不信？自昔諸人有久出家，耆老宿舊諸婆羅門──<name type="person">富蘭那迦葉</name>、<name type="person">末伽梨俱賒梨子</name>、<name type="person">刪闍耶毘羅<app n="fnT02p0391n06">
                <lem wit="【大】">邸</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">胝</rdg>
              </app>邸子</name>、<name type="person">阿闍多翅舍欽婆羅</name>、<name type="person">迦據多迦栴延</name>、<name type="person">尼乾陀闍提弗多羅</name>，彼諸宿舊尚自不信得阿耨多羅三藐三菩提，況汝年少，而出家未久，而當得乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza053.08">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza053.09"> 大王！世有四事小，不可輕。何者為四？一者、王<app n="fnT02p0391n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">子</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>子雖小，最不可輕。二、龍子雖小，亦不可輕。三、火雖小，亦不可輕。四、比丘雖小，亦不可輕。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza053.10">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza053.11" met="5" xml:id="cg053a">
            <l>王者雖為小<caesura/>具習諸技藝</l>
            <l>生處既真正<caesura/>亦不雜鄙穢</l>
            <l>有大美名稱<caesura/>一切悉聞知</l>
            <l>如此雖言小<caesura/>其實不可輕</l>
            <l>欲護己命者<caesura/>不應輕於小</l>
            <l>剎利雖云小<caesura/>法應紹王位</l>
            <l>既紹王位已<caesura/>法當行謫罰</l>
            <l>是以應敬順<caesura/>不宜生輕慢</l>
            <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0392a" n="0392a"/>
            <l>於諸聚落中<caesura/>及以閑靜處</l>
            <l>若見小龍子<caesura/>形狀雖微細</l>
            <l>能大亦能小<caesura/>亦復能興雲</l>
            <l>降注於大雨<caesura/>若以小故輕</l>
            <l>必能縱毒螫<caesura/>欲護身命者</l>
            <l>不宜輕於彼<caesura/>為於己利故</l>
            <l>宜應自擁護<caesura/>亦如有小<app n="fnT02p0392n01">
                <lem wit="【大】">小</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">火</rdg>
              </app>小</l>
            <l>若具於眾緣<caesura/>猛炎甚熾盛</l>
            <l>
              <app n="fnT02p0392n02">
                <lem wit="【大】">遇</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">過</rdg>
              </app>遇於大暴風<caesura/>能焚燒山野</l>
            <l>既焚林野已<caesura/>遇時還復生</l>
            <l>欲護己命者<caesura/>不應輕小火</l>
            <l>若於淨戒所<caesura/>惡口加罵辱</l>
            <l>其身及子孫<caesura/>一切皆毀謗</l>
            <l>於未來世中<caesura/>當同受惡報</l>
            <l>是故應自護<caesura/>莫以惡加彼</l>
            <l>剎利具技藝<caesura/>龍子及與火</l>
            <l>比丘持淨戒<caesura/>此四不可輕</l>
            <l>為護己命故<caesura/>謹慎應遠離</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza053.12">爾時波斯匿王聞此語已，其心戰慄，身毛為竪，即從坐起，偏袒右肩，合掌向佛，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza053.13">世尊！我於今者實有過罪，自知毀犯。譬如<app n="fnT02p0392n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾愚，狂癡無知，所作不善。唯願世尊憐愍我故，聽我懺悔！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza053.14">佛告波斯匿王言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza053.15">我今愍汝，聽汝懺悔。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza053">
        <p n="bza053.16">時波斯匿王既蒙懺悔，心大歡喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
