<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza054">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0392a26"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza054">
        <p n="bza054.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza054">
        <p n="bza054.02">爾時<name type="person">波斯匿</name>王稟性仁孝，母初崩背，哀號戀慕，不自堪勝，燒葬母已，便自沐浴，衣髮故濕，於日中時往詣佛所，禮佛足已，在<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0392b" n="0392b"/>一面坐。佛告王曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza054.03">王從何來？衣髮故濕。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza054.04">波斯匿王白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza054.05">世尊！我之慈母，情特尊敬。一旦崩背，我送母喪，遠至曠野，殯葬已訖，新<app n="fnT02p0392n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">浴洗</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">洗浴</rdg>
            </app>浴洗故，衣髮猶濕。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza054.06">佛告大王：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza054.07">汝於母所極愛敬不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza054.08">王即答言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza054.09">實為愛敬！設令有人能使我母<app n="fnT02p0392n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">還</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">復</rdg>
            </app>還得活者，我以象軍、車軍、馬軍、步軍悉以與之。<app n="fnT02p0392n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">續</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">贖</rdg>
            </app>續我母命，心無悔恨。設以半國賞之，亦不生恨。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza054.10">王復言曰：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza054.11">佛語誠實。一切生者會必歸死。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza054.12">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza054.13"> 實爾，實爾，生必有死。五趣四生，無不終者。王者、臣民、婆羅門眾會歸當死。灌頂人王，威力自在，統領國土，會歸終<app n="fnT02p0392n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">沒</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">歿</rdg>
            </app>沒。轉輪聖王，王四天下，七寶具足，亦會當死。五通神仙在於山藪飲水食果，亦歸於死。三十三天極受快樂，光色熾盛，處天宮殿，壽命延長，亦歸終<app n="fnT02p0392n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">沒</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">歿</rdg>
            </app>沒。諸羅漢等捨於重擔，逮得己利，盡諸有結，心得自在，正智解脫，後邊之身，亦歸散滅。諸辟支佛獨一無侶，常在閑靜，亦當散滅。諸佛正覺具於十力，有四無畏，得四無礙，能師子吼，身亦無常，會歸散滅。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza054.14">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza054.15">大王！我為大王種種分別，生必有死，略而言之，無生不終。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza054.16">佛即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza054.17" met="5" xml:id="cg054a">
            <l>一切生皆死<caesura/>壽命必歸終</l>
            <l>隨業受緣報<caesura/>善惡各獲果</l>
            <l>修福上昇天<caesura/>為惡入地獄</l>
            <l>修道斷生死<caesura/>永入於涅槃</l>
            <l>非空非海中<caesura/>非入山石間</l>
            <l>無有地方所<caesura/>脫之不受死</l>
            <l>諸佛與緣覺<caesura/>菩薩及聲聞</l>
            <l>猶捨無常身<caesura/>何況諸凡夫</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0392c" n="0392c"/>
        <p n="bza054.18">時波斯匿王聞佛所說，心開意解，更不憂愁，歡喜而去。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza054">
        <p n="bza054.19">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
