<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza069">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0398a01"/>
      <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0398a" n="0398a"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza069">
        <p n="bza069.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza069">
        <p n="bza069.02">爾時<name type="person">波斯匿</name>王往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="pasenadi">
          <p n="bza069.03">世尊！婆羅門種，常生婆羅門家；剎利種，常生剎利家不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza069.04">佛<app n="fnT02p0398n02">
            <lem wit="【大】">告</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">答</rdg>
          </app>告王曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza069.05">
                            汝今不應作如是語。何以故？有四種人：一者、從明入明，二者、從明入冥，三者、從冥入明，四者、從冥入冥。何謂從冥入冥？若有眾生，生於下賤貧窮之者，或生魁膾、<app n="fnT02p0395n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">伎</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">技</rdg>
            </app>技巧之家，或身羸瘦，其形極黑，聾、盲、瘖瘂，諸根不具，為他作使，不得自在。如此之人，或身行惡業，或口作惡業，或心念不善，身壞命終，墮於地獄，是名從冥入冥。如<app n="fnT02p0398n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">從</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">前</rdg>
            </app>從廁出，復入一廁。我說此人，從冥入冥。若如此人，生於下賤及魁膾、<app n="fnT02p0395n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">伎</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">技</rdg>
            </app>技巧，或身羸瘦，其形極黑，聾、盲、瘖瘂，諸根不具，為他走使，不得自在，是名為冥。若如此人，能身行善，能口行善，能意行善，身壞命終，得生天上。如此人。從地而起，得昇於床；從床而起，得乘於車；從車而起，得乘於馬；從馬而起，得乘於象；從象而起，得昇宮殿。以是緣故，我說從冥入明。何謂從明入冥？若有人，生於剎利家，或復生於婆羅門家，或生大長者家，多饒財寶，巨富無量，庫藏盈溢，多諸僕從，輔相大臣、親友眷屬，亦甚眾多，身形端正，有大威力。如是之人，是名為明。若此之人，身行惡業，口行惡業，意行惡業，身壞命終，墮於地獄。如人從宮殿下，墮於象上；從象上下，而乘於馬；從馬上下，而乘於車；從車上下，而坐於床；從床<app n="fnT02p0398n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">而</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">上</rdg>
            </app>而下，墮落於地；從地而墮，墜於糞坑。我說此人，從明入冥。何謂從明入明？若有人，<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0398b" n="0398b"/>生於<app n="fnT02p0398n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">剎利</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">剎利家</rdg>
            </app>剎利、大婆羅門家，或生長者，多饒財寶，巨富無量，庫藏盈溢，多諸僕從，輔相大臣、親友眷屬，亦甚眾多，身形端正，有大威力。此名為明。如此之人，身行善業，口行善業，意行善業，身壞命終，得生天上。如似從一宮殿，至於宮殿；從象至象；從馬至馬；從車至車；從床至床。如此之人，我說從明入明。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza069.06">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza069.07" met="5" xml:id="cg069a">
            <l>大王汝當知<caesura/>貧窮不信者</l>
            <l>瞋恚懷嫉妬<caesura/>恒起惡覺觀</l>
            <l>邪見無恭敬<caesura/>沙門婆羅門</l>
            <l>持戒及多聞<caesura/>見則加罵辱</l>
            <l>設有少財物<caesura/>無有奉施心</l>
            <l>毀罵施與者<caesura/>如此之業緣</l>
            <l>必墮於地獄<caesura/>是業墮地獄</l>
            <l>名從闇入闇<caesura/>大王今當知</l>
            <l>貧窮好施者<caesura/>有信無瞋恚</l>
            <l>慚愧而好施<caesura/>沙門婆羅門</l>
            <l>持戒及多聞<caesura/>起敬禮問訊</l>
            <l>常行正善行<caesura/>自施讚施者</l>
            <l>受者亦讚嘆<caesura/>如是至後世</l>
            <l>生三十三天<caesura/>此名從此闇</l>
            <l>將入於明處<caesura/>大王又當知</l>
            <l>大富而不信<caesura/>心常懷瞋恚</l>
            <l>常起貪嫉妬<caesura/>邪見不恭敬</l>
            <l>沙門婆羅門<caesura/>持戒及多聞</l>
            <l>見則加罵辱<caesura/>無有奉施心</l>
            <l>從此而命終<caesura/>墮於惡地獄</l>
            <l>名從明入闇<caesura/>大王又當知</l>
            <l>大富信無<app n="fnT02p0398n06">
                <lem wit="【大】">瞋</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">明</rdg>
              </app>瞋<caesura/>慚愧得具足</l>
            <l>能捨大慳心<caesura/>沙門婆羅門</l>
            <l>持戒及多聞<caesura/>起敬而問訊</l>
            <l>常行於正善<caesura/>自施讚施者</l>
            <l>受者所歎譽<caesura/>捨此身命已</l>
            <l>以是果報故<caesura/>生三十三天</l>
            <l>此名從於明<caesura/>而入於明處</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza069">
        <p n="bza069.08">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
