<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                              法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                    lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                    Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                    edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                    the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                                English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza018">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0379c03"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza018">
        <p n="bza018.01">如是我聞：一時佛<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza018">
        <p n="bza018.02">爾時有一比丘，於清晨朝往趣河邊，脫衣，洗浴。還出岸上，晞乾其身。有天放光，照于河岸，問比丘言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p n="bza018.03">比丘！此是巢窟，夜則烟出，晝則火燃。有婆羅門，見是事已，破彼巢窟，并掘其地。時有智人，語婆羅門言：<q who="sumedho">以刀掘地，見有一龜。</q>婆羅門言：<q who="brahmano">取是龜來！</q>復語：<q who="sumedho">掘地，見一蝮蛇。</q>語令捉取。復語：<q who="sumedho">掘地，見一肉段。</q>語令挽取。復語：<q who="sumedho">掘地，見一刀舍。</q>婆羅門言：<q who="brahmano">此是刀舍。</q>語令掘取。復語：<q who="sumedho">掘地，見楞祇芒毒蟲。</q>語令掘取。復語：<q who="sumedho">掘地，見有二道。</q>復語：<q who="sumedho">掘出。</q>語：<q who="sumedho">更掘地，見有石<choice>
                <sic>娶</sic>
                <corr resp="T100">聚</corr>
              </choice>。</q>語令出石。復語：<q who="sumedho">掘地，見有一龍。</q>婆羅門言：<q who="brahmano">莫惱於龍！</q>即跪彼龍。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza018.04">天語比丘言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p n="bza018.05">莫忘我語！可以問佛。佛有所說，至心憶持！所以者何？我不見若天、若魔、若梵有能分別者，除佛及以聲聞弟子，比丘，無能得解如是問者。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza018.06">爾時比丘往至佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面立，所聞天語，具向佛說：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza018.07">世尊！云何巢窟，夜則烟出，晝則火<app n="fnT02p0379n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">然</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">燃</rdg>
            </app>然？誰是婆羅門？誰是智人？云何是刀？云何是掘？云何為龜？云何蝮蛇？云何肉段？云何刀舍？云何楞祇芒毒虫？云何二道？云何石聚？云何名龍？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza018.08">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza018.09">諦聽！諦聽！當為汝說。巢窟者，所謂是身──受於父母精氣，四大和合，衣、食長養，乃得成身──，而此身者會至散敗、膖脹、虫爛乃至碎壞。夜烟出者，種種覺、觀。晝火<app n="fnT02p0379n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">然</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">燃</rdg>
            </app>然者，從身、口業廣有所作。婆羅門者，即是如來。有智人者，即諸聲聞。刀<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0380a" n="0380a"/>喻智慧。掘地者，喻於精進。龜者，喻於五蓋。蝮蛇者，喻瞋惱害。肉段者，喻慳貪、嫉妬。刀舍者，喻五欲。楞祇芒毒虫，喻如愚癡。二道者，喻於疑。諸石聚者，喻於我慢。龍者，喻於羅漢盡諸有結。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza018.10">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza018.11" met="5" xml:id="cg018a">
            <l>巢窟名為身<caesura/>覺觀如彼烟</l>
            <l>造作如火<app n="fnT02p0379n09">
                <lem wit="【大】">然</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">燃</rdg>
              </app>然<caesura/>婆羅門如佛</l>
            <l>智人是聲聞<caesura/>刀即是智慧</l>
            <l>掘地喻精進<caesura/>五蓋猶如龜</l>
            <l>瞋恚如蝮蛇<caesura/>貪嫉如肉段</l>
            <l>五欲如刀舍<caesura/>愚癡如楞祇</l>
            <l>疑者如二道<caesura/>我見如石聚</l>
            <l>汝今莫惱龍<caesura/>龍是真羅漢</l>
            <l>善答問難者<caesura/>唯有佛世尊</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza018">
        <p n="bza018.12">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
