<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza086">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0403b10"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza086">
        <p n="bza086.01">如是我聞：一<choice>
            <sic>切</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">時</corr>
          </choice>佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza086">
        <p n="bza086.02">爾時有一老婆羅門，年耆根熟──先於往日多造眾惡，極為麤弊，毀犯所禁，不<app n="fnT02p0403n14">
            <lem wit="【大】">信</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">修</rdg>
          </app>信福善，不先作福，臨終之時無所依止──，往詣佛所，問訊佛已，在一面坐，而白佛言：</p>
        <q who="brahmano">
          <p n="bza086.03">世尊！我於往日多造眾惡，極為麤弊，毀犯所禁，不能修福，<app n="fnT02p0403n15">
              <lem wit="【大】">又</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">久</rdg>
            </app>又不修善，亦復不能先作福德，臨終之時無所依止！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza086.04">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza086.05">實如汝語。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza086.06">老婆羅門言：</p>
        <q who="brahmano">
          <p n="bza086.07">善哉瞿曇當為我說，使我長夜獲於安樂，得義，得利！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza086.08">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza086.09">實如汝說：汝於往日身、口、意業不<app n="fnT02p0403n16">
              <lem wit="【大】">作善行</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">行於善</rdg>
            </app>作善行，毀犯禁戒，不修福德，不能先造臨命終時作所<app n="fnT02p0403n17">
              <lem wit="【大】">怙恃</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">恃怙</rdg>
            </app>怙恃。汝於今者實為衰老，先造眾罪，所作麤惡，不造福業，不修善行，不能先造可畏之時所歸依處。譬如有人，將欲死時思願逃避，入善舍宅以自救護。如是之事，都不可得。是故今當身修善行，<app n="fnT02p0403n18">
              <lem wit="【大】">意口</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">口意</rdg>
            </app>意、口亦然。若三業善，臨命<app n="fnT02p0403n19">
              <lem wit="【大】">之</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">終</rdg>
            </app>之時即是舍宅，可逃避處。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza086.10">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza086.11" met="5" xml:id="cg086a">
            <l>人生壽命促<caesura/>必將付於死</l>
            <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0403c" n="0403c"/>
            <l>衰老之所侵<caesura/>無有能救者</l>
            <l>是以應畏死<caesura/>唯有入佛法</l>
            <l>若修善法者<caesura/>是則歸依處</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza086.12">佛說是已，……（第二經無差別）：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza086.13" met="5" xml:id="cg086b">
            <l>應求歸依處<caesura/>大人宜修善</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza086.14">（第三長行別，偈則不同。）偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza086.15" met="5" xml:id="cg086c">
            <l>壯盛及衰老<caesura/>三時皆過去</l>
            <l>餘命既無幾<caesura/>常為老所患</l>
            <l>近到閻王際<caesura/>婆羅門欲生</l>
            <l>二間無住處<caesura/>汝都無資粮</l>
            <l>應作小明燈<caesura/>依憑於精<app n="fnT02p0403n20">
                <lem wit="【大】">勤</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">進</rdg>
              </app>勤</l>
            <l>前除於諸使<caesura/>不復生老死</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
