<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                              法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                                    lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                                    Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                                    edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                                    the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                                English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza012">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0376c15"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza012">
        <p n="bza012.01">如是我聞：一時佛住<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">仙人山</name>中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza012">
        <p n="bza012.02">時尊者<name type="person">阿難</name>處於閑靜，默自思惟：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza012.03">世尊昔來說三種香，所謂根、莖、華香。一切諸香不出此三。然三種香，順風則聞，逆風不聞。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza012.04">尊者阿難思惟是已，即從坐起，往至佛所，禮佛足畢，在一面立，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza012.05">世尊！我於向者獨處閑靜，默自思惟：<q who="anando">世尊所說根、莖、華等三種之香，眾香中上。然其香氣，順風則聞，逆則不聞。</q>世尊！頗復有香，逆風、順風皆能聞不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza012.06">佛告阿難：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza012.07">如是，如是，世有好香，順、逆皆聞。何者是耶？若聚落城邑若男若女修治不殺、不盜、不婬、不妄語、不飲酒。若諸天及得天眼者，盡皆稱嘆。彼城邑聚落若男若女持五戒者，如是戒香，順、逆<app n="fnT02p0376n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">皆</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">俱</rdg>
            </app>皆聞。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza012.08">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza012.09" met="5" xml:id="cg012a">
            <l>若栴檀沈水<caesura/>根莖及花葉</l>
            <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0377a" n="0377a"/>
            <l>此香順風聞<caesura/>逆風無聞者</l>
            <l>持戒香丈夫<caesura/>芳<app n="fnT02p0377n01">
                <lem wit="【大】">馨</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">聲</rdg>
              </app>馨遍世界</l>
            <l>名聞滿十方<caesura/>逆順悉聞之</l>
            <l>栴檀及沈水<caesura/>優鉢羅<app n="fnT02p0377n02">
                <lem wit="【大】">拔</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">跋</rdg>
              </app>拔師</l>
            <l>如此香微劣<caesura/>不如持戒香</l>
            <l>如是種種香<caesura/>所聞處不遠</l>
            <l>戒香聞十方<caesura/>殊勝諸天香</l>
            <l>如此清淨戒<caesura/>不放逸為本</l>
            <l>安住無漏法<caesura/>正智得解脫</l>
            <l>眾魔雖欲求<caesura/>莫知其方所</l>
            <l>是名安隱道<caesura/>此道最清淨</l>
            <l>永離於諸向<caesura/>捨棄於眾趣</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza012">
        <p n="bza012.10">說是偈已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
