<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDesc>
        <glyph xml:id="g023">
          <glyphName>CJK IDEOGRAPH 15538</glyphName>
          <charProp>
            <localName>pronunciation</localName>
            <value>die2; yi4?</value>
          </charProp>
          <mapping type="cbeta">[疊*毛]</mapping>
          <mapping type="cbetaNo">CB00626</mapping>
          <mapping type="UTF-8">E3 B2 B2</mapping>
          <mapping type="unicode">15538</mapping>
          <graphic url="gaiji/g023.gif"/>
          <note>
            appears in bza081; bza092; bza110; bza186; bza262; bza322; bza342;
                                    tn0099-0882; tn0099-1197
          </note>
        </glyph>
      </charDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza081">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0401c02"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza081">
        <p n="bza081.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza081">
        <p n="bza081.02">爾時舍衛城中<name type="person">婆私吒</name>婆羅門女於佛、法、僧前心信清淨，歸依三寶，心不生疑。苦、<app n="fnT02p0401n16">
            <lem wit="【大】">習</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">集</rdg>
          </app>習、滅、道，亦不生疑。得見四諦，逮第一果，見法同等。其夫婆羅門姓，<name type="person">婆羅突邏闍</name>。為夫所使，足<app n="fnT02p0401n17">
            <lem wit="【大】">趺</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">跌</rdg>
          </app>趺倒地。從地起已，叉手合掌，向佛方所，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="dhananjani">
          <p n="bza081.03">南無佛陀．如來．至真．等正覺，真金之色，圓光一尋，身體方整，如尼拘陀樹，說法第一，第七仙聖，解脫，世雄。我之世尊！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.04">爾時其夫婆羅門聞婦此語，極生瞋忿，而罵詈言：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <p n="bza081.05"> 汝<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0402a" n="0402a"/>是顛狂旃陀羅也！誰今為此癡旃陀羅作蠱道也？更無如汝，極下賤者。汝於三明大婆羅門所不能恭敬，方禮禿頭、瘦黑之人。如此沙門，共耶那<app n="fnT02p0402n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">邏</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">羅</rdg>
            </app>邏延斷人種者，極相讚嘆。汝若信樂，極深厚者。咄我於今，請與汝師，共相講論！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.06">婦語夫言：</p>
        <q who="dhananjani">
          <p n="bza081.07">我都不見若沙門、婆羅門、若天、若魔、若梵，有能與佛共講論者。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.08">其婦復言：</p>
        <q who="dhananjani">
          <p n="bza081.09">南無佛陀．如來．至真．等正覺，真金之色，身體方整，圓光一尋，如尼拘陀樹，說法第一，第七仙聖，解脫，世雄。我之世尊！汝自知時。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.10">婆羅門即詣佛所，問訊已訖，在一面坐，說偈問曰：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <lg n="bza081.11" met="7" xml:id="cg081a">
            <l>摧壞何物得安眠<caesura/>除<app n="fnT02p0402n02">
                <lem wit="【大】">却</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">祛</rdg>
              </app>却何法獲無憂</l>
            <l>是何一法能死滅<caesura/>瞿曇沙門為我說</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.12">爾時世尊說偈答言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza081.13" met="7" xml:id="cg081b">
            <l>摧壞瞋恚得安眠<caesura/>除滅瞋恚得無憂</l>
            <l>瞋恚詐親能死害<caesura/>摩納如是應當知</l>
            <l>滅除瞋恚聖所讚<caesura/>能害彼者得無憂</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.14">爾時世尊為婆羅門如應說法，示、教、利、喜，次第為說：施論、戒論、生天之論。欲為不淨，苦惱之本，出要為樂。廣示眾善，白淨之法。時婆羅門聞佛所說，心開意解，踊躍歡喜。佛知摩納心意調濡，踊躍歡喜，心無狐疑，堪任法器，為說一法，堪任解悟。如諸佛法，為說四諦：苦、<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0048n02"/>習、盡、道。廣為說已，時婆羅突邏闍聞佛所說，如白淨<g ref="g023">[疊*毛]</g>，易受染色，即於坐上見四真諦，了達諸法，得法真際，度疑彼岸，不隨於他，得無所畏，即從坐起，合掌向佛，<app n="fnT02p0402n03">
            <lem wit="【大】">白</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">白佛</rdg>
          </app>白言：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <p n="bza081.15">世尊！我已出離。今欲歸依佛、法、僧寶，盡我形壽，為優婆塞，不殺、不盜、不婬、不妄語、不飲酒。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.16">即於佛<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0402b" n="0402b"/>所得不壞信，禮佛歸家。其婦見夫如上歎佛：</p>
        <q who="dhananjani">
          <p n="bza081.17">我師如是。汝共語耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.18">夫答婦言：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <p n="bza081.19">我不見世間若沙門、若婆羅門、若天、若魔、若梵，有能與佛共論議者。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.20">復語婦言：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <p n="bza081.21">與我衣來。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.22">婦即與之。既得衣已，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bharadvajagotto">
          <p n="bza081.23">世尊！唯願聽我於佛法中出家學道！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza081.24">佛即然許，命一比丘，度使出家。既出家已，稱出家法，獨已專精。……（餘如婆羅突邏闍經中廣說。乃至）得阿羅漢，心得好解脫。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza081">
        <p n="bza081.25">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
