<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza118">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0417a23"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza118">
        <p n="bza118.01">如是我聞：<choice>
            <sic>賤</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA"/>
          </choice>一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">耆闍崛山<name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>
          </name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza118">
        <p n="bza118.02"> 爾時尊者<name type="person">摩訶迦葉</name>、尊者<name type="person">阿難</name>在耆闍崛山中。于時阿難食時已到，語尊者摩訶迦葉，言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza118.03">大德！食時已到，可共乞食。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.04">於是摩訶迦葉著衣持鉢，與阿難出耆闍崛山，入王舍城乞食。阿難語摩訶迦葉言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza118.05">日時猶早，我欲至彼比丘尼精舍，觀諸比丘尼等所<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0417b" n="0417b"/>行法式。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.06">迦葉答言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza118.07">可爾。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.08">即時共詣比丘尼精舍。爾時諸比丘尼遙見二尊者來，即敷床座。既敷座已，白二尊者：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhuni">
          <p n="bza118.09">可就此坐！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.10">時二尊者即就其坐。諸比丘尼既見坐已，稽首禮足，在一面立。爾時摩訶迦葉為比丘尼種種說法，示、教、利、喜。於彼眾中有比丘尼，名<name type="person">偷羅難陀</name>，聞說法要，心不甘樂，即出惡言：</p>
        <q who="thullananda">
          <p n="bza118.11">今者云何長老迦葉在阿難前為比丘尼而說法要？如賣針人，至針師門，求欲賣針，終不可售！今者迦葉亦復如是。云何乃在阿難前而說於法？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.12">作是語已，嘿然而住。時摩訶迦葉以淨天耳聞其所言，語長老阿難：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza118.13">汝見是偷羅難陀比丘尼心不喜<app n="fnT02p0417n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">樂悅心</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">悅</rdg>
            </app>樂悅，心出麁言不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.14">是時阿難語迦葉言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza118.15">彼說何事？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.16">迦葉答言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza118.17">彼作是說：<q who="thullananda">云何迦葉在<name type="person">阿難──比提醯<app n="fnT02p0417n06">
                  <lem wit="【大】">子</lem>
                  <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】"/>
                </app>子牟尼──</name>之前而說法要？</q>以汝同彼針師之子，以我名為賣針之人。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.18">尊者阿難語迦葉言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza118.19">止，止，尊者！<app n="fnT02p0415n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾愚少智，不足具責。唯願大德聽其懺悔！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.20">迦葉即語長老阿難言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza118.21">如來．世尊．多陀阿伽度．阿羅呵三藐三佛陀為教導故，引彼月喻，日<app n="fnT02p0417n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">漸</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">新</rdg>
            </app>漸增長，能具慚愧，離於無慚，忍<app n="fnT02p0417n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">于</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">於</rdg>
            </app>于罵辱，禁制身心，往返人間，為<app n="fnT02p0417n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">導</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">道</rdg>
            </app>導於我。為說於汝，同彼月耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.22">阿難答言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza118.23">如來．世雄實不說我同於彼月！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.24">迦葉復言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza118.25">
            <app n="fnT02p0417n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">唯</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">唯顧</rdg>
            </app>唯佛．世尊．多陀阿伽度．阿羅呵．三藐三佛陀．等正覺知者說我同彼月初生時，日<app n="fnT02p0417n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">漸</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">新</rdg>
            </app>漸增長，能具慚愧，離於無慚，忍于罵辱，禁制身心，往返諸家。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.26">阿難白言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza118.27">實爾。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.28">尊者迦葉語阿難言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza118.29">如來．世尊於無量百千大眾之前稱我名字，言：<q who="gotamo">是大德有慚愧人，智慧深遠。</q>喻似於<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0417c" n="0417c"/>己。佛告比丘：<q who="gotamo">我今離於欲、惡不善，有覺有觀，喜樂一心，入於初禪，晝夜常在如是定中。迦葉比丘亦常離於欲、惡不善，有覺有觀，喜樂一心，入於初禪，晝夜恒在如是定中。</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.30">阿難答言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza118.31">實爾，迦葉！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza118.32">二、三、四禪，慈、悲、喜、捨及四禪定，三明六通，亦復如是。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza118">
        <p n="bza118.33">爾時尊者摩訶迦葉於比丘尼大眾之前作師子吼已，從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0329n06"/>坐而起，即還所止。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
