<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza120">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0419a03"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza120">
        <p n="bza120.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">耆闍崛山</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza120">
        <p n="bza120.02"> 爾時尊者<name type="person">舍利弗</name>及<name type="person">大迦葉</name>俱在彼山。時彼國中有諸異見六師徒黨，來詣尊者舍利弗所，問訊已訖，在一面坐，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza120.03">如來．世尊頗說<q who="gotamo">於我死此生彼</q>，如是說不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.04">舍利弗答言：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p n="bza120.05">如斯之事佛所不說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.06">外道六師復作是言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza120.07">若如是者，說<q who="gotamo">於我身在此間</q>耶？<q who="gotamo">更不生</q>耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.08">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p n="bza120.09">如斯之事佛亦不說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.10">外道復言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza120.11">
            <q who="gotamo">我於此死，亦生於彼，亦不生彼。</q>如是說耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.12">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p n="bza120.13">佛亦不說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.14">外道<app n="fnT02p0419n02">
            <lem wit="【大】">復</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
          </app>復言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza120.15">
            <q who="gotamo">我死之後，非生非不生</q>耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.16">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p n="bza120.17">佛亦不說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.18">外道復言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza120.19">我先問汝：死此生彼，……（乃至）非生非不生，悉不見答。汝若名為宿舊出家，應廣解義，為我分別。今者觀汝不能答我，便是童蒙，無智愚人！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.20">時彼外道作是語已，即從坐起，還其所止。爾時尊者摩訶迦葉去舍利弗不遠。外道去後，舍利弗即詣於彼大迦葉所，以外道問向迦葉說如來何故如是四問默然不答，何以故不<app n="fnT02p0419n03">
            <lem wit="【大】">引</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">能</rdg>
          </app>引相似比類而答於彼：</p>
        <q who="sariputto">
          <p n="bza120.21">我昔曾聞有人問佛：<q who="titthiya">於此死已，受後有不？</q>佛默然不答。又問：<q who="titthiya">死後不受有耶？</q>佛亦不答。又問：<q who="titthiya">我此死已，亦受後有，亦不受耶？</q>佛亦不答。又問：<q who="titthiya">我死之後，非受於有，非不受有耶？</q>佛亦不答。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza120.22">尊者迦葉語舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza120.23">如來寧可說色滅已，生於後有，……（乃至）非生非不生。世尊於彼色所盡處，正智解脫，然都無有死此生彼，死此不生彼，亦生亦不<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0419b" n="0419b"/>生，非生非不生。是故不答。如斯之義甚深廣大，無量無邊，無有算數，乃至盡滅。受、想……（乃至）識，死此生彼，……（乃至）非生非不生亦復如是。此是動轉，此是憍慢，此是放逸，此是有為造作之業，此是愛結。此愛生彼，愛不生彼，<app n="fnT02p0419n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">愛亦</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">亦愛</rdg>
            </app>愛亦生彼亦不生彼，愛非生彼非不生彼。如<app n="fnT02p0419n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">來</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">是</rdg>
            </app>來愛盡，得善解脫。愛盡，生彼有亦無也，不生彼有亦無也，生彼不生彼亦無也，非不有生彼非不無生彼亦無也。此義甚深，廣大無邊，無有算數，至於盡滅。大德舍利弗！當知：以是因緣故，如來於問中而不正答：死此生彼，此死不生彼，亦生彼亦不生彼，非生非不生。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza120">
        <p n="bza120.24">此二大人互相讚美，各還所止。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
