<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza112">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0414c12"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza112">
        <p n="bza112.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園。</name>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza112">
        <p n="bza112.02">爾時佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza112.03">若有比丘，將欲往詣於檀越家，先作是念：<q who="bhikkhu">若有所施，當速與我，勿令遲晚！至心施我，莫不至誠！願使多得，勿令寡少！<app n="fnT02p0414n13">
                <lem wit="【大】">惠</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明異】">思</rdg>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">與</rdg>
              </app>惠我精細，勿得麁澁！</q>若作是念，決定意者往檀越家，檀越雖與，不至心施，不恭敬與；雖施飲食，不令豐足；與其麁澁，不與精細；設有施與，遲緩不速；而此比丘不稱意故，羞恥愁憂，生損減心。而此比丘應作是念：<q who="bhikkhu">至檀越舍，彼非<app n="fnT02p0414n14">
                <lem wit="【大】">己</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">我</rdg>
              </app>己家。云何而得稱遂其心？何故生念：欲令檀越速施不遲，……（乃至）精細，不用麁澁！</q>若作是念，設無所得，心不悔恨，離於增減，無有怨嫌。設彼檀越少有所施，不至心與，遲晚不速，……（乃至）與麁，不與精細，如是比丘心不嫌恨，亦不愧恥，心無增減。迦葉比丘作如是心：<q who="kassapo">至檀越所，斯非己家。云何而得自稱其意？望彼至心，速施不遲，……（乃至）精細，莫得麁澁！</q>迦葉比丘作如是念，至檀越家，雖不得<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0415a" n="0415a"/>施，都無慚恥，心不損減。是故──比丘！──應作是心，至於他家，不應生念：<q who="bhikkhu">速施於我，……（乃至）精細！</q>是故汝等當作是學：如迦葉比丘往檀越家。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza112">
        <p n="bza112.04">時諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
