<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza184">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0439b29"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza184">
        <p n="bza184.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0439c" n="0439c"/>獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza184">
        <p n="bza184.02">爾時佛告諸比丘： <q who="gotamo">
            <p n="bza184.03">於往昔時<name type="place">俱薩羅國</name>有五百乘車，而以為伴。行到曠野<app n="fnT02p0439n06">
                <lem wit="【大】">險</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">嶮</rdg>
              </app>險難之處，無有水草。有五百賊，尋逐其車，規欲<app n="fnT02p0439n07">
                <lem wit="【大】">摽</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">漂</rdg>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">勡</rdg>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">剽</rdg>
              </app>摽掠。時有天神，住曠野中，知賊欲劫，而作是念：<q who="devata">我今當往，詣彼車所。我當問之，彼若能答，當為救護；設有不通，我當放捨。</q>思惟是已，尋即來到行客車前──身光遍照，五百乘車盡皆大明──，即便以偈問商估言：<q who="devata">
                <lg n="bza184.04" met="7" xml:id="cg184a">
                  <l>誰於寤者名為睡<caesura/>誰於睡者名為寤</l>
                  <l>誰能解達如斯義<caesura/>宜知是時應答我</l>
                </lg>
              </q>
                                時商估中有優婆塞，於三寶所深得淨信，歸佛、法、僧，於佛、法、僧得了決定，無有狐疑。又於四諦亦無疑心，已得見諦，獲於初果，晨朝早起，正身端坐，繫念在前，高聲誦經，誦法句偈及波羅<app n="fnT02p0439n08">
                <lem wit="【大】">緣</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">經</rdg>
              </app>緣，種種經偈。彼優婆塞說偈答言： <q who="upasaka">
                <lg n="bza184.05" met="7" xml:id="cg184b">
                  <l>我於寤者名為睡<caesura/>我於睡者名為寤</l>
                  <l>我知斯事悉明了<caesura/>是故今者以偈答</l>
                </lg>
              </q> 爾時天神以偈問言： <q who="devata">
                <lg n="bza184.06" met="7" xml:id="cg184c">
                  <l>汝今云何作是言<caesura/>我於寤者名為睡</l>
                  <l>我於睡者名為寤<caesura/>云何<app n="fnT02p0439n09">
                      <lem wit="【大】">如</lem>
                      <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">知</rdg>
                    </app>如此而答我</l>
                </lg>
              </q> 優婆塞以偈答言： <q who="upasaka">
                <lg n="bza184.07" met="7" xml:id="cg184d">
                  <l>斷除貪欲瞋恚癡<caesura/>諸漏已盡阿羅漢</l>
                  <l>彼稱為寤我名睡<caesura/>不知苦<app n="fnT02p0439n10">
                      <lem wit="【大】">習</lem>
                      <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">集</rdg>
                    </app>習及滅道</l>
                  <l>我於彼睡名為寤<caesura/>天神汝今應當知</l>
                </lg>
              </q> 天神復說偈問言： <q who="devata">
                <lg n="bza184.08" met="7" xml:id="cg184e">
                  <l>善哉於寤名為睡<caesura/>汝能善解答我問</l>
                  <l>久來不見法兄弟<caesura/>今得相見大歡悅</l>
                  <l>
                    <app n="fnT02p0439n11">
                      <lem wit="【大】">今</lem>
                      <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">爾</rdg>
                    </app>今爾眾伴為汝故<caesura/>一切安隱得歸還</l>
                </lg>
              </q>
            </p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza184">
        <p n="bza184.09">
          <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0440a" n="0440a"/>佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
