<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza199">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0447b19"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza199">
        <p n="bza199.01">如是我聞：一時佛住<name type="place">王舍城</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza199">
        <p n="bza199.02">時有梵志，厥名<name type="person">優陟</name>，來詣佛所，問訊佛已，在一面坐，即問佛言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza199.03">瞿曇！一切世界為有邊耶，為無邊耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza199.04">佛告優陟：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza199.05">如斯等問，吾初不答。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza199.06">優陟言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza199.07">瞿曇！我問世界有邊無邊，悉不見答。若然者，汝常說法，解釋問難，為何所答？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza199.08">佛<app n="fnT02p0447n10">
            <lem wit="【大】">言</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">告</rdg>
          </app>言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza199.09">優陟！吾於諸法悉善知已，為聲聞弟子分別正道，蠲除眾苦，盡其邊際。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza199.10">優陟言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza199.11">瞿曇！汝於諸法悉善知已，為聲聞弟子說<app n="fnT02p0447n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">于</rdg>
            </app>於正道，蠲除眾苦，盡其邊際。若如是者，汝所得道，為一切人盡行是道，為有多少而行斯道？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza199.12">爾時如來<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0447c" n="0447c"/>默然不答。第二、第三亦如是問，如來默然，悉不加報。爾時<name type="person">阿難</name>執扇侍佛，以扇扇佛，聞彼優陟所諮已，即語之言：</p>
        <q who="anado">
          <p n="bza199.13">汝後所問與前無異，是以世尊默<app n="fnT02p0447n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">然</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>然不答汝。我且為汝說一方喻。譬如邊守有城，牆壁牢實，欄楯窓牖，悉皆堅固。街、巷、里、陌、官府、市肆，周障布置，不相干錯。而此城中唯有一門。時守門人聰明智慧，有大念力，善能分別客舊諸人，識者聽入，不識則遮。時城中人欲有出者，不知出要，周匝遍觀，更無孔穴，唯此一門乃從求出。而此守門智慧之人雖不具知城中種類，然知其中將出城者，皆由此門。如是──優陟！──如來亦爾，雖不具悉思惟分別，然知出入，皆由此門。如來亦然，知過去苦，現在、未來苦之邊際，皆由斯道，得盡於苦。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza199">
        <p n="bza199.14">優陟梵志聞<app n="fnT02p0447n13">
            <lem wit="【大】">佛</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">阿難</rdg>
          </app>佛所說，歡喜而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
