<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza115">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0415c18"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza115">
        <p n="bza115.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza115">
        <p n="bza115.02">爾時尊者<name type="person">摩訶迦葉</name>住舊園林<name type="place">毘舍佉講堂</name>。時尊者迦葉於日沒時從禪定起，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐。佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza115.03"> 汝可教授諸比丘等，為其說法。所以者何？我常教授，汝亦應爾。我<app n="fnT02p0415n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">常</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">恒</rdg>
            </app>常為彼而說法要，汝亦應爾。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza115.04">迦葉白佛言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza115.05">世尊！是諸比丘不能受語，難可教授！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza115.06">佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza115.07">汝<app n="fnT02p0415n14">
              <lem wit="【大】">何以</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">以何</rdg>
            </app>何以故而不教授，為其說法？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza115.08">迦葉對曰：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza115.09">世尊是法根本，是法之導，法所依憑。善哉世尊願為敷演！我聞語已，至心受持！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza115.10">佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza115.11">汝今善聽，受持憶念！吾當為汝分別解說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza115.12">迦葉白佛：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza115.13">
            <app n="fnT02p0415n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">爾止</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">止爾</rdg>
            </app>唯然，世尊！願樂欲聞！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza115.14">
          <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0416a" n="0416a"/>佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza115.15">昔有比丘，自修阿練若行，讚嘆修阿練若行者；自行乞食，著糞掃衣，讚嘆乞食，著糞掃衣者；少欲知足，常樂空閑寂靜之處，勤修精進，心不馳散，恒樂禪定；自盡諸漏，讚盡漏者。以是之故，一切比丘咸來親近，而問訊之。而此比丘語諸來者：<q who="bhikkhu">善來，比丘！可就此座。汝名為何？是誰弟子？履行賢良，應沙門法。夫出家者，宜應如汝作於沙門。若見汝者，學汝所為，不久必當獲於己利！</q>新學比丘覩斯事已，而作是念：<q who="bhikkhu">彼有比丘，共相恭敬。我今亦當習學其行，自修阿練若行，讚嘆修阿練若行者；自行乞食，著糞掃衣，讚嘆乞食，著糞掃衣者；少欲知足，常樂空閑寂靜之處，勤修精進，心不馳散，恒樂禪定；自盡諸漏，讚盡漏者。以是之故，一切比丘咸來親近，安慰問訊。而此比丘語諸來者：<q who="bhikkhu">善來，比丘！可就此坐。汝名為何？是誰弟子？履行賢良，應沙門法。出家之人宜應如汝，作於沙門。若見汝者，學汝所為，不久必當獲己義利！</q>
            </q>諸新學者若生是念，長夜利益，得義得樂，名自濟拔，能令正法得久住世。是人進趣，終不退沒。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza115.16">佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza115.17">若有比丘，生則有福。初始出家，多得利養──衣服、湯藥、床敷<choice>
              <sic>敷</sic>
              <corr resp="T100"/>
            </choice>臥具，四事豐饒。復有比丘，見是比丘，親近談語，安慰問訊。時此比丘語彼比丘：<q who="bhikkhu">汝名何等？是誰弟子？生則有福，多得利養──衣服、湯藥、床敷臥具，四事豐饒。若有比丘，親近汝者，四事不乏。</q>若有新學比丘，覩斯事已，應作是念：<q who="bhikkhu">彼有生福，比丘共相恭敬。我今亦當<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0416b" n="0416b"/>修如是行，衣服、臥具、飲食、湯藥，四事供養，亦常豐饒。</q>若新學比丘作如是意，學如是事已，是名長夜衰耗，都無利益及以利樂，非沙門法，受諸苦惱，名自輕毀。梵行不立，沒于淤泥，為惡所欺，具於結使，數受諸有，名生熱惱。獲得苦報，必當受於生、老、病、死。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza115">
        <p n="bza115.18">時大迦葉及諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
