<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza154">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0431c12"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza154">
        <p n="bza154.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">迦毘羅衛國</name>
          <name type="place">尼拘陀林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza154">
        <p n="bza154.02">時<name type="person">釋摩男</name>往詣佛所，修敬已畢，在一面坐，而白佛言：</p>
        <q who="mahanama">
          <p n="bza154.03">世尊！云何名優婆塞具丈夫志？（廣說如上。）復當云何滿足諸行？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.04">佛告摩訶男：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza154.05">優婆塞雖具足信，未具禁戒，是名有信，不具於戒。欲求具足信、戒之者，當勤方便，求使具足，是名信、戒滿足優婆塞。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.06">佛復告摩訶男：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza154.07">優婆塞雖具信、戒，捨不具足，為具足故，勤修方便，令得具足。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.08">時摩訶男白佛言：</p>
        <q who="mahanama">
          <p n="bza154.09">世尊！我於今者具信、戒、捨。具足三支。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.10">佛告摩訶男：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza154.11">雖具三事，然不數往僧坊精舍。以是因緣，名不具足。應勤方便，數往塔寺。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.12">時摩訶男言：</p>
        <q who="mahanama">
          <p n="bza154.13">諸優婆塞！我今應當具足信、戒及以捨心，詣於塔寺。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.14">佛告摩訶男：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza154.15">若能具足信、戒、捨心，數詣塔寺，親近眾僧，是名具足。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.16">佛告摩訶男：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza154.17">雖復具足如上四事，若不聽法，名不具足。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.18">摩訶男言：</p>
        <q who="mahanama">
          <p n="bza154.19">我能聽法。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.20">佛復告摩訶男：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza154.21">雖能聽經，若不受持，亦名不具。雖能受持，不解其義，亦名不具。雖<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0432a" n="0432a"/>解義趣，而未能得如說修行，亦名不具。若能具足信、戒、捨心，數往塔寺聽法、受持、解其義趣、如說修行，是則<app n="fnT02p0432n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">名</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>名為滿足之行。摩訶男！雖復具足信、戒、捨心，數詣塔寺，親近眾僧，然猶未能專心聽法，是亦名為行不具足。以斯義故，應當方便，專心聽法。雖能聽法，若不受持，亦名不具。是故應當受持正法。雖能受持，若不解義，亦名不具。是故應當解其言趣。雖解義<app n="fnT02p0432n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">味</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">趣</rdg>
            </app>味，若復不能如說修行，亦名不具。是故應當如說修行。若能具足信心、持戒及捨心等，數往僧坊、專心聽法、受持莫忘、解其義趣，信、戒、捨心、往詣塔寺、聽受經法、受持不忘、解其義趣，若復不能如說修行，是亦名為不具足也。摩訶男！優婆塞以信心故，則能持戒；以持戒故，能具捨心；具捨心故，能往詣僧坊；往詣僧坊故，能專心聽法；專心聽法故，則能受持；能受持故，解其義趣；解其義趣，能如說修行；能如說修行故，勤作方便，能令滿足。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.22">時摩訶男復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="mahanama">
          <p n="bza154.23">世尊！云何優婆塞具足幾支，自利、未利於他？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.24">佛告摩訶男：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza154.25">具足八支，能自利益，未利於他。何等為八？優婆塞！己有信，不能教他。自持淨戒，不能教人。令持禁戒，自修於捨，不能教人令行布施。自往詣塔寺，親近比丘，不能教人往詣塔寺，親近比丘。自能聽法，不能教人令聽正法。自能受持，不能教人受持。自能解義，不能教人令解其義。自能如說修行，不教他人如說修行。是名具足八支，唯能自利，不能利他。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.26">時摩訶男復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="mahanama">
          <p n="bza154.27">具足幾法，能自利益，亦利於他？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.28">佛告<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0432b" n="0432b"/>之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza154.29">若能具足十六支者，如是之人能自他利，自生信心，教人令<app n="fnT02p0432n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">得</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">信</rdg>
            </app>得。自行受持，教人受持。自行捨心，亦復教人令行捨心。身自往詣僧坊塔寺，亦復教人往詣僧<app n="fnT02p0432n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">坊</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">坊塔寺</rdg>
            </app>坊，親近比丘。自能聽法，亦復教人令聽正法。自能受持，亦復教人令受持法。自解義趣，亦復教人解其義味。自如說行，亦復教人如說修行。若能具足十六<app n="fnT02p0432n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">支</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">支者</rdg>
            </app>支，此則名為自利利他。如斯之人若在剎利眾、若婆羅門眾、若居士眾、若沙門眾，隨所至處，能為此眾作大照明。猶如日光，除諸闇冥。當知是人，甚為希有。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza154.30">佛說是已，釋摩男禮佛而退。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza154">
        <p n="bza154.31">時諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
