<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza128">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0422c18"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza128">
        <p n="bza128.01">爾時世尊遊行於<name type="place">末牢村邑</name>，漸次至於<name type="place">優樓頻螺聚落</name>，在<name type="place">鸚鵡閻無果林</name>中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza128">
        <p n="bza128.02">時驢姓聚落主遙聞世尊遊末牢邑，至優樓頻螺聚落鸚鵡閻無果林，作是思惟：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.03">我聞世尊瞿曇所說之法，能滅現在一切苦習。我亦欲滅現在一切苦習，宜應詣彼，聽斯妙法。彼或為我說於盡滅苦習之道！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.04">時彼驢姓思惟是已，即出聚落，往世尊所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.05">世尊！我聞如來所說之法，能滅眾生現在苦習。善哉！世尊！垂哀矜愍，願為敷演現在能滅苦習之義！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.06">爾時世尊即告之曰：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.07">我若為汝說於過去曾更無量眾苦滅<app n="fnT02p0422n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">苦</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">苦滅苦</rdg>
            </app>苦習法，汝或<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0423a" n="0423a"/>時信，或不信，或樂、不樂。我今亦欲為汝說於未來無量眾苦滅苦習法，而汝或信，或不信，或樂、不樂。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.08">佛復告曰：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.09">我於今者即於此處為汝說於滅苦習法。汝當諦聽，至心受持！諸有眾生，起小苦處，而此苦中種種差別，是等眾苦因欲而生，皆習於欲，欲為根本，欲為因緣。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.10">時聚落主復白佛言：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.11">善哉！世尊！今我根鈍，不解略說。唯願垂愍，廣演斯義，令我開悟！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.12">佛復告言：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.13">今我問汝，隨所樂答。此優樓頻螺聚落中所有民眾，假設有人，盡繫縛之，加諸罵辱，皆悉斬戮。汝頗於中生苦惱不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.14">聚落主言：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.15">雖復憂慘，不必一向生大苦惱。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.16">復白佛言：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.17">世尊！此優樓頻螺聚落之中是我愛者，則能生我憂、悲、苦、惱，心不悅豫；非我愛者，非我所欲，非我所念，於斯等邊我則無有憂、悲、苦、惱。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.18">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.19">聚落主！是故當知：一切種種苦惱之生，皆由於欲，悉因於欲，欲為根本。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.20">佛復告言：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.21">聚落主！於汝意云何？若汝子未生，未依於母，未見聞時，頗於彼所有欲親昵，愛念心不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.22">對曰：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.23">無也。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.24">佛復告言：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.25">汝子依母，而生長已，汝若見時，頗生欲親、愛念以不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.26">對曰：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.27">實爾。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.28">佛言：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.29">汝子依母，生已漸大，設當敗壞，王賊劫奪。若如是者，汝生苦惱、憂悲念不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.30">聚落主曰：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.31">若遭是事，當于爾時我心愁毒，若死，若近死，況復不生憂、悲、苦、惱！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.32">佛復告言：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.33">是故當知：一切種種苦惱之生，皆因於欲，悉從欲生，欲為根本。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.34">聚落主言：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.35">希有！世尊！所說甚善，巧為方喻！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.36">復白佛言：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.37">我子設當在于遠處，遣使往看。使若還遲，我與其母心意不安，怪使遲<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0423b" n="0423b"/>晚：『我子將不平安耶？』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.38">佛言：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza128.39">聚落主！是故當知：眾生苦惱，種種憂悲，皆因於欲，由欲而生，欲為根本。假<app n="fnT02p0423n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">使</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">設</rdg>
            </app>使四愛敗壞變異，便生四種憂、悲、苦、<app n="fnT02p0423n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">惱</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">惱苦惱</rdg>
            </app>惱。若三亦皆生於憂、悲、苦、惱。若有一愛，便生一憂、悲、苦、惱；若無愛者，是則無有憂、悲、苦、惱，離於塵垢。如池蓮華，不著<app n="fnT02p0423n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">于</rdg>
            </app>於水。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.40">說是法時，驢姓聚落主遠離塵垢，得法眼淨，見法，得法，<app n="fnT02p0423n04">
            <lem wit="【大】">解法</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
          </app>解法知法，度疑離惑，不從他心，不趣異道，於佛教法獲得辯力，即從坐起，整衣服，合掌白佛，而作是言：</p>
        <q who=" gandhagata">
          <p n="bza128.41">世尊！我已出離，歸依三寶。從今日夜為優婆塞，盡我形壽生清淨信。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza128.42">聞佛所說，歡喜頂禮而去。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza128">
        <p n="bza128.43">諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
