<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza102">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0410b10"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza102">
        <p n="bza102.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">優樓頻螺聚落</name>
          <app n="fnT02p0410n04">
            <lem wit="【大】">泥</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">尼</rdg>
          </app>
          <name type="place">泥連河</name>側<name type="place">菩提樹</name>下，成佛未久。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza102">
        <p n="bza102.02">佛於樹下獨坐思惟，而作是念：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza102.03">唯有一道，能淨眾生，使離苦惱，亦能除滅不善惡業，獲正法利。所言法者，即四念處。云何名為四念處耶？觀身念處、觀受念處、觀心念處、觀法念處。若人不修四念處者，為遠離賢聖之法，遠離聖道。若離聖道，即遠離甘露。若遠離甘露，則不免生、老、病、死、憂、悲、苦、惱。如是等人，我說終不能得離於一切諸苦。若修四念處，即親近賢聖法者。若親近賢聖法，即親近賢聖道。若親近賢聖道，即親近甘露法。若親近甘露法，即能得免生、老、病、死、憂、悲、苦、惱。若免生、老、病、死、憂、悲、苦、惱，如是等人，即<app n="fnT02p0410n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">說</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">脫</rdg>
            </app>說離苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza102.04">時梵主天遙知如來心之所念，作是念言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza102.05">我於今者當至佛所，隨喜勸善！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza102.06">思惟是已，譬如壯士，屈<app n="fnT02p0410n06">
            <lem wit="【大】">申</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">伸</rdg>
          </app>申臂頃，來至佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面立，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza102.07">誠如世尊心之所念：唯有一道，能淨眾生，……（乃至）得免憂、悲、苦、惱。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza102.08">時梵主天即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <lg n="bza102.09" met="5" xml:id="cg102a">
            <l>唯此道出要<caesura/>斯處可精勤</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0410c" n="0410c"/>欲求遠離苦<caesura/>唯有此一道</l>
            <l>若涉斯道者<caesura/>如鶴飛空逝</l>
            <l>釋迦牟尼尊<caesura/>逮得<app n="fnT02p0410n07">
                <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">于</rdg>
              </app>於佛道</l>
            <l>一切正<app n="fnT02p0410n10">
                <lem wit="【大】">導</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">道</rdg>
              </app>導師<caesura/>當以此覺道</l>
            <l>顯示於眾生<caesura/>常應數數說</l>
            <l>咸令一切知<caesura/>生有之邊際</l>
            <l>唯願說一道<caesura/>愍濟諸眾生</l>
            <l>過去一切佛<caesura/>從斯道得度</l>
            <l>未來及今佛<caesura/>亦從此道度</l>
            <l>云何名為度<caesura/>能度瀑駚流</l>
            <l>究竟於無邊<caesura/>調伏得極<app n="fnT02p0410n11">
                <lem wit="【大】">淨</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">得</rdg>
              </app>淨</l>
            <l>世間悉生死<caesura/>解知一切界</l>
            <l>為於<app n="fnT02p0410n12">
                <lem wit="【大】">具</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">見</rdg>
              </app>具眼者<caesura/>宣明如此道</l>
            <l>譬如彼恒河<caesura/>流赴於大海</l>
            <l>聖道亦如是<caesura/>佛為開顯現</l>
            <l>斯道如彼河<caesura/>趣於甘露海</l>
            <l>昔來<choice>
                <sic>末</sic>
                <corr resp="CBETA">未</corr>
              </choice>曾聞<caesura/>轉妙法輪音</l>
            <l>唯願天人尊<caesura/>度老病死者</l>
            <l>一切所歸命<caesura/>為轉妙法輪</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza102">
        <p n="bza102.10">時梵主天頂禮佛足，即沒而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
