<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza109">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0412c19"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza109">
        <p n="bza109.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza109">
        <p n="bza109.02">時有一梵，起大邪見，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza109.03">我此處常，不見有能生於我宮，況復有能過於我上者！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza109.04">爾時世尊入<app n="fnT02p0412n05">
            <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">于</rdg>
          </app>於三昧，從閻浮提沒，現於梵頂虛空中坐。尊者憍陳如以淨天眼觀於世尊為至何處，即知如來在梵頂上虛空中坐。時憍陳如亦入是定，於此而沒，現梵頂上，處如來下，在於東面。時尊者摩訶迦葉以淨天眼觀於如來為至何處，尋知世尊在梵頂上，復入此定，於此處沒，在如來下，現梵頂上，在於南面。<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0413a" n="0413a"/>尊者目連以淨天眼觀於如來為至何處，尋知世尊在梵頂上，即入是定，於此處沒，現梵頂上，處如來下，<app n="fnT02p0413n01">
            <lem wit="【大】">現</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">在</rdg>
          </app>現於西面。時尊者阿那律復以淨天眼觀察如來為至何處，尋知世尊在梵頂上，亦入是定，於此處沒，現梵頂上，處如來下，在於北面。爾時世尊告梵天言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza109.05">汝本所見，為捨<app n="fnT02p0413n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">已</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">以</rdg>
            </app>已不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza109.06">復告梵天：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza109.07">汝本心念：<q who="brahma">我不見有能生我宮者，況能出過！</q>汝今試觀此等<app n="fnT02p0413n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">天</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">大</rdg>
            </app>天身，容貌光明，勝汝<app n="fnT02p0413n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">已</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">以</rdg>
            </app>已不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza109.08">時梵白佛：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza109.09">唯然，已見。而今見之，斯等光明，昔所不見。而今見之，斯等光明，真為殊勝。自今已後，更不敢言『此處常恒，無有變易。』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza109.10">佛告梵天：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza109.11">此處無常、空、不自在。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza109.12">佛為彼梵種種說法，示、教、利、喜，入如是三昧，從彼梵沒，還<app n="fnT02p0412n05">
            <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">于</rdg>
          </app>於祇洹。尊者憍陳如、摩訶迦葉、阿那律等亦為彼梵種種說法，示、教、利、喜，亦入是定，從彼處沒，還<app n="fnT02p0412n05">
            <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">于</rdg>
          </app>於祇洹。唯尊者大目犍連在彼而坐。爾時彼梵問目連言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza109.13">世尊弟子頗有如汝，有大威德神足者不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza109.14">目連答言：</p>
        <q who="mahamoggallano">
          <p n="bza109.15">諸餘聲聞亦有如是威德神足。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza109.16">尊者目連即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="mahamoggallano">
          <lg n="bza109.17" met="7" xml:id="cg109a">
            <l>牟尼弟子大羅漢<caesura/>有大威德具三明</l>
            <l>得盡諸漏知他心<caesura/>能現神變化群生</l>
            <l>如是聲聞甚眾多<caesura/>是故汝今宜恭敬</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza109.18">時尊者目連說是偈已，種種說法，示、教、利、喜，亦入是定，從彼梵沒，還於祇洹。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
