<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza129">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0423b14"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza129">
        <p n="bza129.01"> 爾時世尊與千二百五十大比丘僧、千<name type="person">優婆塞</name>、五百乞兒而自圍遶，遊行<name type="place">摩竭提國</name>，從一聚落至一聚落，從城至城，（……乃至）到<name type="place">彼那羅健陀城</name>
          <name type="place">賣<app n="fnT02p0423n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">疊</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">㲲</rdg>
            </app>疊園林</name>，於中止住。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza129">
        <p n="bza129.02">時閉口姓聚落主是<name type="person">尼乾陀</name>弟子，聞佛在摩竭提遊，乃至是中到此園林，作是念言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza129.03">我當往白師尼乾陀，然後往詣瞿曇邊。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.04">時閉口姓即往尼乾陀所，頂禮其足，在一面坐。時尼乾陀即告之言：</p>
        <q who="nigantha">
          <p n="bza129.05">汝能以二種論難瞿曇不？如兩<app n="fnT02p0423n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">鍓</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">
                <g ref="#CB04826"/>
              </rdg>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">鑐</rdg>
            </app>鍓鉤，<app n="fnT02p0423n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">鉤</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">釣</rdg>
            </app>鉤取於魚，既不得吐，又不得<app n="fnT02p0423n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">嚥</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">咽</rdg>
            </app>嚥。斯二種論亦復如是，能令於彼不得吐、<app n="fnT02p0423n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">嚥</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">咽</rdg>
            </app>嚥。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.06">聚落主言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza129.07">唯願教我，我當往問。何等二論，能令瞿曇不得吐、<app n="fnT02p0423n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">嚥</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">咽</rdg>
            </app>嚥？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.08">尼乾陀言：</p>
        <q who="nigantha">
          <p n="bza129.09">汝詣彼所，如我辭曰：汝今瞿曇頗欲利益諸家不？若不利益，與諸凡愚有何差別？若言利益，汝今云何將千二百比丘、千優婆塞、五百乞兒從一聚落至一聚<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0423c" n="0423c"/>落，從城至城，破壞諸家？所經之處，為汝踐蹈、摧壞、傷毀。如雹害禾，是名破壞，非為利益！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.10">爾時閉口受其教已，詣賣<app n="fnT02p0423n06">
            <lem wit="【大】">疊</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">㲲</rdg>
          </app>疊林，往<app n="fnT02p0423n10">
            <lem wit="【大】">詣</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">至</rdg>
          </app>詣佛所，粗相問訊，在一面坐，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza129.11">瞿曇！汝今寧可不欲增長利益於諸家耶？汝豈不常讚嘆增長利益者乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.12">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza129.13">我於長夜恒欲增長利益之法。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.14">時聚落主而作是言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza129.15">汝若利益，何故今者於飢饉世與千二百比丘、千優婆塞、五百乞兒俱從一聚落至一聚落，從城至城，破壞諸家？斯非增長利益之法！所為損減，如雹害禾。汝壞人民，亦復如是。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.16">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza129.17">我憶九十一劫已來無有一家以熟食施而致損減。汝今且觀一切諸家多饒財寶，眷屬僮僕，象、馬、牛、羊是富基業。有不從施而得者，不盡從施。我獲斯果報，有八因緣，能壞諸家。若為王賊所侵，為火所燒，大水所漂，失所伏藏，生於惡子，不解生業，威逼用財。惡子無理，用於財貨。一切世人皆云：八事能破居家。我今更說第九之破。言第九者，所謂無常。離是九種，外言沙門瞿曇能破諸家，無有是處。若棄如是九種因緣，言沙門瞿曇能破諸家，不增長者，無有是處。不捨是語，不捨是欲。如斯等人，猶如拍毱，必墮地獄。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.18">時閉口姓聚落主聞是語已，必生驚怖，憂惱厭惡，身毛為竪，起禮佛足，歸命於佛，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza129.19">我今誠心向佛懺悔！我甚愚癡，猶如<app n="fnT02p0423n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾兒，所作不善。今於佛前虛妄不實，下賤妄語。唯願哀愍，聽我懺悔！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza129.20">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza129.21">知汝至心。汝實知罪，實<app n="fnT02p0423n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">知</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">如</rdg>
            </app>知愚癡，猶如<app n="fnT02p0423n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾兒，所作不善。汝於如<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0424a" n="0424a"/>來．阿羅呵作大虛妄、鄙賤之業。今自知罪，誠心懺悔，善法增長，惡事退滅。我今愍汝，受汝懺悔，令汝善法增長，常不退失。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza129">
        <p n="bza129.22">時閉口姓聚落主聞佛所說，歡喜頂禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
