<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza193">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0444a05"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza193">
        <p n="bza193.01">爾時尊者<name type="person">僧提迦旃延</name>在<name type="place">那提城</name>
          <name type="person">群寔迦</name>所住之處。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza193">
        <p n="bza193.02">爾時<name type="person">犢子梵志</name>以緣事故，往詣彼城。既至彼已，營事已訖，即便往彼尊者僧提迦旃延所，相問訊已，在一面坐，白尊者言：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza193.03">我有所疑，欲相諮問。汝若閑裕，聽我所問。願為解說！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.04">尊者告言：</p>
        <q who="sabhiyakaccana">
          <p n="bza193.05">犢子！我聽汝問，然後乃知。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.06">犢子問言：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza193.07">以何<app n="fnT02p0444n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">因</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>因緣故，諸餘沙門、婆羅門有人來問：『死此生彼；死此不生彼，……（乃至）非生彼，非非生彼。』悉皆能答；沙門瞿曇為以此問：『色死此生彼，……（乃至）非生彼，非非生彼。』無義理故，置不答乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.08">尊者告言：</p>
        <q who="sabhiyakaccana">
          <p n="bza193.09">我今問汝，隨汝所解，而答於我。於汝意云何：若因若緣，若行若根本，若行所從生，若色若無色，若有想若無想，以此因、以此緣、以此行、以此根本、以此行所從生，無餘寂滅，無想盡處，若如是等無有因緣，無行無相及盡滅法，如來寧可說死此生彼，……（乃至）說非生彼，非非生彼耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.10">犢子言：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza193.11">迦旃延！如是因，如是緣，如是行，如是根本，如是行所從生，是色是無色，是想是無想，此等諸法皆至無餘盡滅，無想滅盡。是等諸法無有因緣，如來云何而當說之？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.12">犢子聞已，心懷歡喜，問尊者言：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza193.13">汝為佛弟子，從來久近？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.14">尊者答言：</p>
        <q who="sabhiyakaccana">
          <p n="bza193.15">我為佛弟子，始過三年。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.16">犢子言：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza193.17">迦旃延！汝獲大利，能於眾中身、口智慧辯才如是。於少時中能具斯事，實為希有！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.18">犢子言：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza193.19">
            <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0444b" n="0444b"/>我今緣事，欲還所止。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza193.20">尊者言：</p>
        <q who="sabhiyakaccana">
          <p n="bza193.21">宜知是時。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza193">
        <p n="bza193.22">犢子梵志聞尊者語，歡喜而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
