<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza123">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0420b09"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza123">
        <p n="bza123.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza123">
        <p n="bza123.02">時彼城中有善鬪將，為聚落主，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，問訊已訖，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="yodhajivagamani">
          <p n="bza123.03">世尊！我於昔者曾從宿舊耆老邊聞：『若欲戰時，要當莊嚴所持器仗，牢自防護，勇猛直進，無有怯弱，能破前敵，傷殺物命，使餘軍眾皆悉退散。作是事已，命終得生箭莊嚴天。』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza123.04">彼時鬪將作如是問。佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza123.05">止！不須說。汝於今者所問義趣，甚為不善。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza123.06">第二、第三亦如是問。佛復告言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza123.07">汝已慇懃三問於我。汝若能受，當為汝說。諸有戰者，牢自莊嚴，善知鬪術，最為陣首，勇猛前進。如是戰將，豈不作意方便，欲得傷害彼諸軍眾，作是念言：『云何當繫縛於彼，傷害於彼，令其壞盡，寧可不生！』如是念耶？戰將！汝於眾生所起三邪惡業。何等名為三邪惡業？所謂即是身、口、意也。若以如是三不善<app n="fnT02p0420n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">業</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】"/>
            </app>業，身壞命終，得生天者，無有是處。戰將！汝今若如是見者，即是邪見。邪見之業，必生二處：或在地獄，或墮畜生。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza123.08">爾時鬪將聞佛語已，悲泣流淚。佛復告曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza123.09">我以<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0420c" n="0420c"/>是故，三請不說。今為汝說，何故涕泣？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza123.10">時彼鬪將白佛言：</p>
        <q who="yodhajivagamani">
          <p n="bza123.11">世尊！我不為聞是說故而生悲惱。憐愍諸鬪戰者，長夜愚闇，<app n="fnT02p0420n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾孩無智，所作不善，常為此事，於未來世當受大苦！如是惡業而實不得生於天中。若以此業而生彼箭莊嚴天者，實無是處。世尊！我從今更不作於如是邪見。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza123.12">佛即讚言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza123.13">善哉！善哉！汝所說者，甚為希有。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza123">
        <p n="bza123.14">爾時鬪將聞佛所說，頂禮還去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
