<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza136">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0426c14"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza136">
        <p n="bza136.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza136">
        <p n="bza136.02">時有一天，光色倍常，於其夜中來詣佛所。威光熾盛，遍照祇洹，悉皆大明。爾時此天禮佛足已，卻坐一面，而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <lg n="bza136.03" met="5" xml:id="cg136a">
            <l>世間<app n="fnT02p0426n11">
                <lem wit="【大】">天及</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">及天</rdg>
              </app>天及人<caesura/>飲食生歡喜</l>
            <l>世間都無有<caesura/>飲食不生喜</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza136.04">爾時世尊復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza136.05" met="5" xml:id="cg136b">
            <l>若有能信施<caesura/>使心極清淨</l>
            <l>今世若後世<caesura/>飲食福隨逐</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza136.06">爾時此天聞佛所說，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p n="bza136.07">世尊！實為希有，善說斯偈！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza136.08">復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p n="bza136.09">世尊！我憶過去，有一人王，名曰<name type="person">遲緩</name>，然彼國王於四城門施於飲食，城中及市亦施飲食。時王夫人白於王言：<q who="????">王今作福，願聽我等助王為福！</q>王聞其言，以城東門所施之食迴與夫人。王之太子亦白父言：<q who="????">父母修福，我亦樂修！</q>王聞其言，以<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0427a" n="0427a"/>城南門所施之食迴與太子。輔相後來啟白王言：<q who="????">王今修善，夫人、太子皆修福業。唯願聽我助修福業！</q>王聞其言，以城西門所施之食迴與輔相。時有諸臣，復白王言：<q who="????">夫人、太子及以輔相咸修福德。我等今者亦樂助修！</q>王聞其言，即以北門所施之食迴與諸臣。時國中人復白王言：<q who="????">夫人、太子、輔相，咸修福德。願聽我等助修福業！</q>王聞其言，復以布施迴與人民。時典施人白於王言：<q who="????">王之所有於四城門及以布施悉皆迴與夫人、太子、輔<app n="fnT02p0427n01">
                <lem wit="【大】">相</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">國</rdg>
              </app>相、大臣、國中人民，斷於王施，兼竭庫藏。</q>王即答言：<q who="????">先所與者，已爾與盡。自今已後他方小國所可貢獻半入庫藏，半用修福。</q>世尊！我於爾時<app n="fnT02p0427n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">念</rdg>
            </app>長夜修福。我於長夜獲得勝報，常懷喜樂，所受福報無有窮盡，不見邊際。如我所受得大果報，乃知世尊善說斯偈。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza136">
        <p n="bza136.10">時遲緩天子聞佛所說，歡喜踊躍，頂禮佛足，還于天宮。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
