<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza191">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0443b12"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza191">
        <p n="bza191.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza191">
        <p n="bza191.02">爾時<name type="person">犢子梵志</name>往詣<name type="person">尊者大目連</name>所，既到彼已，問訊尊者，在一面坐。爾時犢子梵志問目連曰：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza191.03">何因緣故，若沙門、婆羅門來問於佛：『死此生彼，……（乃至）非生非不生。』默然不答？其餘沙門、婆羅門若見有人來問難者，隨意為說。我昔曾問沙門瞿曇：『死此生彼。』默不見答。『死此不生彼；死此亦生彼，亦不生彼；非生彼，非不生彼。』悉不見答。如斯之義，其餘沙門、婆羅門皆悉答之。沙門瞿曇為何事故，默然不答？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza191.04">目連對曰：</p>
        <q who="mahamoggallana">
          <p n="bza191.05">其餘沙門、婆羅門不知色從因生，不知色滅，不知色味，不知色過，不知色出要。以不能解如是義故著色：『我生彼色；我不生彼著色；我亦生彼，亦不生彼著色；我非生彼，非不生彼。』受、想、行、識，亦復如是。如來如實知色從因生，色從因滅，知色味，知色過，知色出要。如來如實知故，色生，彼心無取著，乃知色非生非不生，亦不取著。受、想、行、識，亦復如是。<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0443c" n="0443c"/>如斯之義，甚深無量，無有邊際，非算數所知，無有方處，亦無去來，寂滅無相。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza191">
        <p n="bza191.06">爾時犢子梵志聞尊者目連所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
