<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza151">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0430c10"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza151">
        <p n="bza151.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">那提迦國</name>
          <name type="place">
            <app n="fnT02p0430n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">瓫</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">瓮</rdg>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">甕</rdg>
            </app>瓫寔迦精舍</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza151">
        <p n="bza151.02">爾時世尊告<name type="person">大迦旃延</name>：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza151.03">定意莫亂，當如善乘，調攝諸根。勿同惡馬，諸根馳散。猶如惡馬，繫之<app n="fnT02p0430n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">槽</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">櫪</rdg>
            </app>槽上，唯念水草，餘無所知。若不得食，斷絕羇<app n="fnT02p0430n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">靽</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">絆</rdg>
            </app>靽。亦如有人，多與欲結相應。以貪欲故，多有<app n="fnT02p0430n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">嫌</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">慊</rdg>
            </app>嫌恨之心，多起欲覺。以有欲覺，生諸惱害，種種惡覺由斯而生。以是事故，不知出要，終不能識欲之體相。若復有人，躭好睡眠。以常眠故，多起亂想，種種煩惱從之生長。以是義故，不知出要、對治之法。若復有人，多生掉悔。以其常生掉悔心故，於諸法相不能分明。當知掉悔為散亂因。以是因緣，不知出要、對治之法。若復有人，多生疑心。以疑心故，於諸法中猶豫不了。以斯義故，不知出要、對治之法。
                            如善乘馬，繫之櫪上。其心都不思於水草，不絕羇<app n="fnT02p0430n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">靽</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">絆</rdg>
            </app>靽。譬如有人，心無欲結，但有淨想。以不染著，是欲想故。亦復不生掉悔、疑等、睡眠之蓋。以其不生五蓋之心，因緣力故，便知出要、對治之法。比丘！如是不依於彼地、水、火、風，亦復不依四無色定而生<app n="fnT02p0430n14">
              <lem wit="【大】">禪 法</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">諸禪</rdg>
            </app>禪<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0431a" n="0431a"/>法。不依此世，不依他世，亦復不依日月星辰。不依見聞，不依識識，不依智知，不依推求心識境界，亦不依止覺知，獲得無所依止禪。若有比丘，不依如是諸地禪法，得深定故，<name type="person">釋提桓因</name>三十三天及諸梵眾，皆悉合掌、恭敬、尊重、歸依是人：『我等今者不知當依何法則而得禪定？』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza151.04">爾時尊者<name type="person">薄迦梨</name>在佛後立，以扇扇佛，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="vakkali">
          <p n="bza151.05">世尊！云何比丘修諸禪定，不依四大及四無色，乃至不依覺觀之想？若如是者，諸比丘等云何而得如是禪定？釋提桓因及諸大眾合掌、恭敬、尊重、讚嘆得斯定者，而作是言：『此善男子丈夫中上，依止何事而修諸禪？』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza151.06">佛告薄迦梨：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza151.07">若有比丘，深修禪定，觀彼大地悉皆虛偽，都不見有真實地<app n="fnT02p0430n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">退</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">過</rdg>
            </app>想，水、火、風種及四無色。此世他世，日月星辰，識知見聞，推求覺觀，心意境界及以於彼智不及處，亦復如是，皆悉虛偽，無有實法，但以假號。因緣和合，有種種名。觀斯空寂，不見有法及以非法。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza151.08">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza151.09" met="5" xml:id="cg151a">
            <l>汝今薄迦梨<caesura/>應當如是知</l>
            <l>習於坐禪法<caesura/>觀察無所有</l>
            <l>天主憍尸迦<caesura/>及三十三天</l>
            <l>世界根本主<caesura/>大梵天王等</l>
            <l>合掌恭敬禮<caesura/>稽首人中尊</l>
            <l>咸皆稱斯言<caesura/>南無善丈夫</l>
            <l>我等不知汝<caesura/>依憑何法則</l>
            <l>而得是深定<caesura/>諸人所不了</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza151.10">說斯法時，大迦旃延遠塵離垢，得法眼淨。薄迦梨比丘煩惱永滅，不受後生，盡諸有結。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza151">
        <p n="bza151.11">時<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0431b" n="0431b"/>諸<choice>
            <sic>此</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">比</corr>
          </choice>丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
