<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza158">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0433c02"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza158">
        <p n="bza158.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">迦毘羅衛國</name>
          <name type="place">尼拘陀園林</name>中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza158">
        <p n="bza158.02">爾時<name type="person">摩訶男釋</name>往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="mahanama">
          <p n="bza158.03">世尊！如我解佛所說之義，獲定心故，而得解脫。若如是者，為先得定，後解脫耶？為先解脫，後得定耶？定與解脫，為俱時耶？所未曾得，所未曾行，過去、未來所未曾生，現在亦無。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza158.04">爾時世尊嘿然不答。第二、第三亦如是問。如來嘿然，悉皆不答。時尊者<name type="person">阿難</name>侍如來側，以扇扇佛。于時阿難作是念：</p>
        <q who="anado">
          <p n="bza158.05">今釋摩訶男以此甚深之義諮問世尊，世尊今者所患始除，氣力尚微，未堪說法。我當為彼略說少法，令其還去。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza158.06">時尊者阿難作是念已，即語釋摩男：</p>
        <q who="anado">
          <p n="bza158.07">如來所說，說於學戒，亦說於彼無學之戒；說於學定，亦說於彼無學之定；說於學慧，亦說於彼無學之慧；說學解脫，亦說於彼無學解脫。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza158.08">時摩訶男白阿難言：</p>
        <q who="mahanama">
          <p n="bza158.09">云何如來說於學戒及無學戒，學定無學定，學慧無學慧，學解脫無學解脫？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza158.10">
          <app n="fnT02p0433n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">阿難言</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
          </app>阿難言：</p>
        <q who="anado">
          <p n="bza158.11">如來聖眾住戒持波羅提木叉，具足威儀，<app n="fnT02p0433n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">行</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">正行</rdg>
            </app>行所行<app n="fnT02p0433n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">處</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>處，於小罪中心生大怖，具持禁戒，是則名為持戒具足。厭於欲惡及諸不善，離生喜樂，入<app n="fnT02p0433n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">于</rdg>
            </app>於初禪乃至入第四禪，是名為禪。如實知苦，如實知苦集，如實知苦滅，如實知苦滅道，如是知見，斷五下分結──身見、戒<app n="fnT02p0433n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">取</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">盜</rdg>
            </app>取、疑、欲愛、瞋恚。彼斷五下分結，便得化生，即於彼處而得涅槃，名阿那含。更不還來至此欲界，是則名為學戒，學定，學慧、解脫。復次更於異時盡諸有漏，得於無漏，心得解脫，慧得解脫，現法取<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0434a" n="0434a"/>證，逮得無生，自知生死已盡，梵行已立，所作已辦，不復受有。當于爾時得無學戒、無學定、無學慧、無學解脫。摩訶男！以是緣故，佛說於學及以無學。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza158.12">時摩訶男聞其所說，歡喜頂禮而去。時摩訶男既去不遠，佛告阿難：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza158.13">此迦毘羅衛國諸比丘等頗共諸釋講論如是深遠義不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza158.14">阿難白佛：</p>
        <q who="anado">
          <p n="bza158.15">此迦毘羅衛諸比丘等每與諸釋共論如是甚深之義。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza158.16">佛告阿難：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza158.17">迦毘羅衛比丘與諸釋等獲大善利，能解如是聖賢慧眼。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza158">
        <p n="bza158.18">諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
