<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza121">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0419b14"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza121">
        <p n="bza121.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza121">
        <p n="bza121.02">爾時尊者<name type="person">摩訶迦葉</name>住舍衛國西園林中<name type="place">毘舍佉講堂</name>。彼大迦葉於日沒時從禪定起，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，而白佛言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza121.03">世尊！以何因緣如來初始制戒之時極為尠少，修行者多？今日何故制戒轉增，履行者少？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza121.04">佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza121.05">如是，如是，眾生命濁、結使濁、眾生濁、劫濁、見濁。眾生轉惡，正法亦<app n="fnT02p0419n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">末</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">未</rdg>
            </app>末。是故如來為諸弟子多制禁戒，少有比丘能順佛語，受持禁戒。諸眾生等漸漸退沒。譬如金寶，漸漸損減，至相似金出。如來正法亦復如是，漸漸損減，像法乃出。像法出故，正法滅沒。迦葉！當知：譬如海中所有船舫，多載眾寶，船必沈沒。如來教法亦復如是，以漸滅沒。如來正法不因地沒，亦非水、火、風之所壞。若我法中生於惡欲，行惡威儀，成就眾<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0419c" n="0419c"/>惡，法言非法，非法言法；非是<app n="fnT02p0419n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">毘尼</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">比丘</rdg>
            </app>毘尼說言<app n="fnT02p0419n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">毘尼</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">比丘</rdg>
            </app>毘尼；犯說非犯，非犯說犯；輕罪說重，重罪說輕，如斯之事出於世者，皆由像法句味相似，令佛正法漸漸滅沒。迦葉！當知：有五因緣，能令法滅，一切咸共忘失章句，善法退轉。何等為五？不恭敬佛、不尊重佛、不供養佛、不能至心歸命於佛，然復依止佛法而住。不敬法、不尊重法、不供養法，於正法中不能至心，然依法住。不恭敬戒、不尊重戒、不供養戒、不能至心持所受戒，然依戒住。不恭敬教授、不尊重教授、不供養教授、不能至<app n="fnT02p0419n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">心</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】"/>
            </app>心向教授者，以不恭敬、尊重、供養，亦不至心向教授故，然復依此教授而住。於同梵行──佛所讚者──不恭敬、不尊重、不供養、不能至心禮拜問訊，然猶依彼而得安住。迦葉！以此上來五因緣故，能令正法漸漸滅沒，衰退忘失。迦葉！復有五因緣故，能令正法久住於世，不沒不退，不忘不失。何等為五？恭敬世尊、尊重於佛、供養於佛，常能至心歸依於佛。於法、於戒及以教授、同梵行者亦應供養、恭敬、尊重、至心向之。以此五種善因緣故，能使正法久住於世，不沒不退，不忘不失。以是義故，應當恭敬佛、法、教<app n="fnT02p0419n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">授</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">法</rdg>
            </app>授、同梵行者。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza121">
        <p n="bza121.06">諸比丘等聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
