<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza101">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0410a03"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza101">
        <p n="bza101.01">
          <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0410n03"/>如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">優樓頻螺聚落</name>
          <app n="fnT02p0410n04">
            <lem wit="【大】">泥</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">尼</rdg>
          </app>
          <name type="place">泥連河</name>岸<name type="place">菩提樹</name>下，成佛未久。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza101">
        <p n="bza101.02">爾時世尊獨坐思惟，而作是念：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza101.03">夫人無敬心，不能恭順於其尊長，不受教誨，無所畏憚，縱情自逸，永失義利。若如是者，眾苦纏集；若人孝事尊長，敬養畏慎，隨順不逆，所願滿足，得大義利。若如是者，觸事安樂。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza101.04">復作是念：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza101.05">一切世間若天、若人、若天世界、若人世界、若魔世界、若梵世界、沙門、婆羅門、一切世間有生類中，若有戒、定、慧、解脫、解脫知見勝於我者，我當親近，依止於彼，供養、恭敬。遍觀察已，都不見於世間人、天、魔、梵、沙門、婆羅門、一切世間有勝於我戒、定、慧、解脫、解脫知見，為我依止。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza101.06">復作是念：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza101.07">我所覺法，我今應當親近、供養、恭敬、誠心、尊重。何以故？過去諸佛，一切皆悉親近、依止、供養、恭敬、尊重斯法。未來、現在諸佛亦復親近、依止斯法，供養、恭敬、生尊重心。我今亦當如過去、未來、現在諸佛，親近、依止、供養、恭敬、尊重於法。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza101.08">爾時梵主天王遙知世尊在優樓頻螺聚落泥連河岸菩提樹下，而作是念：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza101.09">觀察世間若天、若人、若魔、若梵、沙門、婆羅門、一切生類若有勝我戒、定、慧、解脫、解脫知見者，我當依止。然都不見有能勝我者。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza101.10">又復觀察：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza101.11">過去、未來、現在諸佛悉皆親近、依止於法，供養、恭敬、生尊重心。我今亦當隨三世佛之所，應作親近、依止、供養、恭敬、尊重於法。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza101.12">時梵主天<app n="fnT02p0410n05">
            <lem wit="【大】">彼</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】【CBETA】【麗】">復</rdg>
          </app>彼作是念：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza101.13">我當從此處沒，往到<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0410b" n="0410b"/>佛所。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza101.14">時梵主天譬如壯士，屈<app n="fnT02p0410n06">
            <lem wit="【大】">申</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">伸</rdg>
          </app>申臂頃，來至佛所，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <p n="bza101.15">世尊！實如所念，誠如所念！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza101.16">即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="brahma">
          <lg n="bza101.17" met="5" xml:id="cg101a">
            <l>過去現在諸如來<caesura/>未來世中一切佛</l>
            <l>是諸正覺能除惱<caesura/>一切皆依法為師</l>
            <l>親近<app n="fnT02p0410n07">
                <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">于</rdg>
              </app>於法依止住<caesura/>斯是三世諸佛法</l>
            <l>是故欲尊於己者<caesura/>應先尊重敬彼法</l>
            <l>宜當憶念佛所教<caesura/>尊重供養無上法</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza101">
        <p n="bza101.18">爾時梵王讚歎世尊，深生隨喜，作禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
