<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza114">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0415b23"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza114">
        <p n="bza114.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza114">
        <p n="bza114.02"> 爾時尊者<name type="person">摩訶迦葉</name>住舊園林<name type="place">毘舍佉講堂</name>中。時尊者迦葉於日沒時從禪定起，往至佛所，禮佛足已，在一面坐。佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza114.03">汝可教授諸比丘等，當為說法。所以者何？我恒教授，汝亦應爾。我常為諸比丘說法，汝亦應爾。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza114.04">迦葉白佛：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza114.05">是諸比丘難可教授，不能受語！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza114.06">佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza114.07">汝於今者見何因緣而不為<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0415c" n="0415c"/>說？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza114.08">迦葉對曰：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza114.09">若不信者，退失善法，便生懈怠，無有<choice>
              <sic>漸</sic>
              <corr resp="CBETA">慚</corr>
            </choice>愧，愚癡無智，貪著他物，有恚害心，睡蓋所覆，掉動不停，於法疑惑，深著我見，具於煩惱垢污之心，喜瞋失念，<app n="fnT02p0415n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">無</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">心無</rdg>
            </app>無<app n="fnT02p0415n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">暫</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">慚</rdg>
            </app>暫定。有如是等種種不善惡法，決定具有。如斯等人尚無少善，況復增進善法，無有退失。若復有人，具於信心，不退善法，精進不倦，能修慚愧。有智之人，具行善法，無有貪想，遠離瞋嫌，除睡眠蓋，心不掉動，無有疑惑，不著身見，心淨無染，不喜瞋恚，能住心念，具於禪定，善法不退。若有具上種種善法，我尚不說彼人善法停住，況不增長。如斯等人於日夜中善法增長。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza114.10">佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza114.11">如是，如是，如汝所說：<q who="kassapo">若不信者，退失善法，……（乃至）如斯等人尚無少善，況復增長。若復有人，具信心者，不退善法，……（乃至）我尚不說彼人善法停住，況不增長。</q>
          </p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza114">
        <p n="bza114.12">時諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
