<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDesc>
        <glyph xml:id="g046">
          <glyphName>CJK IDEOGRAPH 27900</glyphName>
          <charProp>
            <localName>pronunciation</localName>
            <value>fu2</value>
          </charProp>
          <mapping type="cbeta">[泛-之+(犮-乂+又)] 泼??</mapping>
          <mapping type="cbetaNo">CB02703</mapping>
          <mapping type="UTF-8">E6 B3 BC</mapping>
          <mapping type="unicode">27900</mapping>
          <graphic url="gaiji/g046.gif"/>
          <note>appears in bza130</note>
        </glyph>
      </charDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza130">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0424a05"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza130">
        <p n="bza130.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">那羅乾陀城</name>
          <name type="place">賣<app n="fnT02p0423n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">疊</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">㲲</rdg>
            </app>疊林</name>中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza130">
        <p n="bza130.02">爾時閉口姓聚落主而作是念：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.03">我今欲見沙門瞿曇。不見我師<name type="person">尼乾陀</name>者，不得往彼。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.04">即時往詣尼乾陀所，頂禮其足，在一面坐。時尼乾陀即告之曰：</p>
        <q who="nigantha">
          <p n="bza130.05">今我教汝，作二種難，令彼瞿曇既不得吐，又不得<app n="fnT02p0423n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">嚥</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">咽</rdg>
            </app>嚥。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.06">閉口姓即問之曰：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.07">
            <name type="person">阿闍梨</name>！以何二難能令瞿曇不得吐、<app n="fnT02p0423n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">嚥</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">咽</rdg>
            </app>嚥？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.08">復告之曰：</p>
        <q who="nigantha">
          <p n="bza130.09">汝當往詣彼瞿曇所，作如是言：汝可不為利益、安樂一切眾生？汝亦讚嘆利益、安樂一切眾生之法。若言不為利益、安樂一切眾生，與世凡愚，有何差別？若言我欲利益、安樂眾生，何不一切等同說法，云何而有不為說者？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.10">時聚落主受其教已，往詣佛所，粗相問訊，在一面坐，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.11">汝實不欲利益、安樂諸眾生耶？豈不常讚如是法乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.12">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza130.13">我於長夜常欲利益一切眾生，亦恒讚嘆如是之法。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.14">閉口姓言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.15">若如是者，何不為諸眾生等同說法，有不說者？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.16">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza130.17">我今問汝，隨所樂答。譬如世人，有三種田：有一上田，良美<app n="fnT02p0424n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">
                <g ref="#CB02703"/>
              </lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">沃</rdg>
            </app>
            <g ref="g046">[泛-之+(犮-乂+又)]</g>泼壤，極為上好。第二田者，適處其中好。第三田者，曠野邊遠，沙鹵鹹惡。有諸田夫，先於何田而下種子？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.18">閉口姓言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.19">為利益者，先種良田，望獲大利。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.20">佛告之言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza130.21">若良田盡，次種何田？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.22">閉口姓言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.23">次種中者。種中田已，次種下田，亦復擲子，亦望後時少有所獲。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.24">
          <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0424b" n="0424b"/>佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza130.25">欲知上田，如我弟子──諸比丘、比丘尼。我為說法，初、中、後善，成於己利，句義微妙，滿足利益，具足清白，顯發梵行。彼比丘、比丘尼聽我法已，依止我住，歸依於我，依憑於我。我為舟主，而濟渡之。我為開眼，令得視瞻，住於安樂。彼等聞已，各作是言：『佛為我說。我等咸當盡心修行，<app n="fnT02p0425n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">進</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">長</rdg>
            </app>便於我等長夜利益，得義得樂。』彼中田者，如我弟子<name type="person">優婆塞</name>、<name type="person">優婆夷</name>。我為說法，初、中、後善，成就己利，句義微妙，滿足利益，具足清白，顯發梵行。彼優婆塞、優婆夷聽我法已，依止於我，歸依於我，依憑於我。我為舟主，而濟渡之。我為開眼，令得視瞻，住於安樂。彼等聞已，各作是言：『佛為我說。我等咸當至心修行，<app n="fnT02p0424n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">便</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">使</rdg>
            </app>便於我等長夜利益，得義得樂。』欲知下田，沙鹵惡者，如諸外道。我亦為說，初、中、後善……（乃至）顯發梵行。彼諸外道各能聽受，隨其所樂，乃至一句，解其義趣，亦為彼等於長夜中救濟利益，得義得樂。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.26">時閉口姓聞佛所說，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.27">希有！瞿曇！善說美喻！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.28">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza130.29">為成斯義，更說譬喻。如世人有三種瓫：有一水瓫，堅完不損，無有孔裂，亦無<app n="fnT02p0424n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">滲</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">淋</rdg>
            </app>滲漏。其第二瓫亦完不破，無有孔裂，少有<app n="fnT02p0424n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">滲</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">淋</rdg>
            </app>滲漏。第三瓫者，亦破亦漏。彼人注水，應先何器？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.30">對曰：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.31">先於不破漏者，完器滿已，注第二器。其第二器雖完不破，然小<app n="fnT02p0424n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">滲</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">淋</rdg>
            </app>滲漏。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.32">佛復告言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza130.33">滿是瓫已，更注何處？其第三瓫雖復漏破，亦應注水，為未漏間暫得用故。其第一瓫，喻我弟子──諸比丘、比丘尼。我為說法，乃至令其得義得樂。其第二瓫喻我弟子──諸優婆<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0424c" n="0424c"/>塞、優婆夷。我為說法，乃至得義得樂。其第三瓫喻諸外道。我為說法，若少聽受，乃至令其得義得樂。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.34">時閉口姓聚落主聞佛所說，心生驚怖，憂愁厭惡，身毛為竪，起禮佛足，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="gandhagata">
          <p n="bza130.35">我今誠心向佛懺悔！我甚愚癡，猶如<app n="fnT02p0423n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾兒，所作不善，面於佛前虛妄不實，下賤妄語。唯願哀愍，聽我懺悔！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza130.36">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza130.37">知汝至心。汝實知罪，實知愚癡，猶如<app n="fnT02p0423n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾兒，所作不善。汝於如來．阿羅呵所虛妄下賤，作斯妄語。汝今知罪，誠心懺悔，善法日增，惡事退減。今我愍汝，受汝懺悔，令汝善法增長，常不退失。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza130">
        <p n="bza130.38">時閉口姓聚落主聞佛所說，歡喜奉行，頂禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
