<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza122">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0420a07"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza122">
        <p n="bza122.01">爾時世尊在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza122">
        <p n="bza122.02">時彼城中有伎人主，號曰<name type="person">動髮</name>，往詣佛所。到佛所已，頭面禮足，却坐一面，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="talaputanatagamani">
          <p n="bza122.03">瞿曇！我於昔者曾從宿舊極老伎人邊聞：『於伎場上施設戲具，百、千、萬人皆來觀看。彈琴作倡，鼓樂絃歌，種種戲笑，所作訖已，命終之後，生光照天。』如是所說，為實，為虛？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza122.04">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza122.05">止！止！汝今莫問是事。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza122.06">時彼伎主第二、第三亦如是問，佛悉不答。爾時如來語伎主言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza122.07">我今問汝，隨汝意答。若有伎人，於伎場上施設戲具，彈琴作倡，鼓樂絃歌，以是事故，百、千種人皆悉來集。如此諸人本為愛欲、瞋恚、愚癡之所纏縛，復更造作放逸之事，豈不增其貪、恚、癡耶？譬如有人，為繩所縛，以水澆之，逾增其急。如是諸人先為三毒之所纏縛，復更於彼伎場之上作倡伎樂，唯當增其三毒，熾盛如是。伎主！汝為斯事，命終得生光照天者，無有是處。若有人計於伎場上作眾伎樂，命終生於光照天者，我說是人名為『邪見』。邪見之果，生於二處：若墮地獄，或墮畜生。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza122.08">佛說是已，時彼伎主悲泣墮淚。佛告伎主：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza122.09">以是因緣，故汝三請，我不為汝說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza122.10">爾時伎主白佛言：</p>
        <q who="talaputa">
          <p n="bza122.11">世尊！我今不以聞<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0420b" n="0420b"/>佛語故而便涕泣。我愍如斯諸伎<app n="fnT02p0420n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">人</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">仁</rdg>
            </app>人等，<app n="fnT02p0420n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾愚無智，所作不善！彼於長夜作如是見，於未來世當受大苦，常被欺誑，為人所輕。若有伎人，作如是言：『於伎場上作倡伎樂，命終生彼光照天』者，如是之言，名『大妄語』。若以此業生光照天，無有是處。世尊！我從今日更不造彼如是惡業。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza122.12">佛即告言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza122.13">汝今真實，於未來世必生善處。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza122">
        <p n="bza122.14">爾時伎主及諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
