<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza149">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0429c11"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza149">
        <p n="bza149.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza149">
        <p n="bza149.02">爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza149.03">馬有八種過，世間所知，現在可見。何等為八？ 一者、乘馬之人，控轡<app n="fnT02p0429n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">秉</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">乘</rdg>
            </app>秉策，將即遠路，而彼惡馬嚙銜跳躑，頓絕羈勒，破碎乘具，傷毀形體，是名馬過。 其第二者、御者乘之，不肯前進，而此惡馬騰<app n="fnT02p0429n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">躍</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">踊</rdg>
            </app>躍叵制，破碎乘具。 其第三者、御者乘之，不肯著路，但踰坑塹。 其第四者、若乘之時，不肯前進，<app n="fnT02p0429n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">返</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">反</rdg>
            </app>返更却行。 其第五者、都不畏於御乘之人鞭策之痛。 其第六者、御馬之人，以鞭策之方便，距地二足雙立。 其第七者、御馬之人，意欲馳驟，<app n="fnT02p0429n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">返</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">反</rdg>
            </app>返更臥地，不肯進路。 其第八者、御馬之人，意欲令行，而<app n="fnT02p0429n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">返</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">反</rdg>
            </app>返停住。 於佛法中修學丈夫，亦有如是八種過患。何等為八？
                        若比丘同梵行者有見聞疑事，覺觸己身，即語彼言：『汝於今者稚小無智，不善不了。汝今應當覺觸餘人。云何乃欲覺觸於我？汝自有過，反舉他事。』如是之人，一猶第馬。
                            其第二者、見他比丘有見聞疑罪，同梵行者即便語彼。有罪人言：『汝於<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0430a" n="0430a"/>
              今者犯如是罪。』時有罪人復語彼言：『汝今自犯如是之罪，若懺悔者，然後乃可糺舉我罪。』如是之人猶第二馬所有過失。
                                      其第三者、若有比丘，作見聞疑罪，為他所舉，便作異語。隨於愛、瞋及以怖、癡心，生忿怒。如是之人猶第三馬所有過失。
                                      其第四者、若有比丘，亦復作於見聞疑罪，為他所舉，即便語彼舉事人言：『我都不憶，犯如是罪！』當知此人同第四馬所有過失。
                                      其第五者、若有比丘，亦復犯於見聞疑罪，同梵行者而來舉之。時犯罪人即攝衣鉢，隨意而去。其心都無畏忌。眾僧及舉事者當知斯人，同第五馬所有過失。
                                      其第六者、若有比丘，亦復犯於見聞疑罪，同梵行者而舉其事。時犯罪人即便於彼高處而坐，與諸長老比丘諍論道理，舉手大喚，作如是言：『汝等諸人，悉皆自犯見聞疑罪，而更說我犯！』如是罪，當知斯人同第六馬所有過患。
                                      其第七者、若有比丘，亦復犯於見聞疑罪，清淨比丘糺舉其事。彼有罪人，嘿然而住，亦復不言有罪無罪。惱亂眾僧，當知斯人同第七馬所作過失。
                                          其第八者、若有比丘，亦復犯於見聞疑罪，清淨比丘發舉其事。彼犯罪人即便捨戒，
            <app n="fnT02p0430n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">退</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">過</rdg>
            </app>退失善根，罷道還俗。既休道已，在寺門邊住立一面，語諸比丘：『我今還俗，為滿汝等所願以不？汝今歡喜極快樂不？』當知是人，同第八馬所有過<app n="fnT02p0430n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">患</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">惡</rdg>
            </app>患。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza149">
        <p n="bza149.04">諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
