<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza125">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0421a11"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza125">
        <p n="bza125.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza125">
        <p n="bza125.02">時聚落主名曰<name type="person">惡性</name>，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="candagamani">
          <p n="bza125.03">世尊！如世有人，無所修<app n="fnT02p0421n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">集</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">習</rdg>
            </app>集，惱觸於他，作惱觸語，是故諸人咸稱其人，名為『極惡』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza125.04">佛告聚落主：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza125.05">設有一人，惱觸於彼，作惱害語，出惱語故，<app n="fnT02p0421n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">令</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">設令</rdg>
            </app>令他瞋<app n="fnT02p0421n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">忿</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>忿，以是之故，名為『惡性』。不修正見、正業、正語、正命、正念、正方便、正志、正定。不修正定故，惱觸於彼。以惱觸故，極生瞋忿。以瞋忿故，出瞋忿語。出瞋語故，名為『惡性』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza125.06">時村主言：</p>
        <q who="candagamani">
          <p n="bza125.07">希有，瞿曇！實如所言：以惱觸故，實名『惡性』。我以不修正見故，為彼觸惱。以惱觸故，稱我『惡性』。一切世人咸皆稱我以為『惡性』。從是已來，名為『惡性』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza125.08">村主復言：</p>
        <q who="candagamani">
          <p n="bza125.09">瞿曇！云何得不惱觸？</p>
        </q>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza125.10">無惱觸故，得無惱<app n="fnT02p0421n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">語</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">語佛告聚落主</rdg>
            </app>語。雖復為彼之所惱觸，不惱於他。雖復為彼之所惱語，而不惱語以惱<app n="fnT02p0421n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">于</rdg>
            </app>於彼。雖為他惱，不生心惱。以不惱故，世人咸稱『能忍善』者，亦復於彼生忍善想。若如是者，能修正見。修正見故，正業、正語、正命、正志、正方<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0421b" n="0421b"/>便、正定、正念。修正定故，為他所觸，而不生惱。不生惱故，名為『忍善』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza125.11">村主言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza125.12">希有，瞿曇！所說甚善！實如所言：我以不修正見故，為他所惱。為他惱故，出惱觸言。是以世人稱我『惡性』，皆生惡想，故名『惡性』。不修八正道故，為他所觸，出惱觸語，遂至瞋忿。有是想故，世人稱我以為『惡性』。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza125.13">村主言：</p>
        <q who="candagamani">
          <p n="bza125.14">瞿曇！我從今<app n="fnT02p0421n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">已</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>已後如是惡性、卒暴、我慢、凶險，我當捨棄。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza125.15">佛讚之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza125.16">汝若如是，實為甚善。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza125">
        <p n="bza125.17">時彼村主聞佛所說，歡喜頂禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
