<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza117">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0416c07"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza117">
        <p n="bza117.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza117">
        <p n="bza117.02">爾時尊者<name type="person">摩訶迦葉</name>在於邊遠草敷而住，衣被弊壞，染色變脫，鬚髮亦長，來詣佛所。爾時世尊大眾圍遶而為說法。時諸比丘見迦葉已，皆生是念：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza117.03">彼尊者不知出家所有威儀，衣色變穢，鬚髮亦長，威儀不具！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza117.04">爾時世尊知諸比丘心之所念，為欲令彼生欽尚故，遙見迦葉，即語之言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza117.05">善來！迦葉！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza117.06">尋分半座，命令共坐：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza117.07">我當思惟：<q who="gotamo">汝先出家，我後出家。</q>是故命汝，與爾分座。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza117.08">摩訶迦葉聞斯教已，即懷惶悚，便起合掌，頂禮佛足，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza117.09">世尊是我大師，我是弟子。云何與師同共同坐？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza117.10">第二、第三，亦作是言。佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza117.11">實如汝言：我是汝師，汝是弟子。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza117.12">即命迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza117.13">汝可於彼所應坐處於中而坐。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza117.14">時尊者迦葉即奉佛教，敷座而坐。爾時世尊為欲令彼諸比丘等益增厭惡，自呵責故，為欲讚歎摩訶迦葉<app n="fnT02p0416n10">
            <lem wit="【大】">功德</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">得道</rdg>
          </app>功德，尊重與佛齊故，告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza117.15">我修離欲之定，入于初禪，作意思惟。迦葉比丘亦欲離惡不善，有覺有觀，入于初禪。亦復晝夜欲入初禪。二禪、三禪及第四禪，亦復如是。我若發心，欲入慈心、無嫌怨心、無惱心、遍廣心，善修無量，於其東方作如是心；南、西、北<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0417a" n="0417a"/>方，四維上下，亦作是心。我於晝夜欲修是心，摩訶迦葉亦復如是，欲入慈心、無嫌怨心、無惱心、遍廣心，善修無量，於其東方作如是心；南、西、北方，四維上下，亦作是心。我若修於悲、喜、捨心，我於晝夜常入此心，摩訶迦葉亦復如是，於晝夜中常入此心。我欲滅除惱壞，<app n="fnT02p0417n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">却</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">袪</rdg>
            </app>却於色想，除若干想，入無邊虛空，亦欲晝夜常入此定，識處不用處，非想非非想處，亦復如是。我亦欲入神通等定，能以一身作無量身，以無量身還作一身。我欲觀察諸方上下，入于石壁，無有障礙，猶如虛空。坐、臥空中，如彼鴈王。履地如水，履水如地。身至梵天，手捫日月。若我晝夜欲修是定，迦葉比丘亦復如是，欲入於彼神通等定，能以一身作無量身，以無量身還為一身，觀察四方，四維上下，能以此身入于石壁，無有障<app n="fnT02p0417n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">閡</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">礙</rdg>
            </app>閡，猶如虛空。坐、臥空中，如彼鴈王。履地如水，履水如地。身至梵天，手捫日月。亦欲晝夜常入此定，天眼、天耳及他心智、宿命、漏盡，亦復如是。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza117.16">爾時世尊<choice>
            <sic>我</sic>
            <corr resp="T100">於</corr>
          </choice>彼無量大眾之中稱讚迦葉功德，尊重如是，種種與己齊等。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza117">
        <p n="bza117.17">時諸比丘聞佛所說，<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0417n03"/>歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
