<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza197">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0445c09"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza197">
        <p n="bza197.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza197">
        <p n="bza197.02">爾時<name type="person">犢子梵志</name>來詣佛所，問言：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza197.03">瞿曇！若有愚癡，起如是見，作斯論言：『世間是常。唯此事實，餘則無實。……（乃至）我不生彼，非非生彼。』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza197.04">佛告犢子：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza197.05">不知色者，作是見，作是論說，言：『世間色悉皆是常。』自執此見，以為真實，謂諸餘者，以為虛妄。常無常，亦常亦無常，非常非非常；世間有邊無邊，非有邊非無邊，非非有邊非非無邊；身一神一，身異神異；我死此生彼，死此不生彼，我死此亦生彼，亦不生彼，我死此非生彼，非非生彼。受、想、行、識，亦復如是。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza197.06">犢子言：</p>
        <q who="vacchagotta">
          <p n="bza197.07">瞿曇！若有智者，不取是見，不取是論，亦復不應起如此見，作如斯論言：『世界是常。此見為是，餘見為非。』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza197.08">佛告犢子：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza197.09">若能知色，解其性相，如斯等人不起是見，不作是論言：『世界常無常，亦常亦無常，非常非非常見，亦復如是；世界有邊無邊，亦有邊亦無邊，非有邊非非有邊，亦復如是；身一命一，身異命異；我死此生彼，死此不生彼，亦生彼亦不生彼，非生彼非非生彼，亦復如是。』受、想、行、識，亦如上說。若了知識，解其性相，如斯等人不起是見，不<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0446a" n="0446a"/>作是論言：『識是常。此見為是，餘見為非。識為無常，亦常亦無常，非常非非常見，亦復如是；識有邊無邊，亦有邊亦無邊，非有邊非非有邊，亦復如是；身一命一，身異命異；我死此生彼，死此不生彼，亦生彼亦不生彼，非生彼非不生彼，亦復如是。』不知者，如知者說。見者、不見者，如知者說。解、不解，亦如上說。通徹、不通徹，亦如上說。有相、無相，亦如上說。其義深淺，亦如上說。<app n="fnT02p0446n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">寤寤</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">寐寤</rdg>
            </app>寤寤、不<app n="fnT02p0446n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">寤寤</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">寐寤</rdg>
            </app>寤寤，亦如上說。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza197">
        <p n="bza197.10">犢子梵志聞佛所說，歡喜而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
