<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza126">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0421b11"/>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza126">
        <p n="bza126.02">爾時有聚落主，名<name type="person">如意珠頂髮</name>，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="maniculaka">
          <p n="bza126.03">世尊！我於往日在王宮殿與諸輔相共一處坐，群臣眷屬詳議講論：『所謂作沙門者，為得捉於<app n="fnT02p0421n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">錢</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">財</rdg>
            </app>錢寶，以不得捉金不？』時彼眾中有一人言：『縱令捉者，竟有何過？應當得捉。』有一人言：『不應得捉！沙門釋子不捉金寶。』世尊！如是二語，為得名為稱法而說，為不稱說？若作斯語，非為毀佛，非過言耶？為是佛說，為非是乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza126.04">佛告聚落主：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza126.05">若作是說，斯名謗我<app n="fnT02p0421n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">為</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>，為不稱說，名為過說。然我所說實不同彼。何以故？為比丘者，沙門釋子法不應捉金等錢寶。若捉金等錢寶，<app n="fnT02p0421n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">彼非</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">非彼</rdg>
            </app>彼非沙門釋子之法。佛之教法，轉勝端嚴。佛如是說：<q who=" gotamo">為比丘者，不應捉於金等錢寶。設有捉者，非沙門法。</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza126.06">村主言：</p>
        <q who="maniculaka">
          <p n="bza126.07">我<app n="fnT02p0421n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">以</rdg>
            </app>於彼時於大眾中亦作是說：<q who=" gotamo">沙門釋子實不應捉金等錢<app n="fnT02p0421n13">
                <lem wit="【大】">寶</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">財</rdg>
              </app>寶。若有捉者，宜應自恣，放逸五欲。</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza126.08">時彼村主聞佛所說，頂禮而去。當於爾時阿難比丘侍立佛側，以扇扇佛。<app n="fnT02p0421n14">
            <lem wit="【大】">佛</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
          </app>佛告阿難曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza126.09">汝<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0421c" n="0421c"/>可召諸比丘依此王舍城而<app n="fnT02p0421n15">
              <lem wit="【大】">住</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">依</rdg>
            </app>住止者，盡集講堂。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza126.10">爾時阿難奉佛教已，如佛所命勅諸比丘，盡集講堂。時諸比丘各來集已。阿難詣佛，頂禮佛足，在一面<app n="fnT02p0421n16">
            <lem wit="【大】">坐</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">立</rdg>
          </app>坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="anado">
          <p n="bza126.11">世尊！諸比丘僧依王舍城迦蘭陀竹林者，皆來集在講堂之中。唯願世尊宜知是時！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza126.12">爾時世尊即往講堂，於眾僧前敷座而坐。佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza126.13">有如意珠頂髮聚落主來至我所，頂禮我已，而作是言：<q who="maniculaka">我於往日在王宮殿與諸輔相共議講論：「沙門之法，為應捉持金等錢寶，為不捉耶？」時彼眾中有一人言：「假令沙門捉持錢寶及金銀等，有何過咎！但捉無苦。」復有人言：「沙門之法，法不應捉金等錢寶。」如<app n="fnT02p0421n17">
                <lem wit="【大】">斯</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">是</rdg>
              </app>斯二人，其語不同。此二人言，何者稱法？』</q>我即答言：<q who="gotamo">沙門釋子不應捉持金等錢寶。</q>時聚落主而作是言：<q who="maniculaka">我<app n="fnT02p0421n12">
                <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">以</rdg>
              </app>於昔時於彼眾中亦作是語：<q who="maniculaka">如斯沙門得捉金等及以錢寶，亦應恣令受於五欲。</q>
            </q>時彼村主聞我所說，歡喜而去。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza126.14">佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza126.15">汝等當知：彼如意珠頂髮聚落主於眾人前作師子吼言：『沙門法不應受取金銀錢寶。』汝諸比丘從今已後若有所須，欲捉之者，當作草木及捉糞想。寧捉糞穢，不捉寶物。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza126">
        <p n="bza126.16">時諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜頂禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
