<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza127">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0421c24"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza127">
        <p n="bza127.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">瞻<app n="fnT02p0421n19">
              <lem wit="【大】">波</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">婆</rdg>
            </app>波國</name>
          <name type="place">竭城祇池岸</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza127">
        <p n="bza127.02">時聚落主號<name type="person">王頂髮</name>，來詣佛所，頂禮尊足，在一面坐。佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza127.03">此世間中多有眾生，依二種法：一、貪欲樂，二名習於無益身，事非聖之法，徒受無益損減，習於欲樂，是名下賤、繫累之法。受欲樂者，凡有三種。云何為三？<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0422a" n="0422a"/>一者、聚非法財，殘<app n="fnT02p0422n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">害物</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">物害</rdg>
            </app>害物命，自樂己身，而為己身作正樂因，此亦不名供養父母，亦不名與妻子及其僮僕，亦非親友、知識、眷屬、輔弼己者，亦復不名為供養、供給沙門、婆羅門、諸福田等。若如是者，不修上道，不作樂因，不得樂報，是名第一欲樂。
                        設受欲樂，或時如法，或不如法，或為殘害，或不殘害，以樂己身安樂，父母、妻子、僮僕、親友、眷屬、輔弼己者，悉皆供養供給，與正安樂，然不施與沙門、婆羅門及諸福田，亦復不修正道，不作樂因，不求樂報，不作生天因緣，是名第二欲樂。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza127.04">佛復告聚落主：</p>
        <q who=" gotamo">
          <p n="bza127.05">若有集於財<app n="fnT02p0422n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">寶</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">果</rdg>
            </app>寶，如法而聚，<app n="fnT02p0422n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">而</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">不</rdg>
            </app>而為殘害。以如法故，不造殘惡故，<app n="fnT02p0422n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">修</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">能</rdg>
            </app>修自己身，正受其樂，亦名正理供養父母及與妻子、僮僕、親友、眷屬、輔成己者，皆名正與安樂，正事給養。時時供養沙門、婆羅門，修立福田，修於上道，種於樂因，求樂果報，作生天因緣，是名第三受於欲樂。
                        我今為諸受欲樂者，皆悉同說：設受欲樂，我說下賤；設受欲樂，我說為中；設受欲樂，我說為上。
                        何者下賤？非法聚財，又不非法聚財，自樂己身，而為己身作正樂因，此亦不供養，亦不名與妻子、僮僕、親友、眷屬，亦不隨時供養沙門、婆羅門、諸福田等。不修上道，不作樂因，不得樂報，不作生天因緣，是名為下。
                        何等名中？設受欲樂，或時如法，或不如法，或為殘害，以自樂身，亦復安樂父母、妻子、僮僕、親屬，乃至不作生天因緣，是名為中。 云何名上？所<app n="fnT02p0422n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">謂</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">說</rdg>
            </app>謂如法聚財，不作殘害，身正受樂，正理供養父母及與妻子、僮僕、親友乃至能作生<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0422b" n="0422b"/>
              天因緣，是名為上。
                                      何等無益三種苦身？所謂苦非聖法，無有義利。若有苦身，心已變壞，初犯禁戒，身心內外，一切俱熱。追念此事無時暫離，現在之世不離煩熱，終不能得過人之法，是名初無益苦身法。
                                      若復有人雖不犯戒，心亦不變，然復稱於身心二業，內外俱適。修學是事，現在之世不離煩惱，終不能得過人之法，是名第二無益苦身。
                                      復次若更有人雖不犯戒，心不變異，然復稱於身心二業，內外俱適。修念此事，現在之世不離惱熱，有少增進過人之法，或得少智，或得見法，或少禪定，是名第三無益苦身。
                                          聚落主！我亦不說無益苦行都為一種。有一
            <app n="fnT02p0422n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">苦</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">名</rdg>
            </app>苦行名為下品，復有苦行名為中品，又有苦行名為上品。
                        云何名下？初毀戒時心已變壞，身心內外，一切俱熱。追念此事無時暫離，於現在世不離煩惱，終不能得過人之法，是名為下。
                        云何名中？若復有人雖不犯戒，心亦不變，然復稱於身心二業，內外俱適。修學此事，於現在世不離惱熱，亦不能得過人之法，是名為中。
                        云何名上？若更有人雖不犯戒，心不變異，然復稱於身心二業，內外俱適。修學此事，於今現在不能永斷一切煩惱，有少增進過人之法，或得少智，或得見法，或觸禪樂，是名為上。
                        為──聚落主！──除是二邊，趣向於道，所謂三種欲樂及以三種無益苦身，趣向中道。何等名為捨於三種欲樂之事及以三種無益苦身，向中道耶？
                            聚落主！貪染欲樂，惱害自見，亦惱害他。自他俱害，現集諸惡，於當來世亦集諸<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0422c" n="0422c"/>惡。以此因緣心煩悲<app n="fnT02p0422n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">憂</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">擾</rdg>
            </app>憂，受諸苦惱。設盡欲結，亦無自苦，亦不苦他，亦復無有自他之苦。現在之世不集諸苦，於未來世亦復不集一切眾苦。以是義故，得現法樂，離眾惱熱，不擇時節，得近涅槃。於現在世能得道果，智者自知，明了無滯，不隨他教，是名初中道。
                        聚落主！復有中道，離於惱熱，不擇時節，得近涅槃。智者自知，不隨他教，所謂正見、正語、正業、正命、正定、正方便、正志、正念，是名第二中道。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza127.06">說是法時，王頂髮聚落主遠塵離垢，得法眼淨。爾時王頂髮聚落主知法，見法，得法，度疑彼岸，離於疑惑，不隨他教，不受異見，於佛法中得自在辯，即從坐起，整衣服，合掌向佛，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="rasiya">
          <p n="bza127.07">世尊！我於今日已得出過，歸依於佛，亦復歸依法、僧<app n="fnT02p0422n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">二</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">三</rdg>
            </app>二寶。我持優婆塞戒，從今盡壽歸依三寶。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza127">
        <p n="bza127.09">爾時王頂髮聚落主聞佛所說，歡喜踊躍，頂禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
