<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza113">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0415a05"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza113">
        <p n="bza113.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza113">
        <p n="bza113.02">爾時尊者<name type="person">摩訶迦葉</name>在彼舍衛舊園林中<name type="place">毘舍佉講堂</name>。時尊者摩訶迦葉即於其夜從定而起。從定起已，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐。佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza113.03">汝當教授諸比丘等，指道教<app n="fnT02p0415n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">照</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">詔</rdg>
            </app>照禪定之法，為說法要。何以故？我恒教授是比丘等，汝亦應爾。我常為諸比丘說於法要，汝亦應爾。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.04">迦葉白佛：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza113.05">是諸比丘不能受語，難可教授！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.06">佛告迦葉：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza113.07">汝於今者以何因緣不為說法？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.08">迦葉復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza113.09">今二比丘：一是<name type="person">阿難</name>共行弟子，名曰<app n="fnT02p0415n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">難</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">離</rdg>
            </app>
            <name type="person">難<app n="fnT02p0415n04">
                <lem wit="【大】">荼</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">茶</rdg>
              </app>荼</name>；二是<name type="person">目連</name>弟子，名<name type="person">阿毘浮</name>。是二弟子互諍勝負，各自稱言：<q who="bhikkhu">我知見勝！我所說勝！</q>互共相引，欲決知見及以言說：<q who="bhikkhu">為我說妙，為汝說妙？為我句義具足，為汝句義具足？</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.10">爾時阿難侍於世尊，以扇扇佛。爾時阿難語迦葉言：</p>
        <q who="anando">
          <p n="bza113.11">止，止，尊者！聽我懺悔。如此比丘新入佛法，愚無智慧，未有所解。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.12">尊者迦葉語阿難言：</p>
        <q who="kassapo">
          <p n="bza113.13">
            <app n="fnT02p0415n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">爾止</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">止爾</rdg>
            </app>爾止，阿難！汝莫僧中作偏黨語。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.14">爾時世尊告一比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza113.15">汝可往喚彼二比丘。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.16">時彼比丘奉教往喚，語二比丘言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza113.17">世尊喚汝！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.18">時二比丘承佛勅命，即<app n="fnT02p0415n06">
            <lem wit="【大】">往</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">往詣</rdg>
          </app>往佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面立。爾時世尊告二比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza113.19">汝等二人實作是語：<q who="bhikkhavo">我讀誦多，我所知多，我所說言句偈不闕！</q>欲決勝負，為有是不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.20">時二比丘白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza113.21">實爾，世尊！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.22">佛復告言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza113.23">汝若解我所說修<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0415b" n="0415b"/>多羅、祇夜、授記、說偈、優<app n="fnT02p0415n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">他</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">陀</rdg>
            </app>他那、尼<app n="fnT02p0415n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">他</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">陀</rdg>
            </app>他那、伊帝目多伽、本生、毘佛略、未曾有、優波提舍、本事，是十二部，汝若讀誦，令通利者，是等經中為有勝負以不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.24">時二比丘白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza113.25">世尊！是十二部，實無是說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.26">佛復告二比丘，言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza113.27">說十二部經，為欲除滅諍訟勝負。汝今云何作如是說？汝等愚人作如是解，我豈可有如是說耶？若生諍訟，此非佛法。又復不應出家之法。我佛法中終不如是：<q who="bhikkhu">我勝汝負，……（乃至）我所說法句義具足，汝之所說句義不足。</q>如是諍訟，實非我說。汝二比丘如斯之事，汝應作不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.28">時二比丘即禮佛足，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza113.29">我等聞佛所說，自知有過，實如<app n="fnT02p0415n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾愚，無所知解，作不應作，所作不善，乃共相決種種勝負，實有是過。唯願世尊憐愍我故，聽許懺悔！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza113.30">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza113.31">知汝誠心、慇重懺悔。汝實<app n="fnT02p0415n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾愚，無所知解，所作不善，不如佛教，非出家法，乃諍勝負，各云：<q who="bhikkhu">多知，……（乃至）我所言說句義具足，汝不具足。</q>如是勝負，實不應作。吾今受汝誠心懺悔，使汝善法增長，無有退失。何以故？若能至心，實知有罪，然後懺悔，後莫復作，如是懺者，善法增長，無有退失。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza113">
        <p n="bza113.32">諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜頂禮而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
