<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza185">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0440a02"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza185">
        <p n="bza185.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza185">
        <p n="bza185.02">爾時佛告諸比丘： <q who="gotamo">
            <p n="bza185.03">乃往古昔<name type="place">輸波羅城</name>有優婆塞，所居住處諸優婆塞咸共集會，於其堂上<app n="fnT02p0440n02">
                <lem wit="【大】">訶</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">呵</rdg>
              </app>訶欲之過： <q who="upasaka">欲現外形，如露白骨。又如肉段，眾鳥競逐。欲如糞毒，亦螫亦污。又如火坑，亦如疥人，向火<app n="fnT02p0440n03">
                  <lem wit="【大】">癢</lem>
                  <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【聖】">痒</rdg>
                </app>癢痛，<app n="fnT02p0440n04">
                  <lem wit="【大】">愈</lem>
                  <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">逾</rdg>
                  <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">踰</rdg>
                </app>愈增其疾。又如向風，執炬逆走，若不放捨，必為所燒，亦如夢幻。又如假借，亦如樹果。又如<app n="fnT02p0440n05">
                  <lem wit="【大】">鉾</lem>
                  <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">矛</rdg>
                  <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">牟</rdg>
                </app>鉾戟。欲為不淨，穢惡充滿。如食不消，噦臭可惡。</q> 雖復共集種種言說，<app n="fnT02p0440n02">
                <lem wit="【大】">訶</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">呵</rdg>
              </app>訶欲之過，然其還家各自放逸。時優婆塞所集堂神而作是念： <q who="upasaka">諸優婆塞集會此堂，說欲過患，及其還家，嗜欲滋甚，不名清淨，不依法行。我今為彼作諸觸惱，令其覺<app n="fnT02p0440n06">
                  <lem wit="【大】">寤</lem>
                  <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">悟</rdg>
                </app>寤！</q> 作是念已，時彼堂神於優婆塞集會之時即說偈言： <q who="upasaka">
                <lg n="bza185.04" met="5" xml:id="cg185a">
                  <l>優婆塞集<app n="fnT02p0440n07">
                      <lem wit="【大】">論</lem>
                      <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">會</rdg>
                    </app>論<caesura/>說欲是無常</l>
                  <l>汝等還自為<caesura/>欲流所沈沒</l>
                  <l>譬如深淤泥<caesura/>老牛墜在中</l>
                  <l>如今我觀察<caesura/>優婆塞眾多</l>
                  <l>多聞持禁戒<caesura/>唯說一欲過</l>
                  <l>言欲是無常<caesura/>但空有是言</l>
                  <l>實無棄欲心<caesura/>貪著男女相</l>
                  <l>貪著名非法<caesura/>汝等宜捨棄</l>
                  <l>於佛教法中<caesura/>應如法修行</l>
                </lg>
              </q> 爾時<app n="fnT02p0440n08">
                <lem wit="【大】">天</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">堂</rdg>
              </app>天神說如是偈，諸優婆塞聞是偈已，皆悉解悟，厭惡於欲，剃除鬚髮，信家非家，出家學道，勤行精進，修戒、定、慧，悉皆獲得阿羅漢果。</p>
          </q>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza185">
        <p n="bza185.05">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0440b" n="0440b"/>行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
