<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza228">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0457a29"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza228">
        <p n="bza228.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0457b" n="0457b"/>林</name>，夏坐安居。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza228">
        <p n="bza228.02">爾時世尊與大比丘眾五百人俱，皆是阿羅漢，諸漏已盡，所作已辦，捨於重擔，盡諸有結，正智，心得解脫。唯除一人，如來記彼現身盡漏。於七月十五日自恣時到，佛於僧前敷座而坐。爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza228.03">汝等當知我是婆羅門，於般涅槃受最後身，無上良醫，拔於毒箭。汝等皆是我子，悉從於我心、口而生；是我法子，從法化生。我今<app n="fnT02p0457n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">欲</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">欲說</rdg>
            </app>欲自恣，我身、口、意無過失不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.04">爾時尊者<name type="person">舍利弗</name>在眾中坐，從坐而起，整其衣服，合掌向<app n="fnT02p0457n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">白佛</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho/CBETA" wit="【聖】【CBETA】【麗】">佛白</rdg>
          </app>白佛言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza228.05">世尊！如佛所說：<q who="gotamo">我是婆羅門，於般涅槃受最後身，無上良醫，拔於毒箭。汝等皆是我子，悉從於我心、口而生。是我法子，從法化生。</q>我等不見如來身、口有少過失。何以故？世尊能使不調者調，不寂滅者使得寂滅，苦惱之者能<app n="fnT02p0457n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">使</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">使得</rdg>
            </app>使安隱，未入涅槃者使得涅槃。如來是知道者，是示道者，是說道者，是<app n="fnT02p0457n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">導</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】"/>
            </app>導道者，將來弟子相續不絕。世尊教法次第修道，恒相教習，隨順正法，常應擁護、親愛善法。我等不見世尊若身、口、意有少過失。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.06">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza228.07">世尊自恣說我若身、口、意有所闕短，垂哀教勅！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.08">佛告舍利弗：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza228.09">我不見汝有少過失。何以故？汝──舍利弗！──堅持淨戒，多聞，少欲知足，遠離憒閙，樂於閑靜，有精進，具足定心，智慧、疾智、捷智、展轉智、有大<app n="fnT02p0457n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">種智</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">智種</rdg>
            </app>種智、別智。唯除如來，諸餘智慧無能及汝深遠之智。成就實智，示、教、利、喜，心無嫉妬。見他有能示、教、利、喜，隨喜讚歎。若為四眾──比丘、比丘尼、優婆塞、優婆夷說<app n="fnT02p0457n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">法</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">諸法</rdg>
            </app>法，無有<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0457c" n="0457c"/>疲厭。是故汝今若身、口、意無有少過。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.10">舍利弗<app n="fnT02p0457n13">
            <lem wit="【大】">白</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">白佛</rdg>
          </app>白言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza228.11">世尊！頗見是五百比丘於身、口、意有少過不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.12">佛告舍利弗：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza228.13">我不見五百比丘於身、口、意有少過失。何以故？是五百比丘皆是阿羅漢，諸漏已盡，所作已辦，捨於重擔，逮得己利，盡諸有結，正智，心得解脫。以是義故，我不見是五百比丘若身、口、意有少過失。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.14">舍利弗復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza228.15">世尊終不譏彼小闕，亦不見五百比丘若身、口、意有少過失。世尊！此五百比丘幾具三明，幾得俱解脫，幾得慧解脫？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.16">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza228.17">此比丘眾中九十比丘具於三明，有百八十得俱解脫，其餘之者盡慧解脫。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.18">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza228.19">此五百人離諸塵垢，無有腐敗，悉皆貞實。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.20">爾時<name type="person">婆耆奢</name>在彼眾中而作是念：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <p n="bza228.21">佛今自恣。我今欲說讚自恣偈。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.22">婆耆奢合掌向佛，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <p n="bza228.23">世尊！唯願聽我所說！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.24">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza228.25">
            <app n="fnT02p0457n14">
              <lem wit="【大】">婆耆</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">婆耆舍</rdg>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">婆耆奢</rdg>
            </app>婆耆！隨汝所說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza228.26">婆耆奢即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <lg n="bza228.27" met="7" xml:id="cg228a">
            <l>此十五日清淨朝<caesura/>五百比丘<app n="fnT02p0457n15">
                <lem wit="【大】">同共</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">共同</rdg>
              </app>同共處</l>
            <l>皆悉斷於結使縛<caesura/>盡於後有之大仙</l>
            <l>誠心親近淨世尊<caesura/>悉得解脫離後有</l>
            <l>斷於生死所作辦<caesura/>諸漏已盡滅<app n="fnT02p0457n16">
                <lem wit="【大】">掉</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">調</rdg>
              </app>掉悔</l>
            <l>除貪憍慢斷有結<caesura/>拔愛毒箭滅愛有</l>
            <l>人中師子離諸取<caesura/>盡諸有結滅怖畏</l>
            <l>如似轉輪大聖王<caesura/>群臣翼從而圍遶</l>
            <l>遊行大地至巨海<caesura/>譬如鬪戰得大勝</l>
            <l>無上商<app n="fnT02p0457n17">
                <lem wit="【大】">主</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】">王</rdg>
              </app>主弟子眾<caesura/>悉具三明滅於死</l>
            <l>斯等皆是佛真子<caesura/>離諸垢穢純清淨</l>
            <l>如日親友今敬禮</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
