<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza208">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0451b09"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza208">
        <p n="bza208.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza208">
        <p n="bza208.02">爾時尊者<name type="person">舍利弗</name>往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐。于時如來為舍利弗種種說法，示、教、利、喜已，默然而住。時舍利弗見佛默然，即從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0329n06"/>坐起，頂禮佛足，還其所止。未到所住處，道逢梵志，名曰<app n="fnT02p0451n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">優陟</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">憂陟</rdg>
          </app>
          <name type="person">優陟</name>，問舍利弗：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza208.03">從何處來？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza208.04">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza208.05">梵志！當知我於今日詣世尊所，聽法來還。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza208.06">
          <app n="fnT02p0451n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">優陟</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">憂陟</rdg>
          </app>優陟復言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza208.07">汝今故未難於教法，猶如<app n="fnT02p0451n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾兒未離乳耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza208.08">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza208.09">我今聽法，無有厭足，不同<app n="fnT02p0451n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾兒。何以故？<app n="fnT02p0451n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
            </app>孾兒轉大，則離母乳。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza208.10">
          <app n="fnT02p0451n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">優陟</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">憂陟</rdg>
          </app>優陟復言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza208.11">我已久離聽法教<app n="fnT02p0451n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">誡</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">戒</rdg>
            </app>誡。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza208.12">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza208.13">如汝法中雖復教<app n="fnT02p0451n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">誡</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">戒</rdg>
            </app>誡，無有義利。行於非道，不名乘出，不至菩提，是壞敗法。無有一法可恃怙者。汝之師尊，非是如來．阿羅呵．三藐三佛陀。汝今宜應速疾離彼邪師教法。譬如弊牛，志性輕躁，好為<app n="fnT02p0451n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">抵</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">觝</rdg>
            </app>抵突，加復少乳，所生犢子，其形甚小，數數離母，隨意放逸。如汝師尊，無義教法，亦復如是，志性輕躁。所有教法，無有義利。所有弟子，稚小無智。遠離其師，隨意放逸。各自說言：『我已離於教<app n="fnT02p0451n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">誡</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">戒</rdg>
            </app>誡之<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0451c" n="0451c"/>法。』如來法中有義教誡，<app n="fnT02p0451n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">有義教誡</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>有義教誡，有善乘出，趣向菩提，不為邪見之所破壞。有諸善法而可恃怙。我之世尊是如來．多陀阿伽度．阿羅呵．三藐三佛陀。諸弟子等隨逐不捨。猶如善牛，志性不輕，不為<app n="fnT02p0451n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">抵</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">觝</rdg>
            </app>抵突，加復多乳，其犢身體日日長大，隨逐其母，終不捨離。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza208.14">
          <app n="fnT02p0451n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">優陟</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">憂陟</rdg>
          </app>優陟梵志讚舍利弗：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza208.15">善哉！善哉！汝獲善利。所受教<app n="fnT02p0451n10">
              <lem wit="【大】">誡</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">戒</rdg>
            </app>誡，是出世法，趣向菩提，有善乘出，至於涅槃，不可沮壞，有所依憑。汝師世尊是如來．阿羅呵．三藐三佛陀。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza208">
        <p n="bza208.16">作是語已，各還所止。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
