<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDesc>
        <glyph xml:id="g012">
          <glyphName>CJK IDEOGRAPH 17255</glyphName>
          <charProp>
            <localName>pronunciation</localName>
            <value>zang1</value>
          </charProp>
          <mapping type="cbeta">[牛*羊]</mapping>
          <mapping type="cbetaNo">CB00212</mapping>
          <mapping type="UTF-8">E4 8D A7</mapping>
          <mapping type="unicode">17255</mapping>
          <graphic url="gaiji/g012.gif"/>
          <note>appears in bza061; bza089; bza259</note>
        </glyph>
      </charDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza259">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0464b14"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza259">
        <p n="bza259.01">如是我聞：一時佛遊<name type="place">俱薩羅</name>，至<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza259">
        <p n="bza259.02">爾時<name type="person">優竭提舍利婆羅門</name>施設大祀，七百牛王繫之於柱。牸牛、犢子、<g ref="g012">[牛*羊]</g>、羖、羊等，如是種種所有畜生，不可稱計，在祀場中處處繫之。設諸餚膳，種種飲食。爾時餘國諸婆羅門聞彼設祀，悉來雲集。時優竭提舍利婆羅門聞佛從俱薩羅到舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園，欲往佛所，作是念言：</p>
        <q who="uggatasarira">
          <p n="bza259.03">我今設祀，所作會具當問瞿曇將不少耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.04">時婆羅門乘羽葆車，所著衣裳上下純白，提三岐金叉，持金藻盥，滿中淨水。諸摩納眾圍遶左右，餘國種種諸婆羅門亦為翼從，來詣佛所，問訊已訖，在一面坐，具白佛言：</p>
        <q who="uggatasarira">
          <p n="bza259.05">世尊！我於今者設斯大祀，繫七百牛王及諸畜生，乃至餘國婆羅門等，悉來雲集。辦具已訖，欲設大祀。願佛教我滿足，有勝無少減不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.06">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza259.07">婆羅門！汝為祀主，<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0464c" n="0464c"/>大施求福，亦大得罪。豎三種刀，斯名不善。作於苦因，亦得苦報。得於苦利，受報亦苦。云何名為三種刀？意、口、身刀也。何名意刀？汝若祀時，意業不善，殺諸畜生，以為大祀，是名豎於意刀。何者口刀？汝欲祀時，而作是言：『我於明日當殺爾許種種生命。』是名豎於口刀。云何名為身刀？汝若祀時，手牽牛王及諸畜生，受於咒願，是名豎於身刀。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.08">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza259.09">又有三種火，最勝、最妙，宜應謹慎，亦當恭敬。非汝所事，邪見火也。何謂為三？一名、恭敬火，二名、苦樂俱火，三名、福田火。云何名為恭敬火？應當供養、尊重、恭敬、擁護父母。何以故？父母求子，禱祀神祇，然後得子。父母赤白，和合成身，生育長養。以是之故，名恭敬火。如是之火，應正供養，與眾快樂，令無乏苦。云何名為苦樂俱火？若族姓子起於精勤，積集錢財，於其妻子并諸眷屬、奴婢、僕使、知友、輔相及諸親族，皆應供養，供給所須，與其利樂。如是等輩，皆同苦樂。是名苦樂俱火。云何名為福田火？若沙門、婆羅門能斷貪欲，解脫貪欲；能斷瞋恚，解脫瞋恚；能斷愚癡，解脫愚癡。如是等沙門、婆羅門，名福田火。上趣諸天，能招樂報。此名福田火。是以族姓子應當至心供養、恭敬，使得快樂。又有三種火，必應滅之。何者三火？所謂貪欲、愚癡、瞋恚火。不如世間火，有時須然，有時須滅。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.10">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza259.11" met="5" xml:id="cg259a">
            <l>恭敬俱福田<caesura/>此三火應祀</l>
            <l>若勤心供養<caesura/>獲得三種樂</l>
            <l>云何為三樂<caesura/>施戒及修定</l>
            <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0465a" n="0465a"/>
            <l>三種之果報<caesura/>人天涅槃樂</l>
            <l>若人於一切<caesura/>善解於方法</l>
            <l>於祠祀時節<caesura/>能養其眷屬</l>
            <l>供養應供者<caesura/>能供養應供</l>
            <l>終竟必獲得<caesura/>永離災患處</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.12">爾時優竭提舍利婆羅門聞佛所說，即語<name type="person">烏答摩納</name>：</p>
        <q who="uggatasarira">
          <p n="bza259.13">汝可往詣彼祀場中，先所繫養諸畜生等，以係祀者今悉散放，隨逐水草。盡其壽命，莫作拘礙。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.14">烏答摩納言：</p>
        <q who="matuposako">
          <p n="bza259.15">和上如所教敕，我能為之！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.16">即往祀場，宣告諸人：</p>
        <q who="matuposako">
          <p n="bza259.17">我受優竭提舍利教敕，一切畜生，悉皆解放，任意令去。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.18">烏答摩納往祀場所未久之間，如來於後即為優竭提舍利婆羅門，如諸佛法為說法要，示、教、利、喜。時婆羅門即受禁戒，乃至見諦。（餘如突羅闍品中所說。）時優竭提舍利婆羅門即整衣服，頂禮佛足，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="uggatasarira">
          <p n="bza259.19">世尊！唯願明日與諸大眾往祀場中，受我供設！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.20">爾時世尊默然受請。時婆羅門聞佛所說，又見受請，歡喜而去。時婆羅門至祀場已，通夜辦具種種餚膳，乃至敷座，又具淨水。後日晨朝往詣佛所，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="uggatasarira">
          <p n="bza259.21">時到！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza259.22">爾時如來與諸大眾著衣持缽，往詣祀場，在眾僧前敷座而坐。時婆羅門睹佛、大眾寂然坐定，手行淨水，施設種種餚膳飲食。食訖，攝缽。時婆羅門在世尊前敷座而坐，願樂聽法。爾時如來即為咒願：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza259.23" met="5" xml:id="cg259b">
            <l>於諸大祀中<caesura/>祠祀火為上</l>
            <l>婆羅門書中<caesura/>薩婆底為上</l>
            <l>一切國土中<caesura/>人王最為上</l>
            <l>百川眾流中<caesura/>海水最為上</l>
            <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0465b" n="0465b"/>
            <l>列宿麗于天<caesura/>月光最為上</l>
            <l>一切眾明中<caesura/>日光最為上</l>
            <l>十方世界中<caesura/>佛為第一尊</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza259">
        <p n="bza259.24">爾時世尊為婆羅門，種種說法，示、教、利、喜，從座而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
