<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza203">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0449a04"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza203">
        <p n="bza203.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza203">
        <p n="bza203.02">爾時<name type="person">長爪梵志</name>往詣佛所，在一面坐，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="dīghanakha">
          <p n="bza203.03">如我今者，於一切法悉不忍受。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza203.04">佛告長爪梵志：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza203.05">汝於諸法悉不忍者，見是忍不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza203.06">長爪復言：</p>
        <q who="dīghanakha">
          <p n="bza203.07">如此之見，我亦不忍。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza203.08">佛告長爪梵志：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza203.09">汝若不忍如是見者，何故而言：<q who="dīghanakha">我於諸法悉皆不忍。</q>？誰為汝出不忍之語？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza203.10">佛復告<app n="fnT02p0449n02">
            <lem wit="【大】">大姓</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">火性</rdg>
          </app>大姓：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza203.11">汝若知若見，不忍是見，即斷是見，已棄是見。譬如有人，既嘔吐已，若如是者於餘見中即不次第，便為不取，便是不生。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza203.12">長爪梵志復作是念：</p>
        <q who="dīghanakha">
          <p n="bza203.13">汝所言我已斷是見，已棄是見。譬如人吐，便於諸見無有次第，不取不生。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza203.14">佛告長爪：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza203.15">若如是者，多有眾生同汝<app n="fnT02p0449n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">所</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">不</rdg>
            </app>所見，亦復如是論者。諸有異道沙門婆羅門若捨是見，更不受異見，是名少智，極為尠薄，亦名愚癡。梵志！當知世間眾生，皆依三見：初言『我忍一切』，第二言『一切不忍』，第三言『我少忍，少不忍』。賢聖弟子觀察初見，能起貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡，常為如是三毒纏縛，不得遠離，能生患害，能生結使，不得解脫。憙樂於欲，守護縛著，是名為忍。若不忍者，能生貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡，常為如斯三毒所纏，不能遠離，獲得解脫。憙樂於欲，常為愛取，守護縛著，是名不忍。若見少忍，少不忍，亦復如是忍，如上忍中說。不忍，如上不忍中說。賢聖弟子若說言忍，便為與彼二見共諍。若言不忍，亦復與彼二見共諍。若言少忍，少不忍，<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0449b" n="0449b"/>亦與二見共諍。以己所見，違於他故，便起諍論。若起諍論，必相毀害。以共諍論，生毀害故，以見是過，生諸諍論故，便棄是見，不受餘見。以<app n="fnT02p0449n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">是</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">見</rdg>
            </app>是義故，能斷是見，棄離是見。猶如人吐，於諸見中無有次第，不取不生。賢聖弟子若言忍及以不忍，少忍，少不忍亦有是過。如是──梵志！──此色顯現四大所成。賢聖弟子見是身無常，既見無常，便能離欲。見此身滅，即便捨離。若見身無常，便離身欲，便離身愛，離身窟宅，除身決定想。梵志！當知<app n="fnT02p0449n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">受</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">受身</rdg>
            </app>受有三種：苦受、樂受、不苦不樂受。如此三受以何為因？云何為習？因何而生，從何處出？以觸為因。因觸生習。習從觸生，因觸所生。若觸滅，則受滅，離熱得涼。譬如日沒，身邊命邊，受身邊時知是身邊，受命邊時知是命邊。如實而知，無有錯謬。賢聖弟子若受樂受，知身必壞；若受苦受、不苦不樂受，知身必壞。若受樂受，非和合受。<app n="fnT02p0449n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">苦</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">若</rdg>
            </app>苦受、不苦不樂受，亦復如是。云何名為與受不和合？所謂貪欲、瞋恚、愚癡，不與生、老、病、死而共和合。憂、悲、苦、惱，眾苦聚集。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza203.16">爾時尊者<name type="person">舍利弗</name>出家半月，侍如來側，以扇扇佛。于時如來為說斷<app n="fnT02p0449n07">
            <lem wit="【大】">於</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">漏</rdg>
          </app>於離欲之法，時舍利弗如是觀察諸法無常，即便離欲證成，棄捨諸見，無生漏盡，心得解脫。長爪梵志於諸法中得法眼淨。如上所說，既得信心，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza203.17">唯願世尊聽我出家！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza203.18">爾時如來即聽出家。既出家已，懃修精進，得阿羅漢道。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
