<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDesc>
        <glyph xml:id="g023">
          <glyphName>CJK IDEOGRAPH 15538</glyphName>
          <charProp>
            <localName>pronunciation</localName>
            <value>die2; yi4?</value>
          </charProp>
          <mapping type="cbeta">[疊*毛]</mapping>
          <mapping type="cbetaNo">CB00626</mapping>
          <mapping type="UTF-8">E3 B2 B2</mapping>
          <mapping type="unicode">15538</mapping>
          <graphic url="gaiji/g023.gif"/>
          <note>
            appears in bza081; bza092; bza110; bza186; bza262; bza322; bza342;
                                    tn0099-0882; tn0099-1197
          </note>
        </glyph>
        <glyph xml:id="g052">
          <glyphName>CJK IDEOGRAPH 19756</glyphName>
          <charProp>
            <localName>pronunciation</localName>
            <value>yi4</value>
          </charProp>
          <mapping type="cbeta">[麥*弋]</mapping>
          <mapping type="cbetaNo">??????</mapping>
          <mapping type="UTF-8">E4 B4 AC</mapping>
          <mapping type="unicode">19756</mapping>
          <graphic url="gaiji/g052.gif"/>
          <note>appears in bza262</note>
        </glyph>
      </charDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza262">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0467a26"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza262">
        <p n="bza262.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza262">
        <p n="bza262.02">爾時世尊晨朝著衣持缽，入城乞食。有一老婆羅門，捉杖持缽，而行乞食。時佛見已，語婆羅門言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza262.03">汝今極老，何以捉杖持缽，而行乞食？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza262.04">婆羅門言：</p>
        <q who="brama">
          <p n="bza262.05">我有七子，各為妻娶，分財等與，我今無分。為子驅故，而行乞食！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza262.06">佛告之言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza262.07">我今為汝說偈。汝能於大眾中說此偈不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza262.08">答言：</p>
        <q who="brama">
          <p n="bza262.09">我能。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza262.10">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza262.11" met="5" xml:id="cg262a">
            <l>生子太歡喜<caesura/>為之聚財寶</l>
            <l>各為娶妻子<caesura/>而便驅棄我</l>
            <l>此等無孝慈<caesura/>口言為父母</l>
            <l>如彼羅剎子<caesura/>垂死驅棄我</l>
            <l>譬如馬槽櫪<caesura/>滿中置穀<g ref="g052">[麥*弋]</g>
            </l>
            <l>少馬無敬讓<caesura/>驅蹋於老者</l>
            <l>此子亦如是<caesura/>無有愛敬心</l>
            <l>棄我使行乞<caesura/>不如杖愛我</l>
            <l>我今捉此杖<caesura/>御狗及羊馬</l>
            <l>行則佐我力<caesura/>闇夜為我伴</l>
            <l>指水知深淺<caesura/>若趺扶杖起</l>
            <l>蒙杖除多聞<caesura/>是杖愛念我</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza262.12">婆羅門受此偈已，誦讀使利。爾時七子在大會中。時婆羅門於大眾中而作是言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza262.13">汝等今當聽我所說！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza262.14">大眾默然。即說上偈。七子慚愧，起來抱父，各共修敬，將父歸家，置本坐處。諸子各出妙<g ref="g023">[疊*毛]</g>二張，奉上於父。時婆羅門即作是念：</p>
        <q who="brama">
          <p n="bza262.15">我今得樂，是瞿曇力！瞿曇即是我阿闍梨。婆羅門法，法應供養和上、阿闍梨。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza262.16">選最好衣，往至佛所，問訊佛已，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="brama">
          <p n="bza262.17">世尊！我今家中得諸利樂，是汝之恩！我經書中說：『阿闍梨者，應與阿闍梨分。和上者，應與和上分。』瞿曇！汝今是我阿闍梨，應憐愍我，受我此衣！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza262.18">爾時世尊以憐愍故，為受是衣。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza262">
        <p n="bza262.19">婆羅門踊躍，從座而起，歡喜而去。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
