<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza217">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0454b11"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza217">
        <p n="bza217.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza217">
        <p n="bza217.02">爾時<name type="person">蓮華色</name>比丘尼於其晨朝著衣持鉢，入城乞食。食訖，洗鉢，收攝坐具，并洗足已，入<name type="place">得眼林</name>，坐一樹下，端坐思惟，住於天住。爾時魔王而作是念：</p>
        <q who="papima">
          <p n="bza217.03">沙門瞿曇在舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園。蓮華色比丘尼著衣持鉢，入城乞食。食訖，洗鉢，收攝坐具，<app n="fnT02p0454n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">至</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">入</rdg>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】"/>
            </app>至得眼林中，坐一樹下，住於天住。我當為其而作擾亂！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza217.04">作是念已，化為摩納，往至其所，而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="papima">
          <lg n="bza217.05" met="5" xml:id="cg217a">
            <l>娑羅樹下坐<caesura/>如華善開敷</l>
            <l>獨一比丘尼<caesura/>汝今坐禪<app n="fnT02p0454n06">
                <lem wit="【大】">耶</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">那</rdg>
              </app>耶</l>
            <l>更無第二伴<caesura/>能不畏愚癡</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza217.06">
          <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0454b" n="0454b"/>
          <app n="fnT02p0454n07">
            <lem wit="【大】">爾</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】"/>
          </app>爾時<app n="fnT02p0454n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">蓮華</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】【聖】">蓮華色</rdg>
          </app>蓮華比丘尼即作是念：</p>
        <q who="uppalavanna">
          <p n="bza217.07">此為是誰，擾亂於我？甚為欺詐！為是人耶，是非人乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza217.08">入定觀察，知是波旬，即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="uppalavanna">
          <lg n="bza217.09" met="5" xml:id="cg217b">
            <l>百千姦偽賊<caesura/>皆悉令如汝</l>
            <l>不動我一毛<caesura/>故獨無所畏</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza217.10">爾時魔王復說偈言：</p>
        <q who="papima">
          <lg n="bza217.11" met="5" xml:id="cg217c">
            <l>我今自隱形<caesura/>入汝腹中央</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0454c" n="0454c"/>或入汝眉間<caesura/>令汝不得見</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza217.12">時比丘尼復以偈答：</p>
        <q who="uppalavanna">
          <lg n="bza217.13" met="5" xml:id="cg217d">
            <l>我心得自在<caesura/>善修如意定</l>
            <l>斷絕大繫縛<caesura/>終不怖畏汝</l>
            <l>我已吐諸結<caesura/>得拔三垢根</l>
            <l>怖畏根本盡<caesura/>故我無所畏</l>
            <l>我今住於此<caesura/>都無畏汝心</l>
            <l>汝軍眾盡來<caesura/>我亦不怖畏</l>
            <l>斷除一切愛<caesura/>滅諸無明闇</l>
            <l>逮得於<app n="fnT02p0454n09">
                <lem wit="【大】">盡滅</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">滅盡</rdg>
              </app>盡滅<caesura/>安住無漏法</l>
            <l>以是故當知<caesura/>波旬墮負處</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza217">
        <p n="bza217.14">爾時波旬而作是念：</p>
        <q who="papima">
          <p n="bza217.15">蓮華色比丘尼善解我心！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza217.16">憂愁悔恨，慚愧還宮。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
