<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza212">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0452c17"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza212">
        <p n="bza212.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">那羅健陀</name>
          <name type="place">
            <app n="fnT02p0452n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">置疊</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">賣㲲</rdg>
            </app>置疊聚落</name>
          <name type="place">菴婆羅林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza212">
        <p n="bza212.02">時聚落中有一梵志，名<name type="person">那利婆力</name>，在彼村住。其年衰邁，已百二十。彼聚落中所住人民咸謂是人真阿羅漢，悉共恭敬，而供養之。然斯梵志有一親友，福盡命終，得生天上。爾時此天作是思惟：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p n="bza212.03">我今若勸是那利婆力詣佛所者，必不信受。我今當教，脫能信我。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.04">作是念已，即往於彼老梵志所，威光炎熾，遍照其人所住之處。即至彼已，語梵志言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p n="bza212.05">云何於己實是怨家，詐現親相？云何於自<app n="fnT02p0452n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">善</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>善親友<app n="fnT02p0452n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">所</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>所視之如己？云何說斷？云何無熱惱？汝今應當心中默念，不應發言。若有能解如斯義者，當往其所，而求出家，淨修梵行。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.06">爾<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0453a" n="0453a"/>時此天作是語已，即<app n="fnT02p0453n01">
            <lem wit="【大】">沒</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">復</rdg>
          </app>沒不現。於是那利婆力梵志聞斯語已，即往於彼<name type="person">富蘭那迦葉</name>所，心中默念，如斯問難：</p>
        <q who="????那利婆力">
          <p n="bza212.07">云何於己實是怨家，詐現親相？云何於自善親友所視之如己？云何說斷？云何無熱惱？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.08">然富蘭那迦葉尚不能知彼心所念，況能答之。復<app n="fnT02p0453n02">
            <lem wit="【大】">至</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">往</rdg>
          </app>至<name type="person">刪闍耶毘羅胝子</name>所，亦作如是，心中所問……（乃至）<name type="person">尼揵陀若提子</name>所，亦復如是，作心中難。彼若提子尚不能知是念，況復能答。<app n="fnT02p0453n03">
            <lem wit="【大】">時</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">爾時</rdg>
          </app>時那利婆力梵志遍至六師，悉不能知如斯之難。</p>
        <q who="????那利婆力">
          <p n="bza212.09">若不能答，我今何為於其法中出家修道。不如還俗，受五欲樂。我今家業甚為豐饒，寧在家居，布施作福！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.10">復作是念：</p>
        <q who="????那利婆力">
          <p n="bza212.11">我當往詣沙門瞿曇所。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.12">作是念已，即往佛所。於其中路復作是念：</p>
        <q who="????那利婆力">
          <p n="bza212.13">沙門瞿曇年少出家，而富蘭那六師之徒，悉是耆舊宿德之人，尚不能知，況彼沙門瞿曇。既是年少，出家未久，學日又淺，而當能解如斯之義。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.14">作是念時，於其中路迴車欲還。復更思惟：</p>
        <q who="????那利婆力">
          <p n="bza212.15">我昔曾從耆舊宿德老梵志所，聞如是說：『出家之人，年雖幼稚，不應<choice>
              <sic>經</sic>
              <corr resp="CBETA">輕</corr>
            </choice>蔑。何以故？年雖幼稚，有大神通及大智慧。』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.16">作是念已，即往佛所，至佛所已，恭敬問訊，在一面坐，心中默念如是四難：</p>
        <q who="????那利婆力">
          <p n="bza212.17">云何於己實是怨家，詐現親相？云何於自善親友所視之如己？云何說斷？云何無熱惱？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.18">爾時世尊知彼梵志心之所念，即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza212.19" met="5" xml:id="cg212a">
            <l>屏處極毀罵<caesura/>百千種誹謗</l>
            <l>面前而讚歎<caesura/>言是善好人</l>
            <l>實能<app n="fnT02p0453n04">
                <lem wit="【大】">辨</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">辯</rdg>
              </app>辨諸事<caesura/>詐偽而不實</l>
            <l>智者應當知<caesura/>此是怨詐親</l>
            <l>
              <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0453b" n="0453b"/>出言詐親善<caesura/>所作無利益</l>
            <l>
              <app n="fnT02p0453n05">
                <lem wit="【大】">智</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">知</rdg>
              </app>智者應當知<caesura/>此是怨詐親</l>
            <l>云何於親友<caesura/>愛重如己身</l>
            <l>不應於親友<caesura/>伺覓其過失</l>
            <l>親友心願同<caesura/>相念常不忘</l>
            <l>如是之親友<caesura/>不為他沮壞</l>
            <l>應當恒敬念<caesura/>愛重如己身</l>
            <l>何故說於斷<caesura/>斷能生喜樂</l>
            <l>亦能得勝利<caesura/>至於寂滅所</l>
            <l>能修於勝果<caesura/>丈夫向正道</l>
            <l>以是義故斷<caesura/>云何得無熱</l>
            <l>得於寂靜味<caesura/>獲得大智慧</l>
            <l>爾時得無熱<caesura/>遠離於諸惡</l>
            <l>入法歡喜味<caesura/>是名為無熱</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.20">爾時梵志聞是偈已，即整衣服，而白佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza212.21">唯願世尊聽我出家！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza212.22">于時如來即聽出家。既出家已，精勤修道，得阿羅漢。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
