<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                      法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                            Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                            text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                            lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                            Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                            edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
            (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
            (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                            comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                            the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                            literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                        English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project is to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The texts are kept in single files in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any changes after 2008 see the revision
                          description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza254">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0462c09"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza254">
        <p n="bza254.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza254">
        <p n="bza254.02">爾時佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza254.03">世有良醫，能治四病，應為王師。何謂為四？一、善能知病，二、能知病所從起，三者、病生已，善知治愈，四者、已差之<app n="fnT02p0462n18">
              <lem wit="【大】">病</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">患</rdg>
            </app>病，令更不生。能如是者，名世良醫。佛亦成就四種之法。如來．至真．等正覺．無上良醫亦拔眾生四種毒箭。云何為四？所謂是苦，是苦<app n="fnT02p0462n19">
              <lem wit="【大】">習</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">集</rdg>
            </app>習，是苦滅，是苦滅道。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza254.04">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza254.05">生、老、病、死、憂、悲、苦、惱，如此毒箭，非是世間醫所能知生苦因緣及能斷生苦，亦不知老、病、死、憂、悲、苦、惱因緣及能斷除。唯有如來．至真．等正覺無上良醫知生苦因緣及以斷苦，乃至知老、病、死、憂、悲、苦、惱，知其因緣及以斷除。是以如來善能拔出四種毒箭，故得稱為無上良醫。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza254.06">爾時尊者<name type="person">婆耆奢</name>在彼會坐，作是念言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <p n="bza254.07">我今當讚如來所說拔四毒箭喻法！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza254.08">即從座起，合掌向佛，而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <lg n="bza254.09" met="5" xml:id="cg254a">
            <l>我今歸命佛<caesura/>愍於群生類</l>
            <l>最上第一尊<caesura/>能拔出毒箭</l>
            <l>世有四種醫<caesura/>能治四種病</l>
            <l>所謂療身疾<caesura/>
              <app n="fnT02p0462n20">
                <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
              </app>孾兒眼毒箭</l>
            <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0463a" n="0463a"/>
            <l> 如來治眼<app n="fnT02p0463n01">
                <lem wit="【大】">病</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">疾</rdg>
              </app>病<caesura/>過於彼世醫</l>
            <l>能以智慧<app n="fnT02p0463n02">
                <lem wit="【大】">錍</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">裨</rdg>
              </app>錍<caesura/>
              <app n="fnT02p0463n03">
                <lem wit="【大】">決</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">抉</rdg>
              </app>決無明眼膜</l>
            <l>如來治身患<caesura/>過於彼世醫</l>
            <l>世醫所療者<caesura/>唯能治四大</l>
            <anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0463n04"/>
            <l>如來善分別<caesura/>六界十八界</l>
            <l>以此法能治<caesura/>三毒身重病</l>
            <l>能治<app n="fnT02p0462n20">
                <lem wit="【大】">孾</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">嬰</rdg>
              </app>孾愚病<caesura/>最勝無<app n="fnT02p0463n05">
                <lem wit="【大】">有上</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">上尊</rdg>
              </app>有上</l>
            <l>故我今敬禮<caesura/>瞿曇之大師</l>
            <l>醫王名迦留<caesura/>多施人湯藥</l>
            <l>復有一明醫<caesura/>名為<name type="person">婆<app n="fnT02p0463n06">
                  <lem wit="【大】">呼</lem>
                  <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【聖】">吁</rdg>
                </app>呼盧</name>
            </l>
            <l>瞻毘及耆婆<caesura/>如是醫王等</l>
            <l>皆能療眾病<caesura/>是等四種師</l>
            <l>治者必得差<caesura/>雖差病還發</l>
            <l>亦復不免死<caesura/>如來無上醫</l>
            <l>所可療治者<caesura/>拔毒盡苦際</l>
            <l>畢竟離生死<caesura/>終更不受苦</l>
            <l>無量億那由<caesura/>阿僧祇眾生</l>
            <l>佛治令盡苦<caesura/>畢竟不還發</l>
            <l>我今白大眾<caesura/>諸賢在會者</l>
            <l>甘露不死藥<caesura/>咸當至心服</l>
            <l>諸人應受信<caesura/>最上治目者</l>
            <l>療身拔毒箭<caesura/>諸醫無與等</l>
            <l>是故宜至心<caesura/>歸命瞿曇<app n="fnT02p0463n07">
                <lem wit="【大】">尊</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">等</rdg>
              </app>尊</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
