<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                      法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                            Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                            text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                            lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                            Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                            edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
            (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
            (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                            comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                            the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                            literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                        English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                          za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                          the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by the Chiang
                          Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                          the project is to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                          the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The texts are kept in single files in
                          an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                          The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any changes after 2008 see the revision
                          description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                          attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                          Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                          and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza258">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0463c27"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza258">
        <p n="bza258.01">如是我聞：一時佛遊<name type="place">俱薩羅</name>，還至<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza258">
        <p n="bza258.02">時有摩納，名曰<name type="person">極慢</name>。其所承藉，七世以來父母真正，博通多聞；既自<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0464a" n="0464a"/>讀誦，亦教他人。其所聞者，聞則能持，四圍陀典已達其趣；娑羅乾陀論及與聲論、毘伽羅論、戲笑之論、毘陀羅論，善解法句，義趣通達，如是種種諸論。容貌端正，才藝過人，難可儔匹。兼生豪族，又處富貴。自恃才力，生大憍慢。於父母所不生敬順及和上、阿闍梨、師長、親屬，斯不敬禮。時極慢摩納聞佛從俱薩羅，至舍衛國祇樹給孤獨園，將往佛所，而作是念：</p>
        <q who="jentapurohitaputta">
          <p n="bza258.03">我至彼時，若沙門瞿曇接待我者，我當問訊；若不問我，當默然還。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza258.04">爾時摩納作是念已，即詣佛所。于時世尊大眾圍遶而為說法。極慢摩納雖往於彼，如來當時聊不顧視。時彼摩納默作是念：</p>
        <q who="jentapurohitaputta">
          <p n="bza258.05">沙門瞿曇都不以我而逕於懷，尋欲歸依！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza258.06">爾時世尊知其心念，即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza258.07" met="5" xml:id="cg258a">
            <l>為義來至此<caesura/>未得便欲還</l>
            <l>何不使獲得<caesura/>稱汝所來心</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza258.08">極慢摩納作是思惟：</p>
        <q who="jentapurohitaputta">
          <p n="bza258.09">沙門瞿曇知我所念！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza258.10">即生信心，欲禮佛足。佛告摩納：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza258.11">我錄汝心，不必禮敬，所為已足。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza258.12">爾時大眾睹斯事已，怪未曾有，咸作是言：</p>
        <q who="jana">
          <p n="bza258.13">沙門瞿曇有大神足。此極慢摩納於己父母、和上、阿闍梨所尚無恭敬，今見瞿曇能自謙下，恂恂恭順！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza258.14">爾時極慢摩納見諸大眾言音，暫止在一面坐，端身正意，而說偈言：</p>
        <q who="jentapurohitaputta">
          <lg n="bza258.15" met="5" xml:id="cg258b">
            <l>當於何等所<caesura/>不應起憍慢</l>
            <l>復更於何所<caesura/>而當生謙讓</l>
            <l>孰能卻眾苦<caesura/>何者與利樂</l>
            <l>供養何者勝<caesura/>為賢智所讚</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza258.16">爾時世尊以偈答言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza258.17" met="5" xml:id="cg258c">
            <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0464b" n="0464b"/>
            <l>供養於父母<caesura/>以空淨滿月</l>
            <l>敬順兄諸親<caesura/>和上阿闍梨</l>
            <l>及餘尊長等<caesura/>於彼不應慢</l>
            <l>宜當自謙下<caesura/>都應悉恭敬</l>
            <l>若見憂惱者<caesura/>應為除諸苦</l>
            <l>亦與其快樂<caesura/>普皆應供養</l>
            <l>若斷貪欲瞋<caesura/>并離愚癡者</l>
            <l>漏盡阿羅漢<caesura/>正智得解脫</l>
            <l>於斯上人所<caesura/>除慢不自高</l>
            <l>應當向歸依<caesura/>合掌而敬禮</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza258.18">爾時世尊為極慢說諸法要，……（乃至）不受後有。……（餘如《波羅蜜闍經》中說。）</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza258">
        <p n="bza258.19">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
