<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza205">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0450a23"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza205">
        <p n="bza205.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza205">
        <p n="bza205.02">時有梵志，名曰<name type="person">重巢</name>，居在於彼<name type="place">須摩竭陀池</name>岸上，於彼眾中作是唱言：</p>
        <q who="????????重巢">
          <p n="bza205.03">我所說偈，若有人能具足分別，顯示其義，我當為其而作弟子。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.04">時諸比丘食時已到，著衣持鉢，入王舍城次第乞食。乞食已訖，即便還歸於其中，路經須摩竭陀<app n="fnT02p0450n04">
            <lem wit="【大】">池</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
          </app>池岸，聞彼梵志作是語已，即還僧坊，收攝衣鉢，洗手足已，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza205.05">世尊！須摩竭陀池岸有重巢梵志，作如是語：<q who="????????重巢">我所說偈，若有人能具足分別，顯示其義，我當為彼而作弟子。</q>唯願世尊往至彼池！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.06">爾時如來默然許之，與諸比丘前後圍遶往詣彼池。爾時重巢梵志遙見佛來，即從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0329n06"/>坐起，敷置高座，語佛言：</p>
        <q who="????????重巢">
          <p n="bza205.07">瞿曇！可就此座。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.08">于時如來即就其座，而告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza205.09">
            <app n="fnT02p0450n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">云</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">聞</rdg>
            </app>云汝自言：<q who="????????重巢">我所作偈，若有人能具足分別，顯示其義，我當為彼而作弟子。</q>為有是不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.10">梵志對曰：</p>
        <q who="????????重巢">
          <p n="bza205.11">實爾，瞿曇！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.12">佛復告曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza205.13">汝所作偈，今當為我誦其章句，吾當為汝分別解說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.14">爾時重巢梵志復敷高床而坐其上，自說偈言：</p>
        <q who="????????重巢">
          <lg n="bza205.15" met="4" xml:id="cg205a">
            <l>若是比丘<caesura/>釋種子者</l>
            <l>應當如法<caesura/>清淨活命</l>
            <l>不宜<app n="fnT02p0450n06">
                <lem wit="【大】">嬈</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">腦</rdg>
              </app>嬈害<caesura/>於諸眾生</l>
            <l>宜應遠離<caesura/>不善諸法</l>
            <l>守意清淨<caesura/>護所受戒</l>
            <l>如是調伏<caesura/>隨順定智</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.16">爾時世尊以偈答曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza205.17" met="5" xml:id="cg205b">
            <l>若稱如是外<caesura/>隨順而履行</l>
            <l>於善丈夫中<caesura/>汝得為最勝</l>
            <l>比丘處閑靜<caesura/>清淨自調順</l>
            <l>不惱害眾生<caesura/>遠離一切惡</l>
            <l>如是調伏者<caesura/>隨順於定智</l>
            <l>柔和善<app n="fnT02p0450n07">
                <lem wit="【大】">濡</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">軟</rdg>
              </app>濡心<caesura/>身口不造惡</l>
            <l>能攝三業者<caesura/>亦名順定智</l>
            <l>為世福田故<caesura/>持鉢<app n="fnT02p0450n08">
                <lem wit="【大】">諸</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">詣</rdg>
              </app>諸家乞</l>
            <l>撿心修念處<caesura/>謙下處卑劣</l>
            <l>除欲棄貪求<caesura/>故獲無所畏</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.18">爾時重巢梵志聞斯偈已，即生念言：</p>
        <q who="????????重巢">
          <p n="bza205.19">沙門瞿<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0450c" n="0450c"/>曇實知我心！我今宜應歸依三寶。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.20">作是念已，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="????????重巢">
          <p n="bza205.21">唯願如來聽我出家！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza205.22">佛即聽許。出家為道，受具足戒，便成沙門，精懃修習，斷諸煩惱，得阿羅漢。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza205">
        <p n="bza205.23">諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
