<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza202">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0448b18"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza202">
        <p n="bza202.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza202">
        <p n="bza202.02">爾時長者<name type="person">須達多</name>好欲詣佛，親近供養，復作是念：</p>
        <q who="sudatta">
          <p n="bza202.03">我若往彼，日時故早，如來猶未從禪定起。我今應先至彼外道所住之處。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.04">即往其所。既至彼已，共相慰問，在一面坐。異學外道問須達言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza202.05">汝可為我說彼沙門瞿曇為作何見？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.06">須達答言：</p>
        <q who="sudatta">
          <p n="bza202.07">如來所說，我不能及其所知見，在吾分外。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.08">外道言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza202.09">汝若不知佛之所見，頗復能知比丘見不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.10">須達答言：</p>
        <q who="sudatta">
          <p n="bza202.11">如斯之事，我亦不知。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.12">外道復言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza202.13">汝若如是，竟何所見？若少所見，請<app n="fnT02p0448n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">聞</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">問</rdg>
            </app>聞其說！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.14">須達復言：</p>
        <q who="sudatta">
          <p n="bza202.15">汝當先說汝之所見，然後我當自說所見。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.16">爾時外道語須達言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza202.17">我所見者，眾生之類是常是實，餘皆妄語。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.18">復有外道語須達言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza202.19">我之所見，一切無常，唯此為實，餘皆妄語。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.20">又復有言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza202.21">亦常無常，非常非無常，唯此為是，餘皆妄語。世界有邊，世界無邊，亦有邊亦無邊，非有邊非無邊。身即是命，命即是身，身異命異。眾生神我，死此生彼，死此不生彼，死此亦生彼，亦不生彼。如是──長者！──我所見者，死此非生彼，非不生彼。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.22">時諸外道各各自說己所見已，語須達言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza202.23">仁者當說！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.24">須達答言：</p>
        <q who="sudatta">
          <p n="bza202.25">如我所見，一切眾生悉是有為，從諸因緣和合而有。言因緣者，即是業也。若假因緣和合有者，即是無常。無常即苦，苦即無我。以是義故，我於諸見心無存著。汝諸外道作如是言：<q who="????????諸外道">一切諸法常，唯此為實，餘皆妄語。</q>如此計者，乃是眾苦之根本也。以貪著斯諸邪見者，與苦相應，能忍大苦，於生死中受無窮苦，皆由計有，世界是常，乃至死後非生於彼，非不生彼。如斯諸見實是有為業集因緣之所和合。以此推之，當知無常。無常即苦，苦即無我。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.26">復有外道語須達言：</p>
        <q who="titthiya">
          <p n="bza202.27">長者！眾生若是業集因緣和合而有，悉皆無常。無常即苦，苦即無我。若如是者，汝今亦復作諸苦本，與苦相應，於生死中受無窮苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.28">須達答言：</p>
        <q who="sudatta">
          <p n="bza202.29">我先已說，一切諸見心無所著。是故我今亦復不著如斯之見。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.30">時彼外道讚須達言：</p>
        <q who="anado">
          <p n="bza202.31">如是，長者！汝<app n="fnT02p0448n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">亦</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">今</rdg>
            </app>亦應當作如是說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza202.32">爾時須達於彼外道異見眾中作師子吼，令諸外道邪見之心皆悉息已，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，以己所<app n="fnT02p0448n09">
            <lem wit="【大】">見</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
          </app>見共外道談論向如來說。佛即讚言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza202.33">善<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0449a" n="0449a"/>哉！應當如是摧諸外道，令墮負處，應熾盛正法之論。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza202">
        <p n="bza202.34">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
