<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza276">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0470a14"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza276">
        <p n="bza276.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza276">
        <p n="bza276.02">爾時<name type="person">提婆達多</name>友<name type="person">瞿迦梨</name>往詣佛所，在一面立。佛告瞿迦梨：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza276.03">汝於<name type="person">舍利弗</name>有緣，莫生嫌想！舍利弗、<name type="person">目連</name>淨修梵行，心意柔軟。汝莫生嫌<app n="fnT02p0470n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">根</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho/CBETA" wit="【宋】【元】【明】【CBETA】【麗】"/>
            </app>根，長夜受諸苦惱！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.04">瞿迦梨言：</p>
        <q who="kokaliko">
          <p n="bza276.05">我信佛語，我隨於佛，然舍利弗、目連實有惡欲。惡欲於彼，實得自在。彼隨惡欲。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.06">佛復告瞿迦梨：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza276.07">汝今勿於彼二人所生嫌恨心！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.08">如是至三。而瞿迦梨雖聞佛言，惡心不改，捨佛而去。去佛不遠，身生惡瘡，初如芥子。須臾之頃，猶如豆許。復漸長大，如毘梨果。身體爛潰，膿血流出。身壞命終，墮大蓮華地獄。時有三天，光色倍常，於其夜中來至佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面立。第一天白佛言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p n="bza276.09">世尊！瞿迦梨是夜命終。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.10">第二天言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <p n="bza276.11">墮大蓮華地獄。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.12">第三天即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="devata">
          <lg n="bza276.13" met="4" xml:id="cg276a">
            <l>夫人生世<caesura/>斧在口中</l>
            <l>由其惡言<caesura/>
              <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0470b" n="0470b"/>自斬其身</l>
            <l>應讚而毀<caesura/>應毀而讚</l>
            <l>口出綺語<caesura/>後受苦殃</l>
            <l>綺語奪財<caesura/>是故小過</l>
            <l>謗佛<app n="fnT02p0470n05">
                <lem wit="【大】">聖賢</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">賢聖</rdg>
              </app>聖賢<caesura/>是名大患</l>
            <l>受苦長遠<caesura/>具滿百千</l>
            <l>入尼羅浮<caesura/>及三十六</l>
            <l>入阿浮陀<caesura/>乃至墮彼</l>
            <l>五阿浮陀<caesura/>誹謗賢聖</l>
            <l>口意造惡<caesura/>入斯地獄</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.14">時彼三天禮佛足已，還於天宮。爾時佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza276.15">汝等欲聞彼阿浮陀地獄壽命長短以不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.16">比丘白言：</p>
        <q who="bhikku">
          <p n="bza276.17">願為我說！我等聞已，信受憶持。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.18">爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza276.19">二十佉利胡麻得波羅<app n="fnT02p0470n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">捺</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">㮈</rdg>
            </app>捺，滿溢一車。有長壽<app n="fnT02p0470n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">人</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">天</rdg>
            </app>人，足滿百年取其一粒。如是胡麻一切都<app n="fnT02p0470n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">盡</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">澌</rdg>
            </app>盡，此阿浮陀地獄所得壽命猶故未盡。此二十阿浮陀觝成一尼羅浮陀，二十尼羅浮陀觝一呵吒吒，二十呵吒吒觝一睺睺，二十睺睺觝一蓮華地獄，二十蓮華地獄觝一大蓮華地獄。瞿迦梨比丘以謗舍利弗、目連故，墮是大蓮華地獄中。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza276.20">佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza276.21">被燒燋柱尚不應謗，況情識類。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza276">
        <p n="bza276.22">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
