<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza209">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0451c11"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza209">
        <p n="bza209.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza209">
        <p n="bza209.02">時有梵志，名曰<app n="fnT02p0451n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">優陟</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">憂陟</rdg>
          </app>
          <name type="person">優陟</name>，往詣佛所，問訊已訖，在一面坐，而作是言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.03">瞿曇！於昔日時諸外道等相與聚集彼大講堂，作種種論。沙門瞿曇在於閑靜修攝其心，智慧辯才。我於是時亦共論議，作如是言：<q who="uttiya">此相應，此不相應。譬如老牛，加復無目。我等亦爾，所有教法甚為鄙陋，盲無慧眼。沙門瞿曇有大智慧，在於閑靜修攝其心。</q>瞿曇！汝今云何教諸弟子？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.04">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.05">我佛法中童男、童女共相聚會，<app n="fnT02p0451n14">
              <lem wit="【大】">歡 娛燕</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">娛歡讌</rdg>
            </app>歡娛燕會，隨<app n="fnT02p0451n15">
              <lem wit="【大】">意</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">喜</rdg>
            </app>意舞戲，是名相應。譬如有人，年過八十，頭白面皺，牙齒墮落，然猶歌舞，作木牛馬，作於琵琶、箜篌、箏笛，亦作小車及蹹毱戲。如斯老人作如是事，名不相應。其有見者，當名此人為作智人，為作癡人？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.06">梵志對曰：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.07">如是之人，名為嬰愚，無有智慧。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.08">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.09">我佛法中相應相順，如童子戲。梵志！當知聖賢法中如童子戲。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.10">
          <app n="fnT02p0451n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">優陟</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">憂陟</rdg>
          </app>優陟白佛：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.11">云何比丘修集善法？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.12">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.13">比丘之法應當遠離諸惡不<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0452a" n="0452a"/>善，修諸善法。不調伏者，為調伏故，應懃修集；不得定者，為得定故，應懃修集；不解脫者，為解脫故，應懃修集；所未斷者，為令斷故，應懃修集；所未知者，為令知故，應懃修集；所不修者，為欲修故，應懃修集；所未得者，為欲得故，應懃修集。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.14">梵志白佛言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.15">世尊！何等不調，欲令調故，應懃修集？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.16">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.17">眼不調，乃至意不調，為令調故，應懃修集。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.18">梵志言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.19">何等不解脫，欲令解脫，應懃修集？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.20">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.21">心不解脫，為令解脫，應懃修集。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.22">梵志言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.23">何等為斷惡，應懃修集？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.24">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.25">斷欲無明與愛故，應懃修集。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.26">梵志言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.27">何等不知，為知故，應懃修集？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.28">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.29">未知名色，為令知故，應懃修集。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.30">梵志言：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.31">何等不修，為修故，應懃修集？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.32">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.33">未修定慧，不得八道，應懃修集。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.34">梵志白佛：</p>
        <q who="uttiya">
          <p n="bza209.35">比丘之行，甚為真實。我今事多，欲還歸家。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza209.36">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza209.37">宜知是時。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza209">
        <p n="bza209.38">
          <app n="fnT02p0451n08">
            <lem wit="【大】">優陟</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】">憂陟</rdg>
          </app>優陟梵志即從<anchor type="variant" n="fnT02p0329n06"/>坐起，還其所止。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
