<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</title>
        <funder>Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會</funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist College
                      法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉, Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.</p>
        <p>The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done in 2009.</p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                            Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                            text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit text
                            lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with Marcus
                            Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm. The digital
                            edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
            (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
            (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                            comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding to
                            the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                            literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly publications (as referenced).
                        English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the Bieyi
                              za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所 and
                              the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by the Chiang
                              Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange 蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of
                              the project is to produce a comparative digital edition and partial translation of
                              the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The texts are kept in single files in
                              an eXist database and are realized via XQuery and XSLT as HTML for the online user.
                              The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any changes after 2008 see the revision
                              description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to CBETA).</p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse
                              and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDesc>
        <glyph xml:id="g047">
          <glyphName>CJK IDEOGRAPH 14865</glyphName>
          <charProp>
            <localName>pronunciation</localName>
            <value>zong1</value>
          </charProp>
          <mapping type="cbeta">[打-丁+(稯-禾)]</mapping>
          <mapping type="cbetaNo">CB00235</mapping>
          <mapping type="UTF-8">E3 A8 91</mapping>
          <mapping type="unicode">14865</mapping>
          <graphic url="gaiji/g047.gif"/>
          <note>appears in bza187; bza188; bza257</note>
        </glyph>
      </charDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza257">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0463b27"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza257">
        <p n="bza257.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza257">
        <p n="bza257.02">爾時<name type="person">尊者婆耆奢</name>來至<name type="place">毘舍佉鹿子母講堂</name>中，遇病困篤。爾時<name type="person">富匿</name>於彼瞻病。時尊<pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0462c" n="0463c"/>者婆耆奢告富匿言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <p n="bza257.03">汝可往詣於世尊所，如我婆耆奢頂禮世尊足下，問訊世尊：『少病少惱，起居輕利，無諸苦不？』</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza257.04">爾時富匿受尊者教，往詣佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐，合掌白佛，言：</p>
        <q who="punniya">
          <p n="bza257.05">世尊！婆耆奢比丘在毘舍佉講堂中病疹困篤，而語我言：<q who="vangisa">往世尊所，稱我名字，頂禮佛足，問訊世尊：「少病少惱，起居輕利，無諸苦不？」</q>
          </p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza257.06">爾時富匿復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="punniya">
          <p n="bza257.07">此婆耆奢或因困疾，即入涅槃。唯願世尊屈意往彼！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza257.08">如來默然，受富匿語。爾時富匿即還詣尊者婆耆奢所，白言：</p>
        <q who="punniya">
          <p n="bza257.09">
            <app n="fnT02p0463n19">
              <lem wit="【大】">和</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">如</rdg>
            </app>和上！我問訊已，復啟世尊：<q who="punniya">婆耆奢或因困病，入于涅槃。</q>世尊默然，聽受我語。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza257.10">爾時世尊從禪定起，即往毘舍佉講堂婆耆奢所。時婆耆奢遙見佛來，自力欲起。佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza257.11">不須汝起。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza257.12">爾時世尊別敷座坐，告婆耆奢：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza257.13">汝今身體苦痛，為可忍不？能飲食不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza257.14">時婆耆奢白言：</p>
        <q who="vangisa">
          <p n="bza257.15">此痛轉增，無有瘳損。今我所患，譬如力<choice>
              <sic>土</sic>
              <corr resp="CBETA">士</corr>
            </choice>，捉儜人髮，<app n="fnT02p0463n20">
              <lem wit="【大】">㨑</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">總</rdg>
            </app>
            <g ref="g047">[打-丁+(稯-禾)]</g>
            <app n="fnT02p0463n21">
              <lem wit="【大】">搣</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】">滅</rdg>
            </app>搣揉捺。我患頭痛，亦復如是。又如大力殺牛之人，以刀刺腹，割其腸肚。我患腹痛，亦復如是。又如瘦人，為有力者強捉火炙，身體燋<app n="fnT02p0463n22">
              <lem wit="【大】">然</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】">燃</rdg>
            </app>然。我苦體痛，亦復如是。我於今日欲入涅槃。我於最後欲讚於佛！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza257.16">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza257.17">隨汝所說。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza257.18">即說偈言。<app n="fnT02p0463n23">
            <lem wit="【大】">本<app n="0463024">
                <lem wit="【大】">無</lem>
                <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">云</rdg>
              </app>少偈</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【聖】"/>
          </app>(本<app n="fnT02p0463n24">
            <lem wit="【大】">無</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">云</rdg>
          </app>無少偈)。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
