<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza260">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0465b06"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza260">
        <p n="bza260.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza260">
        <p n="bza260.02">爾時有摩納，名 <name type="person">僧伽羅</name>，往詣佛所，問訊佛已，在一面坐，即白佛言：</p>
        <q who="sihala">
          <p n="bza260.03">世尊！云何觀察不善丈夫？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza260.04">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza260.05">譬如觀月。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza260.06">又問：</p>
        <q who="sihala">
          <p n="bza260.07">云何觀察善勝丈夫？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza260.08">佛復答曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza260.09">亦如觀月。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza260.10">爾時摩納復白佛言：</p>
        <q who="sihala">
          <p n="bza260.11">云何不善丈夫觀之如月？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza260.12">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza260.13">不善丈夫如十六日，月光漸減，圓滿轉虧，乃至於盡，損減不現。如佛法中不能信心受持禁戒，少所讀誦，若修少施，於其後時懈怠不勤，漸失信心，毀犯禁戒。復不布施，親近惡友，不至僧坊諮受於法。不聽法故，身、口、意業造於不善。以造惡故，身壞命終，墮於惡道。是故當知惡丈夫者，猶如彼月，漸漸損減，乃至滅盡。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza260.14">又問：</p>
        <q who="sihala">
          <p n="bza260.15">云何善勝丈夫亦復如月？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza260.16">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza260.17">譬如初月，光明熾然，漸漸增長，至十五日，圓滿具足。如佛法中能有信心修行禁戒，習於多聞，修於布施，却除邪見，修於正見。於佛法中得純信心，堅持禁戒，善修多聞，能施不慳，具於正見。信心、持戒、多聞、惠施以漸增長，是善丈夫身、口、意行親近善友，具修諸善，身壞命終，得生天上。是故當知善丈夫者亦復如月。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza260.18">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza260.19" met="5" xml:id="cg260a">
            <l>譬如盛滿月<caesura/>處於虛空中</l>
            <l>圓光甚暉曜<caesura/>映蔽於諸星</l>
            <l>亦如具信人<caesura/>戒聞捨貪嫉</l>
            <l>於諸嫉妬者<caesura/>如月蔽眾星</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza260">
        <p n="bza260.20"> 時僧伽羅摩納聞佛所說，<choice>
            <sic>誦</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">踊</corr>
          </choice>躍而去。諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
