<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <charDesc>
        <glyph xml:id="g058">
          <glyphName>Non Unicode Character</glyphName>
          <charProp>
            <localName>pronunciation</localName>
            <value> </value>
          </charProp>
          <mapping type="cbeta">[邱-丘+(卯/亞)]</mapping>
          <mapping type="cbetaNo">CB02706</mapping>
          <mapping type="UTF-8">Non Unicode Character</mapping>
          <mapping type="unicode">Non Unicode Character</mapping>
          <graphic url="gaiji/g058.gif"/>
          <note>appears in bza330</note>
        </glyph>
      </charDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza330">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0485c05"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza330">
        <p n="bza330.01">爾時世尊在<name type="place">毘舍離</name>
          <name type="place">獼猴陂岸大講堂</name>中。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza330">
        <p n="bza330.02">時有四十波利蛇迦比丘，皆阿練若，著糞掃衣，盡行乞食，悉在學地，未離欲法，咸至佛所，頂禮佛足，在一面坐。爾時世尊作是念：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.03">此諸比丘皆阿練若，著糞掃衣，盡行乞食，悉是學人，未斷<app n="fnT02p0485n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">諸</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">欲</rdg>
            </app>諸結。吾當為彼如應說法，令諸比丘不起于坐，心得解悟，盡諸結漏。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.04">佛告之曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.05">比丘當知：生死長遠，無有邊際，無有能知其根<app n="fnT02p0485n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">源</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">原</rdg>
            </app>源者。一切眾生皆為無明之所覆蓋，愛結所使，纏繫其頸。生死長途，流轉無窮。過去億苦無能知者，譬如恒河，流入四海。我今問汝：汝處生死，所出血多，為恒河多？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.06">時諸比丘白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza330.07">世尊！如我解佛所說義者，我處生死，身所出血，多彼恒河四大海水。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.08">佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.09">善哉！善哉！汝從往世所受象身，為他截鼻、截耳，或時截足，鐵鉤<app n="fnT02p0485n14">
              <lem wit="【大】">
                <g ref="#CB02706"/>
              </lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">斵</rdg>
            </app>
            <g ref="g058">[邱-丘+(卯/亞)]</g>頭及以斬項，所出之血無量無邊。又受牛、馬、騾、驢、駱駝、猪、雞、犬、豕，種種禽獸。如受雞形，截其羽翼及其項足，身所出血，是諸禽獸各被割截，所出之血不可計量。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.10">復告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.11">色為是常，是無常乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.12">諸比丘白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza330.13">世尊！色是無常。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.14">佛復問言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.15">色若無常，為當是苦，為非苦乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.16">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza330.17">無常故苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.18">佛復告言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.19">若無常、苦，是敗壞法，於此法中賢聖弟子計有我及我所不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.20">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza330.21">不也，世尊！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.22">佛復告曰：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.23">受、想、行、識為是常耶，為無常乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.24">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza330.25">斯皆無常。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.26">佛復問言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.27">若是無常，為是苦耶，為非苦耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.28">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza330.29">無常故苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.30">佛又問言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.31">若無常、苦，是敗壞法，賢聖弟子寧計是中我、我所不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.32">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza330.33">不也，世尊！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza330.34">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza330.35">善哉！善哉！色是無常，無常故即無我。若無有我，則無我所。如是知實，正慧觀察。受、想、行、識，亦復如是。是故──比丘！──若有是色，乃至少時：過去、未來、現在；若內若外、若近若遠，此盡無我及以我所。如是稱實，正見所見。若受、想、若行、若識、若多若少、若內若外、若近若遠、過去、未來、現在，都無有我，亦無我所。如實知見，賢聖弟子見是事已，即名多聞。於色厭惡，受、想、行、識，亦生厭惡。以厭惡故，<app n="fnT02p0486n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">得</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">則得</rdg>
            </app>得離欲。得離欲故，<app n="fnT02p0486n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">則</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">則得</rdg>
            </app>則解脫。得解脫故，則解脫知見。若得解脫知見，即知我生已盡，梵行已立，所作已辦，更不受有。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0486a" n="0486a"/>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza330">
        <p n="bza330.36">佛說是時，四十波利蛇迦比丘不受後有，心得解脫。時諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
