<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza350">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0488c07"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza350">
        <p n="bza350.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">毘富羅山</name>下。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza350">
        <p n="bza350.02">爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza350.03">諸行無常，是生滅法。無有住時，不可保信，是懷敗法。以是義故，汝諸比丘於諸行所應知止足，生厭惡想，離於愛欲，而求解脫。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza350.04">復告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza350.05">此毘富羅山往昔之時名曰<name type="place">婆耆半闍</name>。爾時此城名<name type="place">帝彌羅</name>。彼時人民壽四萬歲。諸人民等欲上此山，經於四日然後乃能至彼山頂。時世有佛，號迦孫如來．應供．正遍知．明行足．善逝．世間解．無上士．調御丈夫．天、人師．佛．世尊，為諸弟子而說法要，初、中、後善。其義深遠，其語巧妙，純一無雜，具足清白梵行之相。比丘當知：爾時婆耆半闍山相於今已滅，人民盡死，是佛．世尊入涅槃後，人壽轉減。以是義故，諸行無常，是生滅法。無有住時，不可保信，是壞敗法。是故比丘於諸行所應知止足，生厭惡想，離於愛欲，而求解脫。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza350.06">復告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza350.07">乃往昔時此山名曰<name type="place">朋迦</name>。于時此城名<name type="place">阿毘迦</name>。時彼世人壽三萬歲。此諸眾生若欲上山，經於三日便得往還。時世有佛．世尊，號迦那含牟尼如來．應供．正遍知．明行足．善逝．世間解．無上士．調御丈夫．天、人師．佛．世尊。爾時如來普為大眾演說法要。所演說者，初、中、後善。其義深遠，其語巧妙，具足清淨顯發梵行之相。比丘當知：彼佛．世尊入涅槃後，人民轉減。于時山相於今已<app n="fnT02p0489n01">
              <lem wit="【大】">滅</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">減</rdg>
            </app>滅，人民死盡。是故──比丘！──諸行無常，是變易法。不可恃怙，會歸磨滅。汝等應當於諸行所宜知止足，生厭惡想，離於愛欲，而求解脫。</p>
        </q>
        <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0489a" n="0489a"/>
        <p n="bza350.08">佛復告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza350.09">乃往古昔此山名曰<name type="place">善邊</name>。爾時國土名曰<name type="place">赤馬</name>。于時人民壽二萬歲。當爾之時有佛出世，號曰<name type="person">迦葉如來</name>．應供．正遍知．明行足．善逝．世間解．無上士．調御丈夫．天、人師．佛．世尊，廣為大眾敷演，分別諸法秘奧。其所說者，初、中、後善。其義深遠，其語巧妙，純一無雜，具足清白梵行之相。比丘當知：善邊山名於今已滅，人皆終<app n="fnT02p0489n02">
              <lem wit="【大】">沒</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">歿</rdg>
            </app>沒。彼佛．世尊入般涅槃，人命轉減。以是義故，諸行無常，是變易法。無有住時，不可恃怙，會歸磨滅。是故宜應於諸行所生於止足，厭惡之想，離於愛欲，而求解脫。此山今復名毘富羅，而斯國<app n="fnT02p0489n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">土</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">上</rdg>
            </app>土名<name type="place">摩竭提</name>。是中眾生壽命百年，或增或減。此諸眾生若欲上山，須臾之頃即便往還。我釋迦文出現於世，十號具足，為眾演說無量經典。其所說者，初、中、後善。其義深遠，其語巧妙，純一無雜，具足清白梵行之相。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza350.10">復告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza350.11">此山名字，并及國人不久亦當悉皆滅盡。我亦不久當入涅槃。以是義故，諸行無常，是變易法。無有住時，不可恃怙，會歸磨滅。是故──比丘！──宜應至心，於諸行所生止足想，厭惡之心，離於愛欲，而求解脫。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza350.12">爾時世尊即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza350.13" met="7" xml:id="cg350a">
            <l>婆耆半闍帝彌羅<caesura/>阿毘迦羅朋伽迦</l>
            <l>善邊之山赤馬國<caesura/>毘富羅山摩竭提</l>
            <l>諸山悉滅人亦終<caesura/>佛入涅槃壽命滅</l>
          </lg> 以是義故，諸行無常，是生滅法。生滅滅已，寂滅為樂。</q>
      </div>
      <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0486b" n="0486b"/>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza350">
        <p n="bza350.16">時諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
