<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza331">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0486a18"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza331">
        <p n="bza331.01">如是我聞：一時佛住<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza331">
        <p n="bza331.02">爾時佛告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.03">汝等當知：生死長遠，無有邊際，無有能知其根源者。一切眾生皆為無明之所覆蓋，受結纏縛，流轉生死，無有窮已。過去億若無能知者，譬如恒河，流注四海。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.04">復告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.05">生死長遠，於昔過去受形已來憂悲哭泣，所出目淚為多，為恒河多？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.06">時諸比丘白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza331.07">世尊！如我解佛所說義者，生死長遠，目所出淚，踰彼恒河，亦多四海。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.08">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.09">善哉！善哉！所集目淚，實多四海，誠如汝言。過去、來世父母棄背；伯叔、兄弟、姊妹、兒子、宗親眷屬，悉皆死喪及失錢財；象、馬、牛、羊或受鞭<app n="fnT02p0486n04">
              <lem wit="【大】">杖</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">打</rdg>
            </app>杖，或被傷<app n="fnT02p0486n05">
              <lem wit="【大】">刖</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">割</rdg>
            </app>刖，侵毀形體，乃至繫閉，如斯眾苦，悲惱流淚，不可稱計。譬如<app n="fnT02p0486n06">
              <lem wit="【大】">瀑</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">暴</rdg>
            </app>瀑流，漂眾草木，聚沫塞路，愛之聚沫，遮賢聖道。<app n="fnT02p0486n07">
              <lem wit="【大】">血</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">雨</rdg>
            </app>血<app n="fnT02p0486n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">渧</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">滴</rdg>
            </app>渧受身，數受地獄、餓鬼、畜生及餘惡趣。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.10">佛問比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.11">色為是常，是無常乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.12">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza331.13">色是無常。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.14">佛復問言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.15">色若無常，為當是苦，為非苦耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.16">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza331.17">無常故苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.18">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.19">若無常、苦，是敗壞法，於斯法中賢聖弟子寧計有我及我所不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.20">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza331.21">不也，世尊！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.22">佛又問言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.23">受、想、行、識，為是常耶，是無常乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.24">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza331.25">斯皆無常。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.26">佛又問言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.27">若是無常，為是苦耶，為非苦乎？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.28">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza331.29">無常故苦。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.30">又問：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.31">若無常、苦，是敗壞法，賢聖弟子寧計是中我、我所不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.32">比丘對曰：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhavo">
          <p n="bza331.33">不也，世尊！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza331.34">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza331.35">善哉！善哉！色是無常，無常故苦，苦即無我。若無有我，則無我所。如是知實，正慧觀察。受、想、行、識，亦復如是。是故──比丘！──若有是色，乃至少許，過去、未來、現在；若內若外、若近若遠，此盡無我及以我所。如是稱實，正見所見。若受、想、行、識、若多若少、若內若外、若遠若近、過去、未來、現在，都無有我，亦無我所。如實知見，賢聖弟子見是事已，即名<app n="fnT02p0486n09">
              <lem wit="【大】">多</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】"/>
            </app>多聞。於色解脫，受、想、行、識，亦得解脫。憂、悲、苦、惱，一切解脫。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0486b" n="0486b"/>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza331">
        <p n="bza331.36">佛說是已，諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
