<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza341">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0487c06"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza341">
        <p n="bza341.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">舍衛國</name>
          <name type="place">祇樹給孤獨園</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza341">
        <p n="bza341.02">爾時世尊告諸比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza341.03">生死長遠，……（亦如上說。）</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza341.04">爾時眾中有一比丘，從坐而起，整衣服，合掌向佛，白佛言：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza341.05">世尊！劫為久近？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza341.06">佛告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza341.07">吾可為汝敷演而說，恐汝不解。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza341.08">比丘白佛：</p>
        <q who="bhikkhu">
          <p n="bza341.09">頗可方喻<app n="fnT02p0487n11">
              <lem wit="【大】">說不。佛言。可作方喻</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">使我得知佛告比丘吾今為汝說其方喻諦聽善思佛言比丘譬如</rdg>
            </app>說不？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza341.10">佛言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza341.11">可作方喻，以鐵為城，縱<app n="fnT02p0487n12">
              <lem wit="【大】">橫</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">廣</rdg>
            </app>橫正等，高一由旬。設盛芥子，滿中流溢。假設有人，百年之中取一芥子，城中芥子可得都盡。劫之邊際，不可得知。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza341.12">復告比丘：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <p n="bza341.13">劫之長遠，其喻如是。如斯長劫，百、千、億、萬乃至<app n="fnT02p0487n13">
              <lem wit="【大】">百</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">百千</rdg>
            </app>百億萬，苦惱無量無邊，麁惡痛苦，意所不憙。猶如聚沫，<app n="fnT02p0487n14">
              <lem wit="【大】">血</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【元】【明】">雨</rdg>
            </app>血<app n="fnT02p0486n08">
              <lem wit="【大】">渧</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">滴</rdg>
            </app>渧受身，數受地獄、餓鬼、畜生，惡趣之中人中惡趣。是故應斷後有，宜勤方便，遠離諸有。汝等比丘當作是學。</p>
        </q>
      </div>
      <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0487c" n="0487c"/>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza341">
        <p n="bza341.14">諸比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
