<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          This file is part of the Bieyi za ahan jing 別譯雜阿含經-Project at Dharma Drum
                              Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </title>
        <funder>
          Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會
        </funder>
        <sponsor>
          Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies 中華佛學研究所. Dharma Drum Buddhist
                              College 法鼓佛教研修學院.
        </sponsor>
        <principal>Marcus Bingenheimer</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editing &amp; Encoding:</resp>
          <name>
            Jung Hsi-chin 戎錫琴, Shi Zhanghui 釋章慧, Shu Huiyu 疏惠郁, Wang Ruixiang 王瑞鄉,
                                    Chueh Hui-chen 闕慧貞
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Programming</resp>
          <name>Jen Jou Hung 洪振洲, Marcus Bingenheimer</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <p>
          This is the default header for all files in the database. Files which contain
                              gaiji, however, have an additional CHARDECL section in the ENCODINGDESC below.
        </p>
        <p>
          The project was conducted 2005-2008. Some minor revisions and additions were done
                              in 2009.
        </p>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院.</distributor>
        <date>2005-2009</date>
        <availability>
          <p>
            All texts used with permission. Copyright for the Chinese text lies with the
                                    Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). Copyright for the Pāli
                                    text lies with the Vipassana Research Institute. Copyright for the Sanskrit
                                    text lies with Fumio Enomoto. Copyright for the English text lies with
                                    Marcus Bingenheimer. The Tibetan and Manchu texts are in the public realm.
                                    The digital edition itself is made available under the LGPL.
          </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>If Chinese, the text below is based on the Taishō text from the CBETA-Database
                    (Version Feb.2006). If Pāli, the text base is the VRI Chaṭṭa Saṅgāyana edition
                    (ver.3). If Sanskrit the text base is <bibl>
            Enomoto, Fumio 榎本文雄 (1994): A
                                    comprehensive study of the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama: Indic texts corresponding
                                    to the Chinese Saṃyuktāgama as found in the Sarvāstivāda-Mūlasarvāstivāda
                                    literature. Kyoto: Kacho Junior College
          </bibl>
            and other scholarly
                                publications (as referenced). English translations by Marcus Bingenheimer.
          </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>
          This file has been created in the project "A Digital Comparative Edition of the
                              Bieyi za ahan jing" conducted at the Chung-hwa Institute for Buddhist Studies
                              中華佛學研究所 and the Dharma Drum Buddhist College 法鼓佛教研修學院. The project is funded by
                              the Chiang Ching-kuo Foundation for International Scholarly Exchange
                              蔣經國國際學術交流基金會. The aim of the project is to produce a comparative digital edition
                              and partial translation of the 364 sutras of the BZA and their parallels. The
                              texts are kept in single files in an eXist database and are realized via XQuery
                              and XSLT as HTML for the online user. The project lasts from 2005-2008. For any
                              changes after 2008 see the revision description.
        </p>
      </projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Changes from the respective text base are usually marked with a RESP="t.100"
                              attribute on the containing elements
        </p>
        <p>
          BZA: New Punctuation. Markup of person and place names. Verse and prose.
                              References to the print edition (Taishō). Corrected characters (according to
                              CBETA).
        </p>
        <p>ZA: New Punctuation. Verse and prose. References to the print edition (Taishō).</p>
        <p>
          Other Chinese: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA. Verse and
                              Prose.
        </p>
        <p>
          Pāli, Sanskrit, Tibetan: Parallel and not-parallel divisions regarding the BZA.
                              Verse and Prose. Variant readings.
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body xml:id="bza329">
      <anchor type="start" xml:id="Tp0485a24"/>
      <div type="opening" xml:id="obza329">
        <p n="bza329.01">如是我聞：一時佛在<name type="place">王舍城</name>
          <name type="place">迦蘭陀竹林</name>。</p>
      </div>
      <pb ed="T" xml:id="T02.0100.0485b" n="0485b"/>
      <div type="main" xml:id="mbza329">
        <p n="bza329.02">爾時尊者<name type="person">舍利弗</name>、<name type="person">大目犍連</name>在<name type="place">靈鷲山</name>。時舍利弗新剃髮竟，晨朝早起，正身端坐，以衣覆頭。當于彼時有二夜叉：一名<name type="person">為害</name>，二名<name type="person">復害</name>。爾時復害見舍利弗，語為害言：</p>
        <q who="復害夜叉">
          <p n="bza329.03">我於今者欲以拳打剃頭沙門！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza329.04">為害答言：</p>
        <q who="為害夜叉">
          <p n="bza329.05">而此比丘有大神德。汝勿為此，長夜受苦！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza329.06">第二、第三亦如是諫。復害故欲以拳打舍利弗，以不用其所諫曉故，乃至以身躬自抱捉。爾時復害惡心熾盛，雖聞他諫，乃至抱捉都<app n="fnT02p0485n02">
            <lem wit="【大】">不</lem>
            <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【宋】【元】【明】">無</rdg>
          </app>不從順，即以拳打舍利弗頭。既打之已，復害夜叉語為害言：</p>
        <q who="復害夜叉">
          <p n="bza329.07">今打比丘，便為燒煮於我。汝今應當救拔於我！</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza329.08">作是語時，地自開裂，現身陷入無間地獄。爾時尊者大目<choice>
            <sic>捷</sic>
            <corr resp="CBETA">揵</corr>
          </choice>連去舍利弗坐處不遠，坐一樹下，尋聞打於舍利弗聲，往詣尊者舍利弗所，而語之言：</p>
        <q who="大目揵連">
          <p n="bza329.09">不能堪忍受如是苦，將無驚怖、散壞身耶？</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza329.10">舍利弗言：</p>
        <q who="sariputta">
          <p n="bza329.11">我身忍受，都無<app n="fnT02p0485n03">
              <lem wit="【大】">苦 痛</lem>
              <rdg resp="Taisho" wit="【明】">痛苦</rdg>
            </app>苦痛，亦不散壞。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza329.12">尊者即讚歎言：</p>
        <q who="大目揵連">
          <p n="bza329.13">實有神德！假令復害以手打彼耆闍崛山，猶當碎壞，而舍利弗都無異相。</p>
        </q>
        <p n="bza329.14">斯二尊者作是語時，爾時世尊晝在房坐，以淨天耳遙聞其言，即說偈言：</p>
        <q who="gotamo">
          <lg n="bza329.15" met="5" xml:id="cg329a">
            <l>正心如大山<caesura/>安住無動搖</l>
            <l>諸所可染著<caesura/>染不染著法</l>
            <l>遠離於愛樂<caesura/>所謂愛樂者</l>
            <l>即是塵欲法<caesura/>若來加惱觸</l>
            <l>不報惱觸者<caesura/>是名不惱觸</l>
            <l>若如是修心<caesura/>終不受於苦</l>
          </lg>
        </q>
      </div>
      <div type="closing" xml:id="cbza329">
        <p n="bza329.16">爾時比丘聞佛所說，歡喜奉行。</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
